. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
WELCOME TO THE JUNE 16TH, 2026 REGULAR MEETING OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS .
>> MADAM CLERK, WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL?
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHEN PRESENT SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
PRESENT SUPERVISOR FIELDER FIELDER AND NOT PRESENT
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD PRESENT SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
PRESIDENT MANDEL AND PRESENT SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR
PRESENT SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER PRESENT SUPERVISOR
CHERYL SHERRELL PRESENT SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON
PRESENT AND SUPERVISOR HUANG WONG PRESENT MR. PRESIDENT YOU
HAVE A QUORUM. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS ACKNOWLEDGES THAT
WE ARE ON THE UNCEDED ANCESTRAL HOMELAND OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING WHO ARE THE ORIGINAL INHABITANTS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO PENINSULA. AS THE INDIGENOUS STEWARDS OF
THIS LAND AND IN ACCORDANCE WITH THEIR TRADITIONS THE RAW
MATERIALS WE HAVE NEVER CEDED LOST NOR FORGOTTEN THEIR
RESPONSIBILITIES AS THE CARETAKERS OF THIS PLACE AS
WELL AS FOR ALL PEOPLES WHO RESIDE IN THEIR TRADITIONAL
TERRITORY. AS GUESTS WE RECOGNIZE THAT WE
BENEFIT FROM LIVING AND WORKING ON THEIR TRADITIONAL HOMELANDS
. WE WISH TO PAY OUR RESPECTS BY
ACKNOWLEDGING THE ANCESTORS ELDERS AND RELATIVES OF THE RAW
MATERIAL OWNING COMMUNITY AND BY AFFIRMING THEIR
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS AS FIRST PEOPLES.
COLLEAGUES, WILL YOU JOIN ME IN RECITING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE? I PLEDGE ALLEGIANCE TO THE FLAG
OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND TO THE REPUBLIC FOR WHICH
IT STANDS ONE NATION UNDER GOD INDIVISIBLE WITH LIBERTY
AND JUSTICE. >> ON BEHALF OF OUR BOARD I
WOULD LIKE TO ACKNOWLEDGE THE STAFF AT S.F. GOV TV AND TODAY
THAT IS ESPECIALLY KALEENA MENDOZA.
THEY RECORD EACH OF OUR MEETINGS AND MAKE THE
TRANSCRIPTS AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC ONLINE.
>> MADAM CLERK, DO YOU HAVE ANY COMMUNICATIONS?
YES. THANK YOU.
THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS WELCOMES YOU ALL TO BE PRESENT
IN THE BOARD'S LEGISLATIVE CHAMBER.
AND WHEN YOU'RE UNABLE TO BE HERE YOU CAN WATCH THE
PROCEEDING. IT'S AIRING LIVE ON AS OF G OF
TV'S LOCAL CABLE CHANNEL WHERE YOU CAN CATCH THE LIVE STREAM
AT S.F. GOV TV.ORG. IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SUBMIT
PUBLIC COMMENT IN WRITING YOU CAN DO SO BY SENDING AN EMAIL
TO BOX AT S.F. GOV DOT ORG OR USE THE POSTAL SERVICE.
JUST ADDRESS THE ENVELOPE THE SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS THE NUMBER ONE DR. CARLTON BE GOOD LIT PLACE CITY
HALL ROOM 244 SAN FRANCISCO CALIFORNIA 94102.
>> AND IF YOU NEED TO MAKE A REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION FOR A
FUTURE MEETING UNDER THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES ACT
OR TO REQUEST LANGUAGE ASSISTANCE, JUST CONTACT THE
CLERK'S OFFICE AT LEAST TWO BUSINESS DAYS IN ADVANCE BY
CALLING 4155545 184 AND IN LINE MR. PRESIDENT WITH SUPERVISOR
FIELDER'S APRIL SEVENTH MEMO REQUESTING TO BE EXCUSED FROM
THE BOARD MEETINGS UNTIL JUNE 30TH THE MOTION WOULD BE
IN ORDER TODAY. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. IS THERE EMOTION EXCUSE
SUPERVISOR FIELDER FROM TODAY'S MEETING MOVED BY DORSEY
SECONDED BY CHEN. WE CAN TAKE THAT WITHOUT
OBJECTION. WITHOUT OBJECTION.
SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS EXCUSED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO
APPROVAL OF OUR MEETING MINUTES .
>> YES. APPROVAL OF THE MAY 12TH 2026
BOARD MEETING MINUTES. IS THERE A MOTION TO APPROVE
THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED MOVED BY CHEN?
IS THERE A SECOND SECONDED BY MELGAR?
MADAM CLERK WILL YOU PLEASE CALL THE ROLL ON THE MINUTES AS
PRESENTED SINCE SUPERVISOR FIELDER IS NOT IS THAT EXCUSED
FROM THIS MEETING? SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD YOU WILL BE
FIRST ON ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS AND VOTES.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR MANDEL MAN RIGHT
MANDEL MEN EYES SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR
SADR I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON WALTON EYES
SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHAN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I
THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE MINUTES WILL BE
APPROVED AFTER PUBLIC COMMENT AS PRESENTED MADAM CLERK LET'S
GO TO UNFINISHED BUSINESS PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER ONE
ITEM ONE THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO WAIVE THE COMPETITIVE
SOLICITATION REQUIRED AND UNDER ADMINISTRATIVE CODE CHAPTER 21
G AND TO AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC
WORKS TO RETROACTIVELY ENTER INTO A GRANT AGREEMENT WITH THE
TRANSGENDER DISTRICT IN AN APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF 24,000
FOR THE PURPOSES OF PRINTING AND INSTALLING PLACEMAKING
BANNERS IN THE TRANSGENDER DISTRICT IN THE SOUTHEASTERN
TENDERLOIN AND ALONG SIXTH STREET SOUTH OF MARKET PLEASE
CALL THE ROLL ON ITEM ONE SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR MANDOLIN MANDOLIN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I
SUPERVISOR SHORTER SHORTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I
SUPERVISOR WALTON I WILTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I
SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED MADAM CLERK
PLEASE CALL ITEMS TWO THROUGH FIVE TOGETHER ITEMS TWO THROUGH
FIVE ARE FOR ORDINANCES THAT ADOPT AND IMPLEMENT THE
MEMORANDUM OF UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THE CITY AND THE
FOLLOWING UNIONS FOR ITEM TWO THIS IS WITH THE MUNICIPAL
EXECUTIVES ASSOCIATION FIRE EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH
JUNE 30TH 2030. ITEM THREE THIS IS WITH THE
MUNICIPAL EXECUTIVES ASSOCIATION POLICE TO BE
EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2034.
ITEM FOUR THIS ORDINANCE FIXES COMPENSATION FOR PERSONS
EMPLOYED BY THE CITY AND COUNTY WHOSE COMPENSATION IS SUBJECT
TO THE PROVISIONS OF SECTION 8.409 OF THE CHARTER IN JOB
CODES NOT REPRESENTED BY AN EMPLOYEE ORGANIZATION AND TO
ESTABLISH WORK SCHEDULES AND OTHER TERMS OF CONDITIONS
OF EMPLOYMENT AND METHODS OF PAYMENT EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST,
2026 AND FOUR ITEM FIVE THIS ORDINANCE ADOPTS AND IMPLEMENTS
THE FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE 2024 THROUGH 2027 MEMORANDUM OF
UNDERSTANDING BETWEEN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND THE MACHINISTS
UNION LOCAL 1414 THE INTERNATIONAL ASSOCIATION OF
MACHINISTS AND AEROSPACE WORKERS MACHINISTS AUTOMOTIVE
TRADES DISTRICT LODGE 190. EFFECTIVE JULY 1ST 2026 TO
ADOPT A SIDE LETTER AGREEMENT TO UPDATE THE APPENDIX D
APPRENTICESHIP PROGRAM. >> COLLEAGUES TO TAKE THESE
ITEMS. SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCES ARE FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM SIX.
ITEM SIX IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE PLANNING CODE TO MAKE
ADJUSTMENTS TO THE BALBOA RESERVOIR SPECIAL USE DISTRICT
THAT ALLOW FOR A CONNECTING ELEMENT BETWEEN TWO BUILDINGS
ADJACENT TO SOUTH STREET AND ACROSS FROM THE BRIGHTON
PASEO. TO ESTABLISH CERTAIN DESIGN
PARAMETERS TO AUTHORIZE RESIDENTIAL AND CERTAIN OTHER
USES TO ADOPT A MAXIMUM HEIGHT AT THIS LOCATION TO AFFIRM THE
SIGNAL DETERMINATION AND TO MAKE THE APPROPRIATE FINDINGS.
WILL TAKE THIS SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED. MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM
NUMBER SEVEN ITEM SEVEN THIS ORDINANCE EXEMPTS PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE ON GENEVA AVENUE ASSOCIATED WITH THE AFFORDABLE
HOUSING PROJECT AT 2340 SAN JOSE AVENUE.
TO DEDICATE THIS PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE FOR PUBLIC USE
FOR PUBLIC STREET AND ROADWAY PURPOSES TO ACCEPT THE PUBLIC
INFRASTRUCTURE FOR CITY MAINTENANCE AND LIABILITY
PURPOSES SUBJECT TO SPECIFIED LIMITATIONS TO ESTABLISH
OFFICIAL PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY WIDTH AND STREET GRADE.
TO AMEND ORDINANCE NUMBER 1061 ENTITLED REGULATION A
REGULATING THE WIDTH OF SIDEWALKS TO ESTABLISH OFFICIAL
SIDEWALK WIDTHS ON A PORTION OF GENEVA AVENUE TO ACCEPT A
PUBLIC WORKS ORDER RECOMMENDING VARIOUS ACTIONS REGARDING THE
PUBLIC INFRASTRUCTURE. TO WAIVE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE
CHAPTER 23 AND TO AUTHORIZE AN INTERDEPARTMENTAL TRANSFER OF
CITY PROPERTY FROM THE MAYOR'S OFFICE OF HOUSING AND COMMUNITY
DEVELOPMENT TO PUBLIC WORKS AND TO ADOPT THE APPROPRIATE
FINDINGS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL
WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM NUMBER EIGHT ITEM EIGHT THIS IS
AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE ADMINISTRATIVE CODE TO CREATE
THE DOWNTOWN HOSPITALITY ZONE AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET
DETERMINATIONS. >> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
WITHOUT OBJECTION, THE ORDINANCE IS FINALLY PASSED.
PLEASE CALL ITEM NINE THROUGH 11 TOGETHER ITEMS NINE THROUGH
11 ARE THREE ITEMS THAT PERTAIN TO THE INTERIM BUDGET.
ITEM NINE IS FOR THE PROPOSED INTERIM BUDGET
AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO APPROPRIATE ALL ESTIMATED
RECEIPTS AND EXPENDITURES FOR THE DEPARTMENTS OF THE CITY
AND COUNTY. AS OF MAY 30TH 2026 FOR FISCAL
YEAR ENDING JUNE 30TH 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028 ITEM TEN IS
THE PROPOSED INTERIM ANNUAL SALARY ORDINANCE ENUMERATING
POSITIONS IN THE ANNUAL BUDGET AND APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE FOR
FISCAL YEARS ENDING JUNE 30TH, 2027 AND JUNE 30TH 2028.
TO CONTINUE TO CREATE OR ESTABLISH POSITIONS TO
ENUMERATE AND INCLUDE THEIR IN ALL POSITIONS CREATED BY
CHARTER OR STATE LAW FOR WHICH COMPENSATIONS ARE PAID FROM THE
CITY AND COUNTY FUNDS AND APPROPRIATED IN THE ANNUAL
APPROPRIATION ORDINANCE TO AUTHORIZE APPOINTMENTS FOR
CONTINUATION OF APPOINTMENTS THERE ARE TWO TO SPECIFY
AND FIX THE COMPENSATIONS AND WORK SCHEDULES THEREOF TO
AUTHORIZE APPOINTMENTS TO TEMPORARY POSITIONS AND TO FIX
COMPENSATIONS. AND FOR ITEM 11 THIS RESOLUTION
APPROVES THE FISCAL YEAR INTERIM BUDGET OF THE OFFICE OF
COMMUNITY INVESTMENT AND INFRASTRUCTURE OPERATING AS
THE SUCCESSOR AGENCY TO THE SAN FRANCISCO REDEVELOPMENT AGENCY.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL. WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCES ARE PASSED ON FIRST READING AND THE RESOLUTION IS
ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM NUMBER 12 ITEM 12 THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT APPROVES THE
FIRST AMENDMENT TO THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE CITY
AND COUNTY AND THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
AND HOMELESSNESS. THE CHILDREN'S NETWORK TO
PROVIDE MENTAL HEALTH TREATMENT SERVICES TO EXTEND THE TERM BY
ONE YEAR FROM JUNE 30TH 2026 FOR A NEW TERM OCTOBER 1ST,
2024 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2027 AND TO INCREASE THE AMOUNT BY
APPROXIMATELY 3.2 MILLION FOR A NEW TOTAL AMOUNT OF
APPROXIMATELY 11.8 MILLION THE SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
OUT A NUMBER 13 ITEM 13 THIS RESOLUTION AUTHORIZES THE CITY
AND COUNTY TO ENTER INTO THE FOLLOWING TWO RELATED
AGREEMENTS. DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
WITH THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH CARE SERVICES FOR
REIMBURSEMENT UNDER THE STATE'S MEDI CAL COUNTY INMATE PROGRAM
TO PARTICIPATE IN AN AGREEMENT 26 M.C. IP SAN FRANCISCO DASH
38 AND ADMINISTRATIVE SERVICES AGREEMENT NUMBER 20 6-60140
IN AN APPROXIMATE AMOUNT OF 35,000 TERM JULY 1ST 2026
THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2029 AND TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY TO ASSUME
SOLE FINANCIAL RESPONSIBILITY FOR ANY AND ALL PENALTIES
AND INTEREST CHARGED AS A RESULT OF A FEDERAL AUDIT
DISALLOWANCE RELATED TO THE RENDERING OF SERVICES BY THE
STATE UNDER THE AMC IP SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL.
>> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED.
>> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL ITEM 14.
ITEM 14 THIS IS A RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT A CAPITAL GIFT OF A MOBILE
MAMMOGRAPHY VAN VALUED AT 1.5 MILLION FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO
GENERAL HOSPITAL FOUNDATION FOR USE BY THE ZUCKERBERG SAN
FRANCISCO GENERAL HOSPITAL AND TRAUMA CENTER TO BE
PURCHASED WITH A CASH DONATION OF 1.6 MILLION FROM SALESFORCE
INC IN CONSIDERATION FOR AN AGREEMENT TO NAME THE MOBILE
MAMMOGRAPHY VAN Z AS F G MAMA VAN SALES FORCE IN PARTNERSHIP
WITH Z AS OF G AND Z F G H F FOR A HEALTHY COMMUNITY JANUARY
1ST 2027 THROUGH DECEMBER 31ST 2040 ONE.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 15.
>> ITEM 15 THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT AUTHORIZES THE DEPARTMENT
OF PUBLIC HEALTH TO ACCEPT AND EXPEND A $3.75 MILLION
GRANT FROM FUNDS FROM THE HOMES FOR THE HOMELESS FUND LLC, A
WHOLLY OWNED SUBSIDIARY OF THE HOUSING ACCELERATOR FUND FOR
PARTICIPATION IN A PROGRAM ENTITLED PLACEMENT SOLUTIONS
FOR PATIENTS AND TENANTS WHOSE NEEDS EXCEED CURRENT PSC AGE
CAPACITY. >> TO APPROVE THE GRANT
AGREEMENT FOR THE PURPOSES OF TRANSFORMING THE CARE PROVIDES
TO PATIENTS JULY 1ST, 2026 THROUGH JUNE 30TH 2028 FOR A
TOTAL NOT TO EXCEED AMOUNT OF 3.75 MILLION.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED PLEASE CALL ITEM 16 ITEM 16 THIS IS A
RESOLUTION TO AUTHORIZE AND DIRECT THE EXECUTIVE
DIRECTOR OF THE TREASURE ISLAND DEVELOPMENT AUTHORITY OR THEIR
DESIGNEE TO PREPARE AN APPENDIX TO THE INFRASTRUCTURE FINANCING
PLAN FOR THE ANNEXATION OF PROPERTY TO THE CITY AND COUNTY
SAN FRANCISCO INFRASTRUCTURE AND REVITALIZATION FINANCING
DISTRICT NUMBER ONE AS A NEW PROJECT AREA AND DETERMINING
OTHER MATTERS IN CONNECTION THEREWITH.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED. >> MADAM CLERK, PLEASE CALL
ITEM 17 ITEM 17 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND THE SAN
FRANCISCO FIRE CODE TO PROHIBIT THE SALE OFFER AND DELIVERY OF
LITHIUM ION BATTERIES AND REPLACEMENT LITHIUM
AND LITHIUM ION BATTERIES THAT DO NOT MEET SPECIFIED
CERTIFICATION REQUIREMENTS TO ANY ADDRESS WITHIN SAN
FRANCISCO TO ESTABLISH ENFORCEMENT PROCESSES
AND PENALTIES FOR VIOLATIONS. TO AUTHORIZE THE CITY ATTORNEY
TO SEEK INJUNCTIVE AND MONETARY RELIEF AND AN ATTORNEY'S FEES
AND TO AUTHORIZE THE FIRE DEPARTMENT TO IMPLEMENT THE
RESTRICTION THROUGH RULES FORMS AND GUIDANCE.
>> SAME HOUSE, SAME CALL WITHOUT OBJECTION THE ORDINANCE
IS PASSED ON FIRST READING MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL ITEM 18
ITEM 18 THIS IS AN ORDINANCE TO AMEND DIVISION ONE OF THE
TRANSPORTATION CODE TO MAKE NON SUBSTANTIVE ORGANIZATIONAL
CHANGES TO THE PROVISIONS GOVERNED GOVERNING THE
INTERDEPARTMENTAL STAFF COUNCIL ON TRAFFIC AND TRANSPORTATION
AND TO REMOVE OUTDATED PROVISIONS CONCERNING THE
TEMPORARY USE OF STREETS FOR SCHOOL USES TO AMEND THE
ADMINISTRATIVE AND FIRE CODES TO UPDATE CROSS-REFERENCES
AND TO AFFIRM THE SECRET DETERMINATION SAME HOUSE, SAME
CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
ORDINANCE IS PASSED ON FIRST READING AND I WOULD NOTE THAT
WE HAVE BEEN JOINED BY A FORMER MEMBER OF THIS BODY FORMER PUC
GENERAL MANAGER AND CURRENT AIRPORT COMMISSIONER SUSAN LAO
. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO TO A
ROLL CALL. >> YES.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD, YOU WOULD BE FIRST UP TO INTRODUCE NEW
BUSINESS. >> COLLEAGUES I THINK WE CAN
ALL AGREE THAT EVERY SAN FRANCISCAN SHOULD BE ABLE TO
BUY GROCERIES AND PICK UP PRESCRIPTIONS CLOSE TO HOME.
IT'S A BASIC EXPECTATION. AND YET IN TOO MANY OF OUR
COMMUNITIES WE'RE NO LONGER MEETING IT.
>> GROCERY PRICES ARE UP. MILK IS UP 13%.
TOMATOES ARE UP 40% OVER LAST YEAR.
>> AND AT THE SAME TIME THAT FAMILIES ARE STRETCHED THIN ON
FOOD COSTS, THE BUILDINGS THAT USED TO HOUSE THEIR
NEIGHBORHOOD GROCERY STORE OR PHARMACY ARE SITTING EMPTY
OFTEN FOR YEARS WITH NO PLAN TO REOPEN.
SAN FRANCISCO NOW HAS MULTIPLE FOOD DESERTS AS A RESULT.
>> AND THE TWO PROBLEMS COMPOUND EACH OTHER.
LESS ACCESS AND HIGHER PRICES WHERE ACCESS DOES EXIST.
>> LAST WEEK I INTRODUCED THE FIRST TWO PIECES OF THE
AFFORDABLE GROCERIES ACT THE ABANDONED PHARMACY AND GROCERY
TAX WHICH WOULD GO TO VOTERS IN NOVEMBER.
CREATES ACCOUNTABILITY FOR LARGE CORPORATIONS THAT LEAVE
FORMER GROCERY AND PHARMACY STOREFRONTS VACANT AND ZOMBIE
STORES FOR EXTENDED PERIODS OF TIME.
>> INTENTIONALLY KEEPING THESE PARCELS VACANT TO BLOCK
COMPETITION BECAUSE FRANKLY VACANT STORES DON'T FEED
FAMILIES AND EMPTY PHARMACIES DON'T FILL PRESCRIPTIONS.
>> THE SECOND MEASURE THE AFFORDABLE GROCERY FUND
ESTABLISHES A DEDICATED CITY FUND TO INVEST IN REAL
SOLUTIONS. >> THE POSSIBLE THESE INCLUDE
HELPING CORNER STORES CONVERT INTO FULL GROCERY MARKETS LIKE
THE HEALTHY RETAIL S.F. PROGRAM SUPERVISOR JIM KIM STARTED MANY
YEARS AGO. >> IT COULD ENABLE THE CITY TO
ACQUIRE VACANT BUILDINGS AND LEASE THEM AFFORDABLY TO
GROCERS WHO COMMIT TO KEEPING PRICES LOW LIKE MAYOR MAMDANI
IS DOING IN NEW YORK. OR WE COULD PROVIDE GRANTS
AND LOANS FOR NONPROFIT AND WORKER OWNED CO-OP GROCERY
OPERATORS. A SIMPLE CONDITION FOR ALL
THESE IS THAT THEY RUN THROUGH ALL OF IT AS A PUBLIC DOLLARS
THAT SUPPORT A STORE. AFFORDABILITY SHOWS UP AT THE
REGISTER. >> TODAY I'M ANNOUNCING TWO
ADDITIONAL COMPONENTS OF THIS PACKAGE THAT MY OFFICE WILL BE
PURSUING IF THESE PASS IN NOVEMBER.
THE FIRST IS A GROSS RECEIPTS TAX CREDIT FOR PHARMACIES
OPERATING IN SAN FRANCISCO TO PROVIDE AN INCENTIVE FOR NEW
PHARMACIES TO OPEN AND OPERATE HERE.
THIS IS A CARROT TO COMPLEMENT THE TAXES STICK A CONCRETE
FINANCIAL INCENTIVE TO MAKE SAN FRANCISCO MORE ATTRACTIVE FOR
PHARMACY OPERATORS CONSIDERING NEW LOCATIONS OR WEIGHING
WHETHER TO STAY. AND SECOND, ESTABLISHING AN
AFFORDABLE GROSS'S WORKING GROUP AN ADVISORY BODY TO GUIDE
IMPLEMENTATION AND HOLD THE CITY ACCOUNTABLE TO OUTCOMES ON
THE GROUND. ALL OF THESE PIECES OF
LEGISLATION THE GOAL IS STRAIGHTFORWARD.
LESS BLIGHT AND MORE GROCERIES, MORE PHARMACIES, MORE FRESH
FOOD IN EVERY NEIGHBORHOOD. NO SAN FRANCISCANS SHOULD HAVE
TO TRAVEL ACROSS THE CITY JUST TO PICK UP A PRESCRIPTION OR TO
FIND AN AFFORDABLE HEAD OF LETTUCE.
>> THANK YOU TO DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEYS BRAD RASSI, SCOTT
REIBER AND CHARLES OLSON WHO TOOK THESE CONCEPTS AND BUILT
THEM INTO A LEGISLATIVE PACKAGE READY FOR THE VOTERS AS WELL AS
LISA GLUCKSTEIN FROM PLANNING LAUREL CARAVAN DE JUSTICE FROM
WDIV. AMANDA FRIED AND ERIC MUNKY
FROM THE TREASURER AND TAX COLLECTOR FOR PROVIDING
FEEDBACK AND MAKING THESE MEASURES SMARTER AND STRONGER.
AS WELL AS SAM LOGAN, MY CHIEF OF STAFF FOR SHEPHERDING THE
PACKAGE FROM CONCEPT TO INTRODUCTION, I ALSO WANT TO
THANK MY CO-SPONSORS SUPERVISOR MELGAR CHERYL SAUTER AND CHEN
AND OUR COALITION PARTNERS INCLUDING U OF S.W. SEIU LOCAL
87 FARMING FARMING HOPE BOOKER T WASHINGTON AND THE FOOD
AND AGRICULTURAL ACTION COALITION TOWARD SOVEREIGNTY
COALITION. >> I LOOK FORWARD TO THE
BOARD'S SUPPORT AND TO BRINGING THIS TO VOTERS IN NOVEMBER.
>> SECOND COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM INTRODUCING AN ORDINANCE THAT
WILL ALLOW FOR BUILDERS TO TAKE FULL ADVANTAGE OF THE BUILDING
CODE WHEN IT COMES TO INCLUDING MEZZANINE, MEZZANINE OR SPACES
BETWEEN FLOORS OF A BUILDING THAT DO NOT TAKE UP THE FULL
FOOTPRINT OF A BUILDING USUALLY SITUATED ABOVE A PORTION OF THE
GROUND FLOOR. THEY ALLOW FOR BUILDINGS TO
HAVE HIGH CEILINGS IN ONE PART OF A SPACE WHILE ALLOWING FOR
MORE FOCUSED SPACE IN A SMALL PORTION OF THE BUILDING.
UNDER THE BUILDING CODE THOUGH, MEZZANINE CAN BE UP TO 50% OF
THE AREA OF THE FLOOR BELOW SO LONG AS THE SPACE HAS PROPER
SPRINKLERS. >> THE PLANNING CODE, HOWEVER,
HAS A DIFFERENT RULE. IT LIMITS MEZZANINE TO JUST ONE
THIRD OF THE FOOTPRINT. >> THIS IS DESPITE THE FACT
THAT EXPERTS WHO COMPILE THE BUILDING CODE HAVE NO LIFE
SAFETY ISSUES WITH A BIGGER MEZZANINE.
THIS MEANS IF YOU WANT TO BUILD A BUILDING WITH THREE STORIES
AND A MEZZANINE BIGGER THAN ONE THIRD THE SIZE OF THE FLOOR
THAT COUNTS AS A THREE STOREY BUILDING UNDER THE BUILDING
CODE BUT A FOUR STORY BUILDING AND THE PLANNING CODE.
THIS CONFLICT LED TO CONFUSION FOR A PROJECT IN DISTRICT FIVE
WHERE A MEZZANINE WAS COUNTED AS A FLOOR DURING CODE REVIEW.
ANY SORT OF DELAY AND AMBIGUITY CAN COST TIME FOR PROJECTS
IN THIS AMBIGUITY MAY LEAD TO ARCHITECTS NOT TAKING FULL
ADVANTAGE OF THE TOOLS AT THEIR ARSENAL TO MAXIMIZE USABLE
SPACE AND OUR DENSITY. FOR SOME PROJECTS THE EXTRA
FLOOR THAT THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT COUNTS COULD HAVE
CASCADING EFFECTS ON THE USES ALLOWED IN THE FINAL BUILDING.
SO THIS LEGISLATION WILL BRING THE TWO CODES INTO ALIGNMENT.
CLEANING UP ANY CONFUSION AND ALLOWING FOR MORE USABLE
SPACE IN OUR NEW CONSTRUCTION BUILDINGS WITHOUT JEOPARDIZING
SAFETY. THANK YOU TO DEPUTY CITY
ATTORNEY ROB KAPLAN, RACHEL COOPER AND MY TEAM FOR WORKING
ON THIS AS WELL AS LISA GLUCKSTEIN AND ELIZABETH GORDON
JUNKER FROM THE PLANNING DEPARTMENT FOR THEIR INPUT.
ALSO THANKS TO GILLIAN ALLEN, BRIAN HARDY AND REZA CUSHION OF
ONION FOR BRINGING THIS SUBJECT TO OUR ATTENTION.
COLLEAGUES, I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT FOR THIS LEGISLATION
THAT TAKES THE BUILDING AND PLANNING CODE HARMONIZATION
TO ANOTHER LEVEL OR AT LEAST ON ANOTHER MEZZANINE.
>> THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD. >> SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN THANK
YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES I'M ASKING THAT WE
ADJOURN TODAY'S MEETING IN MEMORY OF MICHAEL FRANK RICE
WHO PREVIOUSLY SERVED AS THE PRESIDENT OF THE GLEN PARK
ASSOCIATION AND MICHAEL DIED ON MAY 31ST AT THE AGE OF 79.
MICHAEL WAS BORN IN 1947 IN PARIS, FRANCE.
>> HIS FATHER JAMES WAS A SOCIAL WORKER SENT OVERSEAS TO
HELP RESETTLE JEWISH HOLOCAUST SURVIVORS IN AUSTRIA.
HE AND HIS FAMILY, HIS PARENTS AND HIS OLDER BROTHER MOVED
FROM PARIS. THEN TO SWITZERLAND, THEN TO
GERMANY BEFORE ULTIMATELY RETURNING TO THE UNITED STATES
AND SETTLING SETTLING IN EAST CHESTER, NEW YORK.
MICHAEL FOLLOWED HIS BROTHER TO BOWDOIN COLLEGE IN MAINE
INITIALLY STUDYING CHEMISTRY. HOWEVER, AN AVID READER
AND TALENTED WRITER, HE SOON REALIZED HIS INTERESTS LAY
ELSEWHERE AND SWITCHED HIS MAJOR TO ART HISTORY.
>> AFTER GRADUATING HE WENT ON TO EARN A MASTER'S IN URBAN
PLANNING AT THE UNIVERSITY OF MICHIGAN, ACCORDING TO HIS WIFE
JANE. >> MICHAEL LOVED BIG CITIES
AND LIKE NOTHING BETTER THAN FIGURING OUT A NEW PUBLIC
TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM. IN 1972 HE PACKED HIS THINGS
INTO HIS YELLOW TOYOTA COROLLA AND DROVE ACROSS ACROSS THE
COUNTRY FROM PROVIDENCE, RHODE ISLAND TO SAN FRANCISCO.
TWO YEARS LATER HE MET JANE WHO HAD SIMILARLY TO HER BELONGINGS
INTO HER VW BUG AND MOVED FROM LOS ANGELES TO SAN FRANCISCO.
THE COUPLE MARRIED IN 1977. THE FOLLOWING YEAR THEY
WELCOMED THEIR FIRST SON JOEL AND THEIR SECOND SON NATHAN
IN 1980. >> THE YOUNG FAMILY LIVED
BRIEFLY IN THE CASTRO AND BERNAL HEIGHTS BEFORE
SETTLING IN GLEN PARK. AFTER MOVING TO THE
NEIGHBORHOOD, MICHAEL ATTENDED A FATEFUL GLEN PARK ASSOCIATION
MEETING WHERE HE PARTICIPATED IN A DEBATE ABOUT THE PROPOSED
REBUILDING OF THE DEYOUNG MUSEUM, WHICH HAD BEEN
CRITICALLY DAMAGED BY THE 1989 LOMA PRIETA EARTHQUAKE.
MICHAEL, WHO HAD WRITTEN COUNTLESS ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT
REPORTS FOR PROJECTS INVOLVING ORACLE PARK, THE ACADEMY OF
SCIENCES, GOLDEN GATE PARK MISSION BAY AND MORE WAS WELL
SPOKEN AND CLEARLY KNOWLEDGEABLE.
>> HE IMMEDIATELY CAUGHT THE ATTENTION OF ZOLAN NORDSTROM,
THEN PRESIDENT OF THE GLEN PARK ASSOCIATION WHO INVITED HIM TO
JOIN AND TOLD HIM HE WOULD BE PERFECT AS THE NEXT PRESIDENT.
>> SO ANSWER TURNED OUT TO BE CORRECT.
MICHAEL WENT ON TO SERVE AS PRESIDENT OF THE GLEN PARK
ASSOCIATION FOR 12 YEARS AND HIS EXPERTISE, CARE
AND THOUGHTFUL LEADERSHIP HELPED SHAPED GLEN PARK INTO
THE NEIGHBORHOOD IT IS TODAY WHICH I WOULD NOTE HAS BEEN
RECOGNIZED AS ONE OF THE 40 COOLEST NEIGHBORHOODS IN THE
WORLD BY TIMEOUT MAGAZINE AFTER THE DIMOND SUPERMARKET BURNED
DOWN IN 1998. SIX YEARS OF CONTENTIOUS DEBATE
FOLLOWED AS PEOPLE SPARRED OVER HOW THE SITE SHOULD BE
REDEVELOPED. >> GLEN PARK A MAJORITY OF GLEN
PARK NEIGHBORS FAVORED A PROPOSAL TO BUILD A SUPERMARKET
WITH A LIBRARY ON THE SECOND FLOOR AND ADD 15 UNITS OF
HOUSING. >> DESPITE THE NEIGHBORHOOD'S
OVERALL SUPPORT, A SMALL GROUP FOUGHT TO BLOCK THIS PROJECT AT
EVERY TURN. CIRCULATING DOCTORED IMAGES OF
THE PROPOSAL AND EXPLOITING THE CITY'S CONVOLUTED BUREAUCRATIC
PROCESSES. THIS MAY SOUND FAMILIAR TO
MEMBERS OF THIS BOARD, HOWEVER MICHAEL, WHO HAS STUDIED EVERY
LAWSUIT ENVIRONMENTAL IMPACT REPORT AND CITY DOCUMENT
PERSISTED IN PUSHING THE PROJECT THROUGH.
HIS DILIGENCE PAID OFF AND TODAY THAT AREA IS HOME TO
THE CANYON MARKET AND THE GLEN PARK LIBRARY WHICH HAVE BECOME
BELOVED FIXTURES IN GLEN PARK. AMONG MICHAEL'S MANY OTHER
ACCOMPLISHMENTS WERE HELPING TRANSFORM AN OVERGROWN STRIP OF
LAND INTO THE GLEN PARK GREENWAY A LUSH THREE BLOCK
CORRIDOR THAT REMAINS A SOURCE OF NEIGHBORHOOD PRIDE.
WORKING WITH THEN SUPERVISOR KEVIN DUFTY TO SECURE LONGER
PARKING LIMITS NEAR GLEN CANYON PARK MAKING IT EASIER FOR
FAMILIES AND VISITORS TO ENJOY THE AREA AND PRESERVING GLEN
PARK'S HISTORY THROUGH THE ARCHIVING AND DIGITIZATION OF
HISTORIC NEIGHBORHOOD NEWSPAPERS.
MICHAEL EVENTUALLY LEFT SAN FRANCISCO TO BE CLOSER TO HIS
GRANDCHILDREN BUT EVEN AFTER MOVING AWAY HE REMAINED
CONNECTED TO THE NEIGHBORHOOD AND TO THE CITY.
STAYING INFORMED ABOUT NEIGHBORHOOD ISSUES AND KEEPING
IN TOUCH WITH COMMUNITY LEADERS UNTIL THE END RESIDENTS
NEIGHBORHOOD LEADERS AND CITY OFFICIALS INCLUDING ME REMEMBER
HIM AS A GENTLE LEADER, RESOURCEFUL, DETERMINED
AND ABLE TO REMAIN CALM AND RESPECTFUL NO MATTER HOW
CONTENTIOUS THE CIRCUMSTANCES. REST IN PEACE MICHAEL RICE.
MAY YOUR MEMORY BE A BLESSING. >> THE REST I SUBMIT.
THANK YOU, MR. PRESIDENT. LET'S DO ONE MORE.
THAT WOULD BE SUPERVISOR MELGAR .
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM FORMALLY
INTRODUCING ALONG WITH OUR BUDGET CHAIR SUPERVISOR CONNIE
CHAN A MOTION TO DIRECT THE BUDGET AND LEGISLATIVE ANALYSTS
TO COLLABORATE WITH A COMPTROLLER'S TEAM TO CONDUCT A
PERFORMANCE AND MANAGEMENT AUDIT OF THE ACADEMY OF
SCIENCES. THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCES IS A
DISTRICT SEVEN INSTITUTION LOCATED IN OUR CROWN JEWEL FOUR
REC AND PARK GOLDEN GATE PARKS. THE ACADEMY RECEIVED A GENERAL
FUND ALLOCATION OF $8.1 MILLION IN FISCAL YEAR 2526 AND THERE
IS A PROPOSAL FOR AN INCREASE IN THE MAYOR'S BUDGET IN FISCAL
YEAR 2627. WE ARE DEEPLY TROUBLED BY THE
PRESENT FINANCIAL HEALTH OF THIS INSTITUTION WHICH HAS LED
TO 50 THREE WORKERS BEING LAID OFF EARLIER THIS YEAR ALONG
WITH AN UNMANAGED FINANCIAL DEFICIT AND QUESTIONABLE DEBT
REFINANCING PRACTICES. >> THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCES IS
AN IMPORTANT INSTITUTION, NOT JUST FOR SAN FRANCISCO BUT
BECAUSE OF ITS MISSION TO ADVANCE THE SCIENCES
AND CONSERVATION ESPECIALLY DURING A TIME OF FEDERAL
ATTACKS ON BOTH THE ENVIRONMENT AND SCIENCES.
SIMILAR TO THE ZOO, THE CITY ALSO HAS A MAJOR STAKE IN THE
ACADEMY AND IT BEHOOVES US TO ENSURE THAT IT IS FOLLOWING
BEST PRACTICES AND THAT IT IS FINANCIALLY SUSTAINABLE.
>> I WANT TO THANK THE WORKERS WHO ORGANIZED INTO A UNION LAST
YEAR AND HAVE BEEN RINGING THE ALARM BELLS FOR SOME TIME
AND FOR THEIR DEDICATION TO THE MISSION OF THE ACADEMY'S WORK.
I HOPE THAT THE FINDINGS OF THIS AUDIT AND THE
RECOMMENDATIONS PURDUE WILL PROVIDE US WITH A MAP FORWARD
TO ENSURE THAT THERE IS STRONGER FINANCIAL MANAGEMENT
THAT WE HAVE THE PROPER OVERSIGHT AND CAN PROVIDE
SUPPORT TO THIS VERY IMPORTANT INSTITUTION.
I AM ALSO SUBMITTING IN IN MEMORIAM FOR PHOEBE LEE.
>> I AM SADDENED TO SHARE THAT PHOEBE LEE PASSED AWAY AT THE
AGE OF 88 IN HER DISTRICT SEVEN HOME IN GOLDEN GATE HEIGHTS.
I HONORED WE ALL HONORED PHOEBE LAST YEAR DURING A SPECIAL
COMMENDATION FOR HER CONTRIBUTIONS SUPPORTING
CHINESE ARTS AND CULTURE. PHOEBE LEE WAS A TALENTED
MARTIAL ARTIST STORYTELLER AND THE ELDEST SISTER OF BRUCE
LEE, AN INTERNATIONAL LEGEND BORN IN CHINESE HOSPITAL.
FOR THE PAST FEW DECADES MISLEADS DEVOTED HER TIME TO
SHARING THE INCREDIBLE STORY OF HERSELF AND HER FAMILY.
SHE WAS ALSO THE HONORARY CHAIRMAN OF THE BRUCE LEE CLUB
FOUNDED TO COMMEMORATE HIS LIFE.
MOUSLEY SPENT HER LIFE BUILDING A THE BRIDGES BETWEEN DIVERSE
COMMUNITIES AND SHARING HER CULTURE AND HER STORY INCLUDING
HER FAMILY STORY. HER WORK HAS INSPIRED FUTURE
GENERATIONS OF SAN FRANCISCANS AND FOR THAT WE SHOULD ALL BE
IMMENSELY GRATEFUL. MS..
LEE WAS AN INSPIRATION AND EVEN IN HER FINAL YEARS WOULD GRACE
ANYONE THAT MET HER. WITH HER MARTIAL ARTS MOVES
AND ALSO CANTONESE OPERA, SHE WAS ALWAYS REMINDING THOSE OF
US AROUND HER ABOUT THE POWER OF MOVEMENT AND REFLECTION.
TO THE LEE FAMILY ESPECIALLY HER BROTHER ROBERT AND ALL THE
FRIENDS SHE HAS MADE THROUGHOUT HER LIFE HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO
WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST CONSOLE CONDOLENCES.
I WOULD ALSO LIKE TO CLOSE TODAY'S MEETING IN HER MEMORY
ALONG WITH SUPERVISOR SHYANNE CHEN WHO ALSO WOULD LIKE TO SAY
A FEW WORDS WHEN WE REVISE OUR AGENDA.
THE REST I SUBMIT. THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR MELGAR. THANK YOU MADAM CARD.
>> THANK YOU SUPERVISOR MGR FOR HONORING MS..
PHOEBE LEE AS AN OLDER SISTER OF BRUCE LEE.
SHE BROUGHT IMMENSE WARM AND LEADERSHIP TO OUR
COMMUNITY. I HAD THE PLEASURE OF MEETING
MS. FOUR BAILEY DURING AN EVENT WHERE SHE WAS PROMOTING CHINESE
CULTURE AND ARTS. HER PASSION FOR CULTURAL
PRESERVATION LEFT HER DEEP IN MY IMPRESSIONS ON ME.
>> THROUGH THE LEE'S CLUB SHE SHARED RARE AND VARIED PERSONAL
INSIGHT WITH THE WORLD ABOUT HER BROTHER OBVIOUSLY FROM
THEIR CHILDHOOD DAYS IN HONG KONG WHERE LAUGHTER WAS VIEWED
IN THEIR HOME TO HONORING BRUCE LEE'S LEGACY AFTER HE PASSED.
REST IN PEACE PHOEBE LEE AND FOR BILLY SORRY AND THE
REST I THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR CHEN.
>> MR. PRESIDENT. ALL RIGHT, LET'S GO TO OUR 2:30
P.M. SPECIAL ORDER. >> YES, THE 2:30 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDER IS THE RECOGNITION OF COMMON DONATIONS FOR
MERITORIOUS SERVICE TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
>> AND TODAY WE'RE GOING TO START WITH BARBARA HALE.
>> COME ON UP OUR. >> I DON'T KNOW WHAT WE'RE
GOING TO DO WITHOUT YOU. >> OH.
TODAY I AM HONORED TO PRESENT A SPECIAL COMMENDATION TO BARBARA
HALE, THE SAN FRANCISCO PUBLIC UTILITIES COMMISSION'S
ASSISTANT GENERAL MANAGER FOR POWER WHO WILL BE RETIRING AT
THE END OF THIS MONTH AFTER MORE THAN 21 YEARS OF SERVICE
TO THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO.
THE SPOKES POWER ENTERPRISE MANAGES SAN FRANCISCO'S PUBLIC
ELECTRICITY PROGRAMS SERVING NEARLY 400,000 HOMES
AND BUSINESSES ACROSS THE CITY. FROM STREET LIGHTS AND MUNI
BUSSES TO HOSPITALS, SCHOOLS AND AFFORDABLE HOUSING.
WHEN BARBARA ARRIVED AT THE SFO IN 2000 FOR A HIRED BY GENERAL
MANAGER SUSAN LASALLE WAVES SUSAN LAIL.
>> THERE SHE IS. LITTLE APPLAUSE FOR SUSAN LOYAL
MAKING A GOOD HIRE. >> THE ENTERPRISE DID NOT
EXIST. SHE BUILT IT.
SHE GREW UP IN SONOMA COUNTY, ONE OF EIGHT CHILDREN.
HER FATHER WAS A MIDDLE SCHOOL TEACHER WITH A DEEP COMMITMENT
TO FAIRNESS AND AN INCLUSIVE WORLDVIEW OF VALUES THAT HE
PASSED ON TO HIS DAUGHTER. >> BARBARA EARNED A SCHOLARSHIP
TO SANTA ROSA JUNIOR COLLEGE, TRANSFERRED TO SAN FRANCISCO
STATE UNIVERSITY AND GRADUATED WITH A DEGREE IN ECONOMICS
BEFORE JOINING THE CITY. BARBARA HAD ALREADY BUILT A
DISTINGUISHED RECORD AT THE CALIFORNIA PUBLIC UTILITIES
COMMISSION. RISING THROUGH PROGRESSIVELY
MORE SENIOR ROLES AS ANALYST ADVISER TO THE PRESIDENT,
ADMINISTRATIVE LAW JUDGE AND DIRECTOR OF STRATEGIC
PLANNING. AS I SAID, SUZANNE, THEY ALL
RECRUITED HER IN 2004 TO LEAD THE AGENCY'S NEWLY FORMED POWER
ENTERPRISE. BARBARA WAS ITS FIRSTS AND TO
THIS DAY HAS BEEN THE UK'S ONLY ASSISTANT GENERAL MANAGER FOR
POWER. HER SIGNATURE ACHIEVEMENT IS
CLEAN POWER S.F. SAN FRANCISCO'S PUBLIC CLEAN ENERGY
PROGRAM WHICH SHE LAUNCHED IN 2016.
UNDER HER LEADERSHIP IT GREW FROM ROUGHLY 7800 ACCOUNTS TO
MORE THAN 385,000 AND IT NOW ACCOUNTS FOR 75% OF ALL
ELECTRICITY CONSUMED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
BY 2023 IT WAS DELIVERING 100% RENEWABLE ELECTRICITY
ELECTRICITY TO EVERY ONE OF ITS CUSTOMERS.
REACHING THAT MILESTONE TWO YEARS BEFORE THE PROGRAM'S OWN
TARGET OVER ITS TEN YEAR HISTORY CLEAN POWER S.F. HAS
SAVED CUSTOMERS MORE THAN $146 MILLION ON THEIR ENERGY BILLS
COMPARED TO P, G AND E RATES. BARBARA ALSO CREATED GO SOLAR
S.F. THE CITY'S ROOFTOP SOLAR INCENTIVE PROGRAM WHICH SINCE
2008 HAS DISTRIBUTED NEARLY $30 MILLION AND PUT NEARLY 6000
SOLAR INSTITUTIONS ON ROOFTOPS ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO.
UNDER HER LEADERSHIP THE SFP HAS ALSO BUILT AND NOW OPERATES
30 ROOFTOP SOLAR SYSTEMS ON MUNICIPAL BUILDINGS ACROSS THE
CITY. BARBARA'S INFLUENCE EXTENDS
WELL BEYOND SAN FRANCISCO. SHE HELPED FOUND THE CALIFORNIA
COMMUNITY CHOICE ASSOCIATION AND SERVED AS ITS FIRST
PRESIDENT. TURNING SAN FRANCISCO'S
EXPERIENCE INTO A MODEL FOR PUBLIC CLEAN ENERGY PROGRAMS
ACROSS THE STATE. SHE'S ALSO BEEN A LONGSTANDING
BOARD MEMBER OF THE ASSOCIATION OF WOMEN IN WATER ENERGY
AND ENVIRONMENT. OPENING DOORS FOR WOMEN IN A
FIELD WHERE THEY REMAIN UNDER REPRESENTED WHAT BARBARA HALE
LEAVES BEHIND IS SOMETHING SAN FRANCISCO DID NOT HAVE BEFORE
SHE ARRIVED A WORLD CLASS PUBLIC POWER PROGRAM.
THAT'S THE CITY AND ITS RESIDENTS WILL DEPEND ON FOR
GENERATIONS. BARBARA ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD
OF SUPERVISORS AND THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO, WE
ARE GRATEFUL. DEEPLY, DEEPLY GRATEFUL FOR
YOUR 21 YEARS OF PUBLIC SERVICE.
WE CONGRATULATE YOUR HUSBAND, YOUR TWO DAUGHTERS AND ALL YOUR
FAMILY ON YOUR WELL-EARNED RETIREMENT AND WE WISH YOU ALL
THE BEST IN THE YEARS AHEAD. I HAVE AT LEAST ONE OF MY
COLLEAGUES WHO WANTS TO SPEAK AND I ALSO HAVE THE FORMER
GENERAL MANAGER OF THE PUC. AND LET'S TAKE SUPERVISOR CHAN
FIRST AND THEN JEN AND THEN COMMISSIONER LEO.
>> THANK YOU, PRESIDENT MENDHAM AND OF COURSE BARBARA IS
AMAZING AND I HAVE LEARNED EVERYTHING THAT I WOULD KNOW
AND EVER KNOW ABOUT LIKE PUBLIC POWER, MUNICIPAL POWER BUT ALSO
JUST HOW EVERYTHING WORKS IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND I'M REALLY PROUD OF OUR GRATEFUL.
AS A TWO SURVIVOR, SOPHIE MAXWELL, YOU'VE BEEN FOR ME AS
AN AIDE TO HER WHO REALLY UNDER HER LEADERSHIP SHE WAS THINKING
ABOUT MY POWER PLANS IN HER DISTRICT AND SO MUCH MORE.
YOU WALK ME THROUGH YOU WALK HER THROUGH THOSE ISSUES.
WE'RE JUST IN AND TO UNDERSTAND THE TECHNICAL ASPECT OF IT BUT
TO ALSO VERY MUCH MINDFUL AND RESPECTFUL OF NOT JUST
ELECTED LEADERSHIP BUT ALSO THE COMMUNITY.
I THINK THAT'S REALLY THE CRITICAL PIECE THAT YOU DIDN'T
JUST BRING A BROADER CRADDICK POINT OF VIEW TO THIS DYNAMIC
AND TO THE POWER STRUGGLE PUN INTENDED BUT YOU ALSO BROUGHT
IN WITH THAT EXPERTISE WITH THE UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT WHAT IT'S
REALLY IMPORTANT TO THE COMMUNITY AND AND ESPECIALLY
THE UNDERSERVED COMMUNITY. AND SO I REALLY AM GRATEFUL YOU
HAVE DONE AMAZING WORK FOR IN CHILE.
I WOULD SAY IS SOMETHING THAT NOT JUST THE PAST GENERATION OF
PEOPLE SHOULD LOOK FORWARD TO SEE WHAT WE CAN WHAT WE HAVE
DONE IN SAN FRANCISCO. BUT I THINK FOR THE GENERATIONS
TO COME TO SAY WOW, THIS IS AMAZING WORK IN SAN FRANCISCO
THAT WE ARE ONE OF THE FIRST TO HAVE THE COMMUNITY CHOICE
AGGREGATION AND TO KIND OF TAKE THAT STEP TO SEE WHAT WE HAVE
DONE TODAY WITH CLEAN POWER S.F..
>> AMAZING WORK. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR DORSEY THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
BARBARA WHEN I WORKED FOR CITY ATTORNEY DENNIS HERRERA
AND DEPUTY CITY WITH THE DEPUTY CITY ATTORNEY TERESA MILLER,
YOU KNOW WE HAD THE OPPORTUNITY TO WORK TOGETHER AND I WILL SAY
AS SOMEONE WHO WAS A BELIEVER IN PUBLIC POWER, SOMETHING WE
HAVE BEEN WORKING ON FOR 113 YEARS IN THIS BUILDING TRYING
TO GET DONE, I FEEL LIKE WE ARE CLOSER TO THAT THAN EVER.
IT MAY TAKE MORE YEARS BUT YOU GOT US THERE AND I REALLY
APPRECIATE YOUR LEADERSHIP ON THAT.
YOU'LL BE MISSED AND I'M SURE THAT YOU PEOPLE WILL SEEK OUT
YOUR COUNSEL IN RETIREMENT. BUT CONGRATULATIONS ON A WELL
ON RETIREMENT. >> COMMISSIONER GENERAL MANAGER
,TREASURER. >> TAX COLLECTOR AND SUPERVISOR
LEO MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC THAT ARE
LISTENING IN. WE'RE RECOGNIZED IN WHAT IS I
CAN ONLY CALL A TRUE PUBLIC SERVANT AND ALL THOSE THINGS
THAT YOU HEARD AND SHE GOT ACHIEVED GETTING BRINGING THAT
POWER FROM THE MOUNTAINS AND HAVING THIS CLEAN POWER
AND CSK ALL THE THINGS THAT SHE ACCOMPLISHED SHE DID IT WITH
UNFORTUNATELY VERY TOUGH OPPOSITION, VERY TOUGH
OPPOSITION SOMETIMES FROM HER OWN COMMISSION BUT SHE QUIETLY
STOOD HER GROUND AND I THINK ALL OF YOU SHE COULD BE A REAL
SHE IS AN EXAMPLE OF PUBLIC SERVICE GETTING IT DONE,
STANDING YOUR GROUND EVEN WHEN THERE'S STRONG OPPOSITION.
SO BARBARA, YOU MADE ME LOOK GOOD.
>> THANK YOU, BARBARA HALE. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH. YOU KNOW, WHEN YOU TAKE A JOB
YOU ALWAYS KNOW THIS THIS DAY IS GOING TO COME EVENTUALLY,
RIGHT? BUT YOU'RE NOT REALLY PLANNING
FOR IT. >> SO FORGIVE ME IF I IF I
STUMBLE A BIT HERE. I'M VERY GRATEFUL FOR THE
OPPORTUNITY THAT BEGAN WITH A PHONE CALL WHILE I WAS WAITING
FOR THE BUS ON ON VENICE A PHONE CALL FROM SUSAN AL
SAYING, YOU KNOW, I'M GOING TO BE THE NEW GENERAL MANAGER OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO PUC AND I WANT TO WORK ON POWER AND I
HEAR YOU. >> I HEAR YOU WANT YOU WORK ON
POWER TOO. SO LET'S TALK I'M PARAPHRASING
OF COURSE. >> AND THEN WE WENT FROM THERE
TO TWO TO TODAY. I HAVE GREAT PRIDE AND HUMILITY
IN BEING ABLE TO SAY THAT I'M PART OF THE LEGACY OF OPERATING
THE HATCH HATCH YOU WATER AND POWER SYSTEM A SYSTEM BUILT
FIRST TO PROVIDE ELECTRICITY FOR THE CONSTRUCTION OF THE DAM
BUT THEN ON TO PROVIDE ELECTRICITY THAT POWERS ARE
ESSENTIAL SERVICES HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO POLICE, FIRE, LIBRARY
SCHOOLS, THE GENERAL HOSPITAL SAN FRANCISCO INTERNATIONAL
AIRPORT BEING THE LARGEST OF THOSE CUSTOMERS.
WE WERE FOR MANY YEARS A QUIET LITTLE UTILITY PLUGGING ALONG.
BUT AS THE PRESSURES CAME ON THE CITY TO FIND WAYS TO BUILD
HOUSING MORE AFFORDABLY, DEVELOPERS LIKE LYNN ARE
BUILDING OUT THE HUNTERS POINT SHIPYARD, CONVERTING IT FROM
THE SHIPYARD INTO THE COMMUNITY IT IS TODAY CAME TO CITY HALL
AND SAID IT'S REALLY EXPENSIVE TO WORK WITH PGE AND IT'S
REALLY DIFFICULT TO WORK WITH PGE AND CAN WE WORK WITH THE
POWER FOLKS OVER AT THE SFP? YOU SEE?
AND SO FROM THAT CONVERSATION THE OPPORTUNITY GREW TO PROVIDE
MORE AFFORDABLE POWER THROUGH THE HETCH HETCHY POWER PROGRAM
TO MORE BUSINESSES AND RESIDENTS MISSION ROCK OUR
LATEST EXAMPLE ALSO AS YOU MENTIONED THE GREAT OPPORTUNITY
OF COMMUNITY CHOICE POWER THROUGH OUR CLEAN POWER ASF
PROGRAM. I'M VERY PLEASED TO SAY I WAS
AT THE THE LEADERSHIP ROLE BUT HAD A VERY STRONG TEAM BEHIND
ME INCLUDING MIKE HIMES WHO'S BEEN IDENTIFIED AS THE ACTING
ASSISTANT GENERAL MANAGER. AS I LEAVE LEADING THAT PROGRAM
FROM THE GERM OF AN IDEA INTO THE OPERATION IT IS TODAY.
>> BUT MAYBE THE THE THING I'M MOST PROUD OF IN IN IN MY
CLOSING HERE IS THE PEOPLE THAT I LEAVE BEHIND.
I LEARNED SO MUCH FROM MY COLLEAGUES AT THE SAN FRANCISCO
PUC. >> THEY HAVE SUCH STRONG SKILLS
THAT WILL CARRY US FORWARD AS A SUPERVISOR, CHAN SAID IT'S A
VERY OPTIMISTIC FUTURE FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND THE POWER
PROVISION THAT SFP C REPRESENTS .
>> IT MAY TAKE SUPERVISOR DORSEY A LONG TIME TO GET TO A
FULL PUBLIC POWER HERE IN THE CITY BUT THE FOUNDATION'S BEEN
LAID AND AND THE FUTURE IS OPTIMISTIC.
I'M I'M VERY HUMBLED AND GRATEFUL FOR THE
OPPORTUNITY TO WORK FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN
FRANCISCO TO ENGAGE WITH THIS BODY WITH THE COMMISSION WITH
THE GENERAL MANAGERS THAT I SERVED WITH.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THIS RECORD RECOGNITION.
>> VERY MUCH APPRECIATE IT. THANK YOU, BARBARA.
ALL CAN TAKE YOUR NEXT UP DISTRICT TEN SUPER VISOR WALTON
THANK YOU SO MUCH PRESIDENT MADAM AND COLLEAGUES, IT IS MY
PRIVILEGE TO RECOGNIZE AS AN EXTRAORDINARY COMMUNITY LEADER,
MENTOR, EDUCATOR AND MOTHER PROFESSOR THEODORE ILDEFONSO
OLMO FOR 20 FIVE YEARS PROFESSOR TEODORA HAS DEDICATED
HER LIFE TO EMPOWERING YOUNG PEOPLE THROUGH THE DISCIPLINE,
VALUES AND TRADITIONS OF THE CHALLENGED CAMPO.
A PROUD SAN FRANCISCO NATIVE RAISED IN VISITATION VALLEY,
SHE CONTINUES TO SERVE THE COMMUNITY SHE CALLS HOME WHILE
RAISING HER TWO CHILDREN ALONGSIDE HER HUSBAND.
>> HER JOURNEY OF SERVICE BEGAN AT JAMESTOWN COMMUNITY CENTER
IN THE LATE 1990S AND CONTINUED THROUGH REAL OPTIONS FOR CITY
KIDS. >> TODAY SHE CARRIES ON THAT
LEGACY THROUGH APPA FAMILY SERVICES AND THE SAMOAN
COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT CENTER IN SUNNYDALE.
>> THROUGH HER WORK SHE HAS GIVEN GENERATIONS OF YOUTH
CONFIDENCE DISCIPLINE AND LEADERSHIP SKILLS,
SELF-RESPECT AND THE ABILITY TO PROTECT THEMSELVES AND OTHERS.
UNDER HER LEADERSHIP, TIGER PALM SALON CAMPO HAS BECOME A
BEACON OF EXCELLENCE AND VISITATION VALLEY.
SHE HAS TRAINED COUNTLESS YOUNG PEOPLE AND DEVELOPED 16 BLACK
BUILDS ALL FROM THE NEIGHBORHOOD.
>> HER STUDENTS HAVE REPRESENTED SAN FRANCISCO WITH
DISTINCTION AT LOCAL, NATIONAL AND INTERNATIONAL COMPETITIONS
EARNING NUMEROUS MEDALS WHILE DEMONSTRATING THE VALUES SHE
INSTILLS IN THEM EVERY DAY. >> TODAY WE ARE ALSO HONORED TO
RECOGNIZE TWO OUTSTANDING YOUNG LEADERS WHO EMBODY THOSE VALUES
. HER CHILDREN MALI AND GABRIEL
OLMO FROM MALI, A SENIOR AT PHILLIP AND SALA BURTON HIGH
SCHOOL AND GABRIEL, A SIXTH GRADE STUDENT AT VISITATION
VALLEY MIDDLE SCHOOL HAVE BOTH BEEN SELECTED TO THE 2026 W.K.
U. >> WORLD USA KARATE TEAM CHOSEN
AMONG THE NATION'S TOP MARTIAL ARTISTS.
THEY WILL REPRESENT THE UNITED STATES THIS AUGUST AT THE WQ
WORLD CHAMPIONSHIPS IN BERLIN, GERMANY.
COMPETING AGAINST ATHLETES FROM MORE THAN 25 COUNTRIES AS THE
ONLY TWO SAN FRANCISCO SELECTED FOR THIS PRESTIGIOUS TEAM MALI
AND GABRIEL SERVE AS ROLE MODELS FOR YOUNG PEOPLE ACROSS
OUR CITY. >> SHOWING WHAT CAN BE ACHIEVED
THROUGH HARD WORK DISCIPLINE AND DEDICATION.
>> PROFESSOR THEODORE MALI AND GABRIEL EXEMPLIFY THE VERY
BEST OF SAN FRANCISCO. THEY REMIND US THAT GREATNESS
CAN EMERGE FROM OUR NEIGHBORHOODS WHEN SUPPORTED BY
STRONG FAMILIES, DEDICATED MENTORS AND A COMMUNITY THAT
BELIEVE IN ITS YOUNG PEOPLE. >> WE EXTEND OUR DEEPEST
GRATITUDE AND HEARTFELT CONGRATULATIONS TO PROFESSOR
THEODORE ILDEFONSO OMO FOR 25 YEARS OF TRANSFORMATIVE SERVICE
AND TO MALI AND GABRIEL OMO FOR THEIR OUTSTANDING ACHIEVEMENTS
AND REPRESENTATION OF OUR CITY. ON THE INTERNATIONAL STAGE.
CONGRATULATIONS AND THANK YOU FOR MAKING SAN FRANCISCO PROUD
. >> THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR WALTON AND BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
>> I'M ACTUALLY GOING TO STEP BACK AND LET MY CHILDREN SPEAK
AND GIVE THEM THE FLOOR. GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY BROTHER AND I WOULD LIKE TO THANK SUPERVISOR WALTON AND THE
SAN FRANCISCO BOARD OF SUPERVISORS FOR PRESENTING US
WITH THIS AWARD. WE ARE INCREDIBLY GRATEFUL FOR
THIS HONOR AND FOR THE OPPORTUNITY TO RECEIVE IT NOT
ONLY AS KARATE TEAMMATES BUT ALSO AS SIBLINGS.
OUR MARTIAL ARTS JOURNEY BEGAN AS SOON AS WE STARTED CRAWLING
FROM FILMING WORKOUT VIDEOS FOR SFE ISD'S EDUCATION CHANNEL
DURING COVID TO NOW BEING ABLE TO COMPETE AT THE HIGHEST LEVEL
TOGETHER. >> IT'S SUCH A FULL CIRCLE
MOMENT. >> WE ARE VERY PROUD
AND GRATEFUL TO BE REPRESENTING THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND ALSO THE CITY OF SAN FRANCISCO AND OF COURSE OUR
NEIGHBORHOOD. >> VISITATION VALLEY.
>> WE WOULD ALSO LIKE TO GIVE OUR PRAISE TO GOD BECAUSE HE
HAS ALWAYS BEEN WITH US THROUGHOUT OUR LIVES.
WE BOTH WOULD HAVE BEEN ABLE TO RECEIVE THIS AWARD AND BE
COMPETING IN THE WQ TOURNAMENT WITHOUT HIS EVERLASTING LOVE,
GUIDANCE AND SUPPORT. OUR PRAYERS HAVE DEFINITELY
BEEN HEARD AND ANSWERED. >> WE WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK
OUR AUNTIES LIZETTE GRAY AND DR. PATTI TITO FOR OPENING
THE DOORS OF APA FAMILY SERVICES AND THIS ONLINE
COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT CENTER ALLOWING NOT ONLY MY SISTER
AND I WELL ALL OF THE TIGERBALM KIDS AND ADULTS TO TRAIN
AND BUILD COMMUNITY TOGETHER. THANK YOU FOR PROVIDING US WITH
THESE LOVELY SPACES SO WE CAN CONTINUE TO GROW AND SUCCEED
IN OUR MARTIAL ARTS TRAINING. >> WE WOULD ALSO LIKE TO THANK
OUR KARATE FAMILY AND DCF LEADERS AND STAFF WHO ARE
IN ATTENDANCE FOR THEIR SUPPORT.
AND AS WE PREPARE FOR GERMANY WE COULD NOT HAVE MADE THE TEAM
WITHOUT YOUR DEDICATION, ENCOURAGEMENT AND GOOD VIBES.
THANK YOU UNCLE AMA AND UNCLE LUIS FOR COACHING US
AND HELPING US DISCOVER NEW WAYS TO TRAIN THE STRENGTH
AND IMPROVE OUR STAMINA. THANK YOU TIGER PHONE FOR
KEEPING US ACCOUNTABLE AND PUSHING US TO BE OUR BEST
DURING EVERY TRAINING SESSION. >> WE LOVE YOU GUYS.
LASTLY, WE WOULD LIKE TO GIVE A SPECIAL THANK YOU TO OUR MOM.
WE HAVE NOT WE WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN IN KARATE WITHOUT YOU
AND WE ARE BEYOND GRATEFUL TO HAVE YOU NOT ONLY AS OUR MOTHER
BUT ALSO AS AN AMAZING PROFESSOR MENTOR AND ROLE MODEL
WHO ALWAYS GUIDES US IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION AND WE CAN'T
FORGET ABOUT OUR DAD WHO HAS BEEN THE BEST, WHO HAS BEEN THE
BEST CHEERLEADER BOTH AT HOME AND IN OUR ENDEAVORS.
>> THANK YOU ALL FOR BELIEVING IN US AND SUPPORTING US ON THIS
JOURNEY. >> THANK YOU AND AND I SEE WE
HAVE I SEE WE HAVE OUR DIRECTOR FOR THE DEPARTMENT OF CHILDREN
YOUTH AND FAMILIES SERVICE, DORSEY SMITH I DON'T KNOW IF
YOU WANT TO SAY ANYTHING BUT I KNOW YOU ARE HERE TO SUPPORT.
>> I JUST SAY REALLY QUICK WILLIE REALLY QUICKLY.
I AM SUPER PROUD OF ONE TO HAVE TEODORA THE FOUNDER OF AS ON MY
STAFF AS MY TECHNICAL ASSISTANT CAPACITY BUILDING MANAGER,
YOUTH DEVELOPMENT EXTRAORDINAIRE, SUPER MOM
WONDERFUL PROFESSOR BUT SUPER PROUD OF ALL OF YOU.
I'VE SEEN YOU GROW THROUGHOUT THE YEARS.
YOUR CONFIDENCE, YOUR YOUR FAITH, YOUR ABILITY EVERYTHING
THAT YOU REPRESENT IS WHAT WE WANT FOR CHILDREN AND YOUTH
IN SAN FRANCISCO. EVERYTHING THAT YOUR MOM
THEODORA BRINGS TO WHAT SHE DOES FOR SHAOLIN TEMPLE SHAOLIN
TIGER PARK AND JUST THE WORK THAT SHE DOES IN COMMUNITY.
THIS IS WHAT WE LOVE TO SEE EACH AND EVERY DAY AND THIS IS
WHAT WE HOPE. SAN FRANCISCO STRIVES TO BE SO
THANK YOU AND CONGRATULATIONS. >> THE ONLY SAN FRANCISCO YOUTH
TO GO TO THIS TOURNAMENT. >> AWESOME.
AND BRING ME SOMETHING BACK FROM GERMANY.
OKAY
. >> DISTRICT TWO SUPERVISOR
CHERYL THANK YOU. >> PRESIDENT MANDOLIN.
COLLEAGUES TODAY IT IS MY HONOR TO RECOGNIZE THE DOLPHIN
SWIMMING AND BOATING CLUB AND THE SOUTH END ROWING CLUB
AS THEY CELEBRATE 50 YEARS OF WOMEN'S MEMBERSHIP.
THIS MILESTONE WAS NOT GIVEN BUT WON.
SO COULD I PLEASE ASK DIANE WALTON AND LEE TO COME UP TO
THE PODIUM AT THE SOUTH END ROWING CLUB WAS FOUNDED
IN 1873. >> THE OLDEST ROWING CLUB WEST
OF THE MISSISSIPPI AND THE DOLPHIN CLUB THAT FOLLOWED SOON
AFTER FOUNDED IN 1877. AND FOR NEARLY A CENTURY BOTH
CLUBS WERE MEN ONLY. BUT DESPITE THESE BARRIERS,
WOMEN HAVE BEEN SWIMMING THESE WATERS LONG BEFORE THEY WERE
WELCOMED. >> LOOK AT THAT.
IN 1911, HAZEL LAGUNA BECAME THE FIRST WOMAN TO SWIM ACROSS
THE GOLDEN GATE WEARING A SOUTHEND JERSEY.
IN 1912, NELL SCHMITT BECAME THE FIRST WOMAN TO SWIM ACROSS
SAN FRANCISCO BAY. WOMEN WERE PART OF THIS STORY
BEFORE THE CLUBS WERE READY TO ADMIT IT.
BUT IN 1975 SIX WOMEN BROUGHT SUIT TO INTEGRATE THE CLUB'S
LEE JOAN BROWN, MARY DAKE, TRUDY DE LORENZO, DIANE MAJOR
AND MARILYN RODMAN. AND WITH THE LEGAL HELP BY
ATTORNEYS SANDRA TARAZI AND FELICE, THEIR CASE AGAINST
THE CITY ESTABLISHED THE PRIVATE CLUBS ON PUBLIC LAND
COULD NOT BAR WOMEN BACK. >> SO ON OCTOBER 20TH, 1976,
THE FIRST FIVE WOMEN JOINED THE DOLPHIN CLUB.
SALLY JO AND ANTON SHOOK MARY KAUFMAN, VERONICA MANN, JOYCE
SWETNICK AND ZITA TAFT. THAT SAME YEAR THE FIRST FIVE
WOMEN JOINED SOUTHEND, THE PLAINTIFFS LEAGUE JOAN, MARY,
TRUDY AND DIANE WHOSE COURAGE AND LOVE OF THE BAY OPENED THE
DOOR FOR EVERYONE WHO FOLLOWED. IN 1977 49 MORE WOMEN JOINED
THE DOLPHIN CLUB IN ITS FIRST FULL YEAR OF WOMEN'S
MEMBERSHIP. 13 ARE STILL ACTIVE TODAY.
>> SUSAN ALLEN, JOANIE B.M. BAUER, CYNTHIA EHRLICH.
MILO FAY. PEGGY KNICKERBOCKER.
MORGAN COOLA JACKIE MARAVICH ERA OAKBAY CAROLE BRADY PALMER
PODOLSKY CATHERINE ROCKWOOD ROBIN ROMAN.
SOPHIE TAGGART. AND ONCE WOMEN WERE IN.
NATURALLY THEY LED. >> AT THE DOLPHIN CLUB KATIE
MALONEY MEG RILEY AND DIANE WALDEN HAVE ALL SERVED AS
PRESIDENT AT THE SOUTHEND WOMEN HAVE LED THE CLUB SIX TIMES.
SHARON IN CORSICA NOW. NANCY STRETCH, LAURA TAYLOR,
KIM HOWARD FRAN HAGLER AND VANESSA MARLAND.
THE CURRENT PRESIDENT OF THE DOLPHIN CLUB WHO'S HERE WITH US
TODAY AT SOUTH END SORRY TYPO. >> THANK YOU.
HEY, THIS IS A GROUP EFFORT HERE.
>> I'LL TAKE ALL THE HELP I CAN GET.
ALL RIGHT. >> YOU KNOW WHAT, DANA?
WHAT DID YOU SAY? WOMEN WON AND EVERYBODY
BENEFITED. >> WOMEN FOUGHT AND EVERYBODY
WON. YEAH.
>> THERE WE GO. YEAH.
>> AND THEY REWROTE THE RECORD BOOKS.
SUSAN HIND BONE WAS THE FIRST WOMAN TO WIN THE ALCATRAZ SWIM
IN THE GOLDEN GATE SWIM. >> JOANIE B.M. BAUER, SUSAN
ALLEN, LISA SMITH. SUSAN COBB, CAROL MCGRATH
AND KAREN DRUCKER. THESE SIX DOLPHIN WOMEN BECAME
THE FIRST ALL FEMALE AMERICAN RELAY TEAM TO SWIM THE ENGLISH
CHANNEL. KIM CHAMBERS AND AMY APPLE.
HANDS UP, SIR. SORRY.
CARRIED THE SOUTH END'S OPEN WATER TRADITION TO THE WORLD
STAGE ALONGSIDE RUNNERS LIKE MARTY MARKEL AND ROWERS LIKE
MARY DAKE AND DIANE DAVIS. THESE WOMEN HAVE MADE THEIR
MARKS IN WORLD WIDE RECORD BOOKS.
TODAY 785 WOMEN MAKE UP 37% OF THE DOLPHIN CLUB AND WOMEN MAKE
UP A THIRD OF THE SOUTH END'S 1300 MEMBERS.
THEY ROW BEFORE SUNRISE TRAIN FOR THEIR FIRST ALCATRAZ
CROSSING AND SWIM TO THE FLAG FOR THE VERY FIRST TIME.
>> SPEAKING FOR THE TWO CLUBS TODAY ARE DIANE IMMEDIATE PAST
PRESIDENT OF THE DOLPHIN CLUB AND LEE THE TRAILBLAZER WITH
THE SOUTHEND ROWING CLUB. BOTH LIVING EXAMPLES OF WOMEN'S
LEADERSHIP AT THESE INSTITUTIONS ACROSS GENERATION
LINES. 50 YEARS AGO A HANDFUL OF WOMEN
FOUGHT FOR A DOOR THEY HAD TO OPEN.
AND TODAY HUNDREDS WALK THROUGH IT EVERY DAY.
SO ON BEHALF OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS, THANK YOU
AND CONGRATULATIONS TO BOTH CLUBS AND TO EVERY WOMAN WHO
HAS BEEN PART OF THIS LEGACY. >> OH, SUPERVISOR SAUDER, THANK
YOU. AND IF I MAY ADD VERY QUICKLY,
YOU KNOW SUPERVISOR SHARE AND I SHARE A BORDER AND THIS IS ONE
OF THOSE SITUATIONS WHERE I'M REALLY, REALLY JEALOUS THAT
YOU'RE JUST ACROSS THE LINES AND YOU'RE IN DISTRICT TWO
RATHER THAN DISTRICT THREE. IF WE COULD TRADE I'D LIKE TO
TAKE BOTH OF YOU. I'D LIKE TO TAKE BUENA VISTA
FOR THE IRISH COFFEES BUT WE'LL WORK ON THAT.
I WANT TO APPRECIATE ALL THE WORK THAT YOU'VE DONE.
YOUR LEGACY, YOUR TRAILBLAZING LEGACY.
I KNOW IT'S A BIG COMMUNITY DOWN THERE.
YOU KNOW THERE'S NEVER ANY FIGHTING BETWEEN THE TWO CLUBS.
NEVER. SO IT'S GOOD TO HAVE THIS THIS
MOMENT. THERE YOU GO.
IT'S GOOD TO HAVE THIS MOMENT OF UNITY.
WE'RE REALLY PROUD TO HAVE YOU RIGHT ON THE BORDER OF OUR
DISTRICTS AND YOU KNOW TO HAVE YOU ON THE WATER.
I STILL THINK YOU'RE CRAZY FOR WHAT YOU DO.
>> I DON'T KNOW HOW YOU DO IT BUT GOOD ON YOU AND THANKS FOR
EVERYTHING. WELL, THANK YOU.
I'M LEE. I'M A SOUTH ENDER AND I'M
THRILLED TO BE HERE TODAY. I WANT TO SAY THANKS TO THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS AND TO OUR WONDERFUL LEADERS.
THAT'S VANESSA MARLIN AND DIANE WALTON FROM THE SOUTH
AND ROWING CLUB AND THE DOLPHIN CLUB.
AND WHAT I WANT TO SAY IS HOW WONDERFUL IT IS TO TO STILL BE
HERE AFTER AFTER 50 YEARS. THE REASON I'M STANDING HERE IS
BECAUSE I WAS ONE OF SIX PLAINTIFFS WHO SUED THE CLUB
BACK IN 1974 AND WE ENDURED QUITE A STRUGGLE.
BACK BACK TO THE 70S WAS A TIME OF TUMULTUOUS SOCIAL CHANGE AS
THE OLDER FOLKS AMONG US MIGHT REMEMBER.
AND SO OUR CLUBS WERE NO DIFFERENT.
BUT WE WE SUED THE CLUBS AND WE GOT IN AND AND I THINK THE THE
MAIN POINT IS THAT NONE OF THIS HAPPENED WITHOUT A STRUGGLE.
SO I'M NOT HERE TO SAY ISN'T IT GREAT THAT WE'VE BEEN DOING
THIS FOR 50 YEARS AND I'M HERE TO REMIND EVERYBODY THAT IT WAS
NOT WITHOUT THE STRUGGLE THAT ANY OF THIS HAPPENED.
THAT'S WHAT IT WAS ABOUT AND SO AT ANY RATE, I'M JUST DELIGHTED
TO STILL BE ALIVE AND THAT'S WHY I'M HERE.
EVERYBODY ELSE IS BAD. >> IT WAS JOAN BROWN AND TRUDY
DE LORENZO AND MARY DAY AND DIANE MAJOR.
OH LORD, I'M SURE I'M FORGETTING A COUPLE OF FOLKS I
SHOULD HAVE WRITTEN IT DOWN. BUT THANK YOU GUYS SO MUCH.
IT'S IT'S A WONDERFUL DAY FOR US AND AND I COULDN'T BE
HAPPIER TO SEE ALL OF OUR SUPPORTERS FROM THE CLUB.
>> YEAH. >> THIS IS THE MOST WONDERFUL.
>> HI. DIANE WALTON IMMEDIATE PAST
PRESIDENT OF THE DOLPHIN CLUB AND PRESIDENT OF OUR FOUNDATION
. >> NOW FIRST OF ALL, YOU ARE
ALL INVITED TO COME AND BE IN THE WATER OR ON THE WATER OR
NEAR THE WATER. >> WHATEVER BEST SUITS YOUR
FANCY. SUPERVISOR CHERYL OF COURSE HAS
BEEN IN THE WATER. SO I THINK IT'S ON YOU, SIR.
>> OH. >> BUT ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
WE ALL KNOW AND THAT YOU KNOW SO WELL ONE OF THE LESSONS THAT
WE LEARN BY GETTING TO BE PART OF THIS IS IT'S REALLY
IMPORTANT TO DO HARD THINGS. YOU WAKE UP IN THE MORNING
AND YOU DO HARD THINGS. WE KNOW THAT YOU GUYS DO THAT
AND YOU ALSO PROVIDE THE SPACE THAT ALLOWS US TO DO THAT
AND WE'RE GRATEFUL FOR YOUR SEEING US AND FOR YOUR
SUPPORTING US. OVER THE YEARS IT'S BEEN
EXTRAORDINARY REALLY. WE'RE JUST THIS FUNNY LITTLE
DONUT HOLE IN THE MIDDLE OF A CHAOTIC PARK THAT IS ON CITY
PROPERTY AND AND YOU TAKE VERY GOOD CARE OF US AND WE'RE
GRATEFUL. THE OTHER THING THE SUPERVISOR
BROUGHT UP IS AND I THINK IS SO IMPORTANT FOR US TO WALK AWAY
WITH TODAY AND LEE REFERENCED IT ALSO WHICH IS THE WOMEN
FOUGHT AND EVERYBODY WON. >> SO AGAIN, THANK YOU FOR
EVERYTHING AND AND REALLY COME DOWN AND SWIM JUST YOU CAN ONLY
HAVE TO DO IT TRY ONCE YOU KNOW YOU DON'T HAVE TO COME BACK A
SECOND TIME BUT YOU REALLY SHOULD COME AND TRY AT LEAST
ONCE. >> THANK YOU.
>> I KNOW
. MM HMM.
DISTRICT FOUR SUPERVISOR WONG THANK YOU, PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN.
COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM HONORED TO RECOGNIZE MIKE, NORA
AND KATHRYN ROBERTS THE WINNERS OF SAN FRANCISCO DUMBLEDORE'S
CONTEST. WHEN MY OFFICE LAUNCHED THIS
CONTEST EARLIER THIS YEAR, OUR GOAL WAS SIMPLE TO LISTEN.
WE WANTED TO HEAR DIRECTLY FROM RESIDENTS ABOUT THE CHALLENGES
THEY ENCOUNTER AND THE OPPORTUNITIES THEY SEE TO MAKE
SAN FRANCISCO AN EVEN BETTER PLACE TO LIVE, WORK AND RAISE A
FAMILY. >> WE RECEIVED MORE THAN 200
SUBMISSIONS FROM ACROSS THE CITY AND THEY REMINDED US THAT
SOME OF THE BEST IDEAS COME FROM PEOPLE WHO CARE DEEPLY
ABOUT THEIR COMMUNITIES. AFTER REVIEWING THOSE
SUBMISSIONS, MIKE AND KATHRYN'S ENTRIES STOOD OUT FOR
IDENTIFYING A PRACTICAL SOLUTION THAT COULD BENEFIT
RESIDENTS THROUGHOUT SAN FRANCISCO.
THEY BROUGHT ATTENTION TO SAN FRANCISCO'S CEILING HEIGHT
REQUIREMENT FOR HACKABLE HABITABLE ROOMS WHICH DIFFERS
FROM CALIFORNIA STATE STANDARDS.
WHILE THE DIFFERENCE IS ONLY SIX INCHES, IT CREATES A
SIGNIFICANT CHALLENGE FOR HOMEOWNERS TRYING TO LEGALIZE
EXISTING LIVING SPACES. >> THEIR SUBMISSION HIGHLIGHTED
AN OPPORTUNITY TO ALIGN LOCAL STANDARDS WITH STATE LAW WHILE
MAINTAINING IMPORTANT SAFETY REQUIREMENTS.
DOING SO WOULD HELP MORE RESIDENTS BRING EXISTING LIVING
SPACES INTO SAN FRANCISCO'S LEGAL HOUSING STOCK, CREATE A
PATHWAY FOR UNAUTHORIZED DWELLING UNITS TO BECOME LEGAL
UNITS AND MAKE BETTER USE OF EXISTING HOMES FOR OUR CITY.
WHAT MAKES THIS SUBMISSION ESPECIALLY MEANINGFUL IS THAT
IT REFLECTS THE KIND OF COMMUNITY DRIVEN PROBLEM
SOLVING THAT HELPS SAN FRANCISCO MOVE FORWARD.
MIKE AND CATHERINE SAW A CHALLENGE, TOOK THE INITIATIVE
TO SPEAK UP AND OFFERED A THOUGHTFUL SOLUTION THAT COULD
BENEFIT HOMEOWNERS FAMILIES, RENTERS AND NEIGHBORHOODS
ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO. >> MEANINGFUL PROGRESS HAPPENS
WHEN RESIDENTS AND LOCAL LEADERS WORK TOGETHER.
LISTEN TO ONE ANOTHER AND FOCUS ON SOLVING PROBLEMS AS A
COMMUNITY. I REMAIN COMMITTED TO WORKING
ALONGSIDE RESIDENTS, NEIGHBORHOOD GROUPS AND KUMU
STAKEHOLDERS TO IDENTIFY PRACTICAL WAYS TO STRENGTHEN
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND IMPROVE QUALITY OF LIFE FOR THE PEOPLE
WE SERVE. THAT IS WHY MY OFFICE IS
ADVANCING LEGISLATION TO ALIGN SAN FRANCISCO'S CEILING HEIGHT
REQUIREMENTS WITH STATE LAW AND MAKE IT EASIER FOR
HOMEOWNERS TO LEGALIZE EXISTING HOUSING WHILE MAINTAINING
SAFETY STANDARDS. THIS HELPS BOTH HOMEOWNERS
AND RENTERS. THANK YOU, MIKE AND CATHERINE.
>> YOU TOO ARE OUR OF MANY RESIDENTS UTAH OF MANY
RESIDENTS WHO REGULARLY ENGAGE OUR OFFICE SHARE IDEAS, RAISE
CONCERNS AND WORK WITH US TO IMPROVE OUR COMMUNITY.
>> THE BEST SOLUTIONS OFTEN COME FROM PEOPLE WHO CARE
ENOUGH TO GET INVOLVED AND TAKE THE TIME TO MAKE THEIR VOICES
HEARD. THIS WINNING SUBMISSION IS A
GREAT EXAMPLE OF THAT PARTNERSHIP IN ACTION.
>> TOGETHER WE ARE WORKING TO TURN THE IDEA INTO MEANINGFUL
CHANGE. WE APPRECIATE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO WORK WITH BOTH OF YOU AND WITH SO MANY OTHER
RESIDENTS ACROSS DISTRICT FOUR AND SAN FRANCISCO WHO DEDICATE
THEIR TIME, ENERGY AND IDEAS TO MAKING OUR NEIGHBORHOODS
STRONGER. NOW I'D LIKE TO ASK MIKE, ONE
OF OUR DISTRICT FOUR RESIDENTS, TO SHARE A FEW WORDS BEFORE WE
PRESENT THE COMMENDATION. >> THANK YOU.
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS. ALAN I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL
THE TIMES I'VE BEEN ABLE TO MEET WITH YOU.
I'VE BEEN VERY INVOLVED IN THE COMMUNITY ESPECIALLY SINCE
DURING COVID. INVOLVED IN LOTS OF AFFORDABLE
HOUSING MEETINGS TRYING TO COME UP WITH GOOD SOLUTIONS THAT
WOULD WORK FOR EVERYBODY IN OUR COMMUNITY.
THE REASON THIS IS IMPORTANT FOR A NUMBER OF PEOPLE,
INCLUDING THE RENTERS IS THAT IN THE CITY THERE ARE HUNDREDS
OF THOUSANDS OF IN-LAW UNITS MOSTLY SITTING EMPTY.
THE AVERAGE BLOCK HAS 48 PARCELS AND ON MY BLOCK ALONE
NONE OF MY NEIGHBORS ARE RENTING THEIR UNITS OUT BECAUSE
THEY'RE AFRAID OF THE CONSEQUENCES OF IF THEY GET
TURNED IN FOR HAVING A RENTER. >> AND THE PENALTIES ARE QUITE
HARSH. IT CAN COST HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS TO HAVE TO TEAR OUT YOUR FOUNDATION TO
LOWER THE FLOORING AND TO DO ALL THAT.
>> IN ADDITION TO THAT, IN ADDITION TO AFFORDABLE
HOUSING, AFFORDABLE TAXATION IS ALSO TIED TO THAT.
AND PART OF WHY I FIXED MY UNIT UP HOPING TO BE ABLE TO RENT IT
OUT. I'M 64 YEARS OLD.
I WON'T BE ABLE TO WORK THAT MUCH LONGER.
I WAS HOPING TO HAVE RENTAL INCOME TO PAY FOR MY PROPERTY
TAXES EVERY 30 YEARS. >> YOUR PROPERTY TAXES DOUBLE
MINOR 17,000. I WILL NOT BE ABLE TO PAY
$34,000 WHEN I'M MY DAD'S AGE. >> THAT'S 100 GRAND EVERY THREE
YEARS. AND MANY OF MY NEIGHBORHOOD
NEIGHBORS ARE JUST LIKE ME. >> ANYONE WHO BOUGHT FOR OVER
$1 MILLION. SO COMING UP WITH A CREATIVE
SOLUTION SO PEOPLE CAN AND ARE WILLING TO FIX UP THEIR UNITS,
RENT THEM OUT. AND IT'S ALSO GOING TO KEEP OUR
ELDERLY POPULATION IN THEIR HOME BECAUSE I WOULD LIKE TO
LIVE IN MY HOME MY WHOLE LIFE. BUT RIGHT NOW IT'S DAUNTING
AND I'M LIKE AT WHAT POINT WILL I GET KICKED OUT?
SO I REALLY APPRECIATE THE WHOLE BOARD LOOKING INTO THIS
ISSUE AND TRYING TO COME UP WITH SOME GOOD SOLUTIONS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH,
SUPERVISOR WANG FOR ADDRESSING THIS REALLY IMPORTANT ISSUE.
I'VE JUST NOTICED SO MANY TIMES IN SAN FRANCISCO WE GO FOR SORT
OF THE MORE EXPENSIVE IMPACT TO CALL DISRUPTIVE.
JUST YOU KNOW, INFERIOR SOLUTIONS WHEN THE THE A BETTER
SOLUTION IS LITERALLY RIGHT UNDER OUR NOSES ALL WE HAVE TO
DO IS RISE TO THE OCCASION AND AND FIX IT.
>> AND I'VE PERSONALLY BEEN WORKING ON THIS ISSUE FOR THE
LAST 20 YEARS EVER SINCE I BOUGHT MY BUILDING WHICH HAS
ILLEGAL UNITS IN THE BASEMENT IT LEGALLY I CAN'T CHARGE A
PENNY OF RENT FOR THOSE UNITS SO ANYONE WHO RENTS THEM FROM
ME CAN SUE ME AND GET EVERY DIME BACK AND JUST LIVE THERE
FOR FREE FOR THE REST OF THEIR LIFE.
THAT'S ONLY ONE EXAMPLE OF THE KIND OF LIABILITY THAT I'VE
EXPOSED MYSELF TO BY RENTING THESE UNITS OUT BECAUSE AS MIKE
POINTED OUT, THERE'S NO WAY I WOULD BE ABLE TO AFFORD TO LIVE
IN MY OWN BUILDING OR EVEN TO OWN THAT BUILDING THIS ENTIRE
TIME WITHOUT USING THAT EXTRA RENTAL INCOME THE WHOLE TIME.
BUT THE CITY HAS JUST MADE THAT SO DIFFICULT FOR ME TO DO THAT.
AT THE SAME TIME AS EVERYBODY IS SAYING WE HAVE A HOUSING
CRISIS, WE HAVE A HOUSING CRISIS BUT WE'RE SORT OF GIVING
WITH ONE HAND AND TAKING WITH THE OTHER AND WE DON'T NEED TO
DO THAT. WE JUST NEED TO PUT OUR ENERGY
INTO USING WHAT WE ALREADY HAVE AND YOU KNOW THE RESOURCES THAT
ARE ALREADY THERE WHICH ARE SO MUCH EASIER TO OPEN UP THAN YOU
KNOW, TEARING UP NEIGHBORHOODS AND PUTTING UP BUILDINGS, YOU
KNOW, THAT ARE GOING TO THAT A LOT OF PEOPLE DON'T WANT
AND THEN ARE GOING TO DISRUPT PEOPLE'S LIVES BECAUSE WE NEED
MORE HOUSING. SO IT'S GREAT THAT YOU'RE
LOOKING AT WHAT'S RIGHT IN FRONT OF YOU AND I WOULD BE
SO THRILLED IF THIS LEGISLATION FINALLY WENT THROUGH AND I JUST
WANT TO SAY I'M SOMEBODY WHO'S NOT AFRAID OF SPEAKING UP EVEN
IF IT CREATES BAD LIKE REPERCUSSIONS FOR MYSELF.
>> THAT'S JUST THE WAY I'M WIRED.
BUT I KNOW YOU AND I HAVE HAD BAD CONSEQUENCES FOR SORT OF,
YOU KNOW, STICKING MY NECK OUT ABOUT VARIOUS THINGS THROUGH MY
LIFE SO I KNOW I, I KNOW HOW SERIOUS THAT CAN BE AND I'M
SURE THERE ARE SO MANY PEOPLE ALL OVER THE CITY WHO ARE JUST
TERRIFIED TO SAY ANYTHING ABOUT THIS SITUATION WHO ARE IN THE
SAME SITUATION I'M IN BECAUSE THEY'RE REALLY SCARED THAT IT
COULD COMPLETELY DESTROY THEIR LIVES IF THEY DO THAT.
>> SO I KNOW THAT IF THIS GOES THROUGH THERE ARE SO MANY
PEOPLE WHO WILL BENEFIT WHO AREN'T IN A POSITION LIKE MIKE
AND I ARE IN THAT WE CAN ACTUALLY SPEAK UP AND CALL
ATTENTION TO IT. >> THERE ARE PROBABLY AT LEAST
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHO WOULD BENEFIT FROM THIS WHO ARE
INVISIBLE RIGHT NOW BECAUSE THEY'RE TOO AFRAID TO SPEAK UP.
SO I JUST REALLY WANT TO THANK YOU FOR DOING THIS.
>> I WILL BE AMAZED IF YOU CAN ACTUALLY, YOU KNOW, PULL THIS
OFF AND AND AND I REALLY HOPE THAT THE BOARD WILL COALESCE
BEHIND YOU AND MAKE THIS AS EASY AS POSSIBLE FOR YOU TO
IMPROVE THIS SITUATION. IT WOULD BE FANTASTIC IF YOU
DID THAT. >> THANK YOU SO MUCH
AND LAST BUT NEVER LEAST, CHRISTOPHER VERDUGO.
>> OH ALSO A BITTERSWEET, BITTERSWEET COMMENDATION I HAVE
THE KIND OF PLEASURE OF RECOGNIZING THE OUTGOING CEO OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO GAY MEN'S CHORUS AND MY FRIEND CHRIS
VERDUGO. >> CHRIS'S FIRST INTRODUCTION
TO THE GAY CHORAL MOVEMENT CAME FROM THE GAY MEN'S CHORUS OF
SOUTH FLORIDA WHICH HE JOINED AT THE YOUNG AGE OF 18.
THREE YEARS LATER HE BECAME ARTISTIC DIRECTOR OF PARAGON
PRODUCTIONS KOREA CHOREOGRAPHING, DIRECTING
AND PRODUCING THEATRICAL PRODUCTIONS FOR CRUISE LINES
AND HOTELS THROUGHOUT THE WORLD.
>> THIS IS A VERY GAY PERSON, VERY GAY STAFF STARTING IN 1999
HE COMBINED HIS EVENT PRODUCTION BACKGROUND WITH HIS
FUNDRAISING SKILLS TO WORK WITH THE MIAMI PROJECT TO CURE
PARALYSIS MIAMI BEACHES WINTER PARTY MUSIC FESTIVAL, THE
COMMUNION FOUNDATION AND HE SERVED ON THE BOARD OF
DIRECTORS FOR THE SOUTH BEACH GAY MEN'S CHORUS.
BUT IN 2003 CALIFORNIA GOT CHRIS AND HE MOVED TO L.A.
AND WAS SELECTED AS ONE OF TWO CHOREOGRAPHERS FOR THE MISS
UNIVERSE PAGEANT. >> SO GAY I REPEAT GAY.
SOON AFTER HE LEFT HIS ARTISTIC ROOTS TO FOCUS ON LGBT Q PLUS
AND SOCIAL JUSTICE ISSUES WORKING WITH VARIOUS LGBT,
LGBTQ PLUS NONPROFITS INCLUDING THE NATIONAL GAY AND LESBIAN
TASK FORCE EQUALITY CALIFORNIA HUMAN RIGHTS CAMPAIGN AND GLAD
PRODUCING LOUNGE AT SUNDANCE FOR FOUR YEARS.
IN 2006 HE JOINED THE GAY MEN'S CHORUS OF LOS ANGELES AS A
SINGER AND FIVE YEARS LATER WAS NAMED EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR
AND CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICER UNDER HIS LEADERSHIP, THE L.A.
CHORUS BUILT AN INTERNATIONAL REPUTATION FOR MUSICAL
EXCELLENCE, DOUBLED ITS BUDGET, EXPERIENCED MASSIVE EXPANSION,
INCORPORATING EDUCATION PROGRAMS IN L.A. HIGH SCHOOLS
AS WELL AS A NATIONAL MUSIC TOUR TITLED IT GETS BETTER
IN SEPTEMBER 20TH 16, SAN FRANCISCO LUCKED OUT.
HE MOVED TO SAN FRANCISCO AND ASSUMED THE ROLE OF
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR AT THE SAN FRANCISCO GAY MEN'S CHORUS TWO
MONTHS AFTER HE STARTED THERE THOUGH THE 2016 ELECTION
HAPPENED THE CHORUS HAD A TOUR PLANNED TO GO TO CHINA TO
COMMEMORATE THE COURSE'S 40TH ANNIVERSARY.
BUT IN LIGHT OF THE DEVELOPMENTS THE CHORUS PIVOTED
AND DECIDED TO TAKE ITS TOUR TO COMMUNITIES ACROSS THE UNITED
STATES WHERE IT WAS NEEDED MOST .
>> INSPIRED BY THE LAVENDER PEN THAT SUPERVISOR HARVEY MILK
GAVE TO FORMER MAYOR GEORGE MOSCONE TO SIGN THE LANDMARK
GAY CIVIL RIGHTS BILL IN 1978. THE LAVENDER PEN TOUR FEATURED
MORE THAN 200 SINGERS FROM S.F. GMC AND THE OAKLAND INTERFAITH
GOSPEL CHOIR. THEY EMBARKED ON A NINE DAY
TRIP ACROSS FIVE SOUTHERN STATES MISSISSIPPI, ALABAMA,
TENNESSEE, SOUTH CAROLINA AND NORTH CAROLINA.
>> THE SINGERS AND STAFF FROM THE TWO CHORUSES PAID THEIR OWN
WAY FOR THE TOUR. AND ALL PROCEEDS FROM THE
PERFORMANCES WENT TO LOCAL LGBTQ CHORUSES, NONPROFITS
AND SERVICE PROVIDERS IN THE COMMUNITIES THEY WERE VISITING
. THEY SANG IN CHURCHES
AND CONCERT HALLS ACROSS THE SOUTH.
THEY RALLIED AGAINST ANTI LGBTQ LEGISLATION ON THE STEPS OF THE
MISSISSIPPI STATE CAPITOL. AND THEY WORKED WITH STUDENTS
AT THE UNIVERSITY OF TENNESSEE KNOXVILLE TO HOST WORKSHOPS ON
POLITICAL ORGANIZING, TRANS IDENTITY AND CHORAL SINGING.
>> A DOCUMENTARY ABOUT THE FILM TITLED GAY CHORUS DEEP SOUTH
WENT ON TO WIN THE AUDIENCE AWARD AT THE 2019 TRIBECA FILM
FESTIVAL. IN 2024 CHRIS AND THE CHORUS
TOOK THEIR LOVE TOUR ON THE ROAD THROUGHOUT THE MIDWEST.
GOING BACK A BIT TO TATE TEEN. THAT WAS WHEN CHRIS AND THE
CHORUS TURNED THEIR ATTENTION TO UNAMBITIOUS.
>> SOME WOULD SAY CRAZY BUT DEFINITELY AMBITIOUS PROJECT
WHICH WAS FOR AN LGBTQ ARTS NONPROFIT TO BUY AND OPERATE A
BUILDING THANKS TO A GENEROUS GIFT FROM FOUNDING CHORUS
MEMBER TERRENCE CHAN AND HIS HUSBAND ED SELL THE CHORUS WAS
ABLE TO BUY THE FORMER BARKAI CENTER AT 170 VALENCIA STREET
IN DISTRICT EIGHT. CHRIS LED THE ORGANIZATION
THROUGH A SUCCESSFUL $15 MILLION CAPITAL CAMPAIGN FOR
THE BUILDING NOW KNOWN AS THE CHAN NATIONAL ARTS CENTER.
THEIR ASPIRATION FOR THE BUILDING HAS BEEN FOR IT TO BE
A HUB FOR INNOVATIVE ARTS PROGRAMING FROM THE BAY AREA
AND BEYOND. IN THE YEARS SINCE IT OPENED
IT'S SHOWN THEY'VE SHOWN PERFORMANCES BY STEPHEN
SCHWARTZ, ANDREW LIPPA, LIA DELARIA AND CHEYENNE JACKSON.
HOSTED COMMUNITY EVENTS LIKE APPLE'S ANNUAL LUNAR NEW YEAR
AND SERVED AS A SPACE TO HOLD MEMORIAL SERVICES FOR CHORUS
MEMBERS WHO HAVE DIED IN 2018. >> CHRIS ALSO IN 2018 CHRIS
HELPED LAUNCH RHYTHM THAT'S REACHING YOUTH THROUGH MUSIC AN
IN-SCHOOL PROGRAM THAT BRINGS CHORUS MEMBERS INTO BAY AREA
ELEMENTARY, MIDDLE AND HIGH SCHOOLS TO SHARE MESSAGES OF
INCLUSION, ANTI-BULLYING AND LIVING AUTHENTICALLY
THROUGH MUSIC AND STORYTELLING. TODAY RHYTHM REACHES MORE THAN
3000 STUDENTS AND TEACHERS EACH YEAR.
OVER THIS LAST DECADE, CHRIS HAS OVERSEEN TREMENDOUS GROWTH
AT THE S.F. GMC BUILDING. HIS ADMINISTRATIVE TEAM FROM 3
TO 11 AND THROUGH STRATEGIC FUNDRAISING AND PARTNERSHIPS
GROWING THE SIZE OF THE OPERATING BUDGET FROM $800,000
TO MORE THAN $5 MILLION. >> HE CHAMPIONED THE ARTIST
PORTAL AT THE AIDS MEMORIAL GROVE CREATING A PERMANENT
ARTISTIC INSTALLATION THAT CONNECTS VISITORS TO THE
STORY'S HISTORY AND ENDURING LEGACY OF LGBTQ ARTISTS.
CHRIS'S TENURE AT S.F. GMC HAS EMBODIED THE BEST OF THE
COURSE'S MISSION TO BUILD COMMUNITY, INSPIRE ACTIVISM
AND FOSTER COMPASSION AT HOME AND AROUND THE WORLD.
>> ALTHOUGH CHRIS WILL BE MOVING TO PALM SPRINGS WHICH
FEELS A LITTLE LIKE A JOKE BUT HIS IMPACT ON S.F. GMC WILL BE
FELT FOR YEARS TO COME. AND I HOPE YOU WILL ALL JOIN ME
AND CONGRATULATING HIM ON HIS EXEMPLARY LEADERSHIP
AND SERVICE TO SAN FRANCISCO. >> THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
THANK YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND THANK YOU BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. FIRST I'D LIKE TO BEGIN BY
THANKING YOU PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR YOUR YEARS OF
SUPPORT. WE WOULDN'T HAVE A ARTS CENTER
WERE IT NOT FOR THE CITY AND COUNTY OF SAN FRANCISCO
BEING INCREDIBLY SUPPORTIVE AND WITH YOUR FINANCIAL
RESOURCES BUT ALSO THE SPIRIT AND LOVE AND SUPPORT WITH WHICH
YOU HAVE GIVEN US. I ALSO WANT TO THANK MY STAFF,
SINGERS AND BOARD MEMBERS WHO HAVE SHOWN UP TODAY.
AS I SHARED WITH MY BOARD CHAIR TOM PAULINO, PEOPLE HAVE LIVES.
THEY HAVE JOBS. I DIDN'T EXPECT ANYONE TO BE
HERE AND YET I AM PROFOUNDLY GRATEFUL.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
>> I WON'T BE LONG BUT I DO WANT TO SAY THAT IT'S DEEPLY
MEANINGFUL TO BE HERE TODAY. >> ON NOVEMBER 27TH, 1978,
HARVEY MILK AND MAYOR MOSCONI WERE ASSASSINATED HERE THAT
EVENING A CANDLELIGHT VIGIL ENSUED WITH MEMBERS OF THE SAN
FRANCISCO GAME AND SCORES. THAT WAS OUR FIRST PUBLIC
PERFORMANCE RIGHT THERE ON THE STEPS OF THIS CITY HALL THAT IS
NEVER LOST ON ME, THAT IS NEVER LOST ON ME.
AND AS WE APPROACH ALMOST 50 YEARS OF A STORIED HISTORY MUCH
OF WHICH YOU JUST SHARED PRESIDENT MANTLE MEN BUT SOME
OF WHICH YOU DIDN'T LIKE. TWO YEARS LATER, THREE YEARS
LATER EXCUSE ME WE EMBARKED ON A NATIONAL TOUR ACROSS THE
COUNTRY AND IN OUR WAKE STARTED COURSES FROM DIFFERENT CITIES
WHICH ARE NOW GOING ON TO CELEBRATE THEIR 4748 YEAR
ANNIVERSARIES. >> AND WE ALSO LOST HUNDREDS OF
SINGERS DURING THE AIDS PANDEMIC.
AND THIS ORGANIZATION WAS BUILT BY THEM.
SO IT IS ON THEIR SHOULDERS THAT I STAND THAT WE ALWAYS
STAND WHEN WE ARE ON STAGE IN SCHOOLS AND IN STATES ACROSS
THIS COUNTRY. THAT'S BEEN THE HONOR OF MY
LIFE TO SHEPHERD S.F. TMC OVER THE LAST DECADE BUT I JUST WANT
TO CLOSE WITH A REALLY IMPORTANT STORY.
ON SATURDAY NIGHT AFTER THE LAST CONCERT OF THE SEASON MY
LAST SHOW AS THE CEO, I WAS AT THE AFTER PARTY WITH ONE OF OUR
SINGERS AND I HAD NEVER HEARD HIS STORY AND SO I JUST ASKED
WHAT BROUGHT YOU HERE FOUR YEARS AGO?
AND HE SAID, YOU KNOW, I WAS HE SAID I WAS LIVING IN REDDING
AND I JUST COULDN'T BE MYSELF AND I NEEDED TO MOVE TO A CITY
AND FIND AND FIND IT FIND MYSELF FIND A PLACE WHERE I
COULD TRULY BE ME. AND HE SAID AND I FOUND THIS
CHORUS. AND FROM THE MINUTE I STEPPED
IN TO, YOU KNOW, INTO THE ARTS CENTER I WAS ABLE TO FULLY
AND AUTHENTICALLY EMBRACE ALL OF ME AND THE JOY THAT HE
EXUDES AT EVERY REHEARSAL ON STAGE.
AND WHENEVER YOU JUST MEET WITH HIM AND SPEAK TO HIM IS A
DIRECT EFFECT OF THIS ORGANIZATION AND AND THE FACT
THAT WE EXIST IN THIS CITY. SO THANK YOU SAN FRANCISCO FOR
BEING THE INCREDIBLE BEACON OF LIGHT AND HOPE THAT YOU ARE FOR
PEOPLE ALL AROUND THE WORLD. AND THANK YOU TO THE MEMBERS OF
THE SAN FRANCISCO GAIMAN'S CHORUS THOSE WHO ARE HERE NOW
OUR ALUMNI AND THOSE WHO ARE NO LONGER WITH US FOR CREATING
ANOTHER BEACON OF LIGHT AND HOPE WITHIN THE CITY OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR FOR FOR THE COMMUNITY AND OUR ALLIES.
I KNOW THAT THIS ORGANIZATION WILL CONTINUE FOR ANOTHER 50
YEARS. WELL PAST MY LIFE IN PALM
SPRINGS. BUT I WILL CLOSE TO SAYING IT
HAS BEEN THE HONOR AND WILL FOREVER BE THE HONOR OF MY LIFE
TO HAVE PLAYED SOME SMALL ROLE IN THE LIFE OF THIS
ORGANIZATION. THANK YOU AGAIN FOR YOUR
SUPPORT FOR YOUR LOVE AND FOR THIS INCREDIBLE HONOR.
>> THANK YOU
. I WOULD LOVE THAT.
QUICK, QUICK, QUICK
. >> ALL RIGHT.
WITH THAT, MADAM CLERK, I THINK WE HAVE SOME 3 P.M. SPECIAL
ORDERS TO GO TO. YES, WE DO.
ITEM 19 AND 20. THIS IS A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE
BOARD OF SUPERVISORS CONVENING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE
TODAY TO HOLD A PUBLIC HEARING TO CONSIDER THE RESOLUTION
WHICH IS THE SUBJECT MATTER OF ITEM 22 AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR
OF TRANSPORTATION TO ENTER INTO A LOAN AGREEMENT WITH THE
METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION AS LENDER FOR SAN
FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY PUBLIC
TRANSIT OPERATING PURPOSES UP TO A MAXIMUM PRINCIPAL AMOUNT
OF 200 MILLION FOR A 12 YEAR TERM.
JULY FIRST 2026 THROUGH JUNE 3RD 2038.
PURSUANT TO ASSEMBLY BILL NUMBER 117 SCHEDULED PURSUANT
TO A MOTION NUMBER 20 6-050 APPROVED ON JUNE 9TH 2020 SIXTH
. THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
AS OUR TRANSPORTATION AUTHORITY CHAIR AND MTC REPRESENTATIVE
GIVE ME YOUR NAME, MELGAR RECOUNTED LAST WEEK.
THIS THIS ITEM WAS A LOT OF WORK FROM A LOT OF PEOPLE
AND NOT A CERTAINTY AT ALL OVER MANY YEARS AND THERE WAS A LOT
OF ADVOCACY FROM TRANSPORTATION ADVOCATES AROUND THE BAY AREA
PUSHING FOR THIS GREAT WORK BY SENATORS ARAGON OR AT SENATORS
WIENER AND ARAGON ESPECIALLY OUR WHOLE BAY AREA LEGISLATIVE
CAUCUS. THANK YOU ASSEMBLY MEMBERS
HANEY AND STEPHANIE. ULTIMATELY GOVERNOR NEWSOM
AND HIS STAFF AND THEN OF COURSE THE MTC SPUR ALEESHA
JOHN BAPTIST AND EILEEN MARIANO IN THE MAYOR'S OFFICE THE FOLKS
AT THE MTA DIRECTOR KIRSCHBAUM SUPERVISOR MELGAR.
SO THERE WERE A LOT OF MOMENTS WHEN IT DIDN'T SEEM LIKE WE
WERE TO GET HERE AND YOU DID GET US HERE AND THAT IS A VERY
VERY GOOD THING FOR SAN FRANCISCO AND OUR TRIP AND THE
BAY AREA AND OUR TRANSPORTATION SYSTEM AND SO WITH THAT I'LL
INVITE JUDSON TRUE TO COME ON UP SAY SOME TELL US WHAT'S
GOING ON HERE. >> WHAT ARE WE VOTING ON?
THANK YOU VERY MUCH PRESIDENT MAILMAN, MEMBERS OF THE BOARD.
GOOD AFTERNOON. JUDSON DREW CHIEF OF STAFF
AND DIRECTOR OF EXTERNAL AFFAIRS AT THE S.F. MTA.
IT IS A THIS IS A KEY MOMENT IN A VERY LONG JOURNEY TO GET
THIS TO GET THIS LOAN APPROVED .
THIS LOAN IS A KEY PART OF THE TWO YEAR BUDGET THAT THE MTA
BOARD APPROVED IN APRIL AND THAT THE BUDGET COMMITTEE
HEARD OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS HEARD A
PRESENTATION ON IN MAY. I WILL BE BRIEF AND BE
AVAILABLE FOR QUESTIONS AND I DO WANT TO START OUT JUST
ECHOING PRESIDENT EDELMAN'S YOU KNOW, DEEP THANKS TO EVERYONE
WHO WAS INVOLVED IN IN SECURING THIS EFFORT FROM ELECTED
OFFICIALS TO ALL OF THE GRASSROOTS SUPPORTERS
ESPECIALLY WHO SHOWED UP FOR THE RALLY AT THE END OF SESSION
LAST LATE SUMMER LAST YEAR WHEN IT LOOKED LIKE THE LOAN MIGHT
NOT SURVIVE AS A CONCEPT. AND MAYOR LURIE WAS VERY
INVOLVED AS WELL AND WE VERY MUCH APPRECIATE HIS EFFORTS
AND THE EFFORTS OF EVERYONE HERE AS WELL AS THE STATE
DELEGATION. YOU MENTIONED.
I'LL GO VERY BRIEFLY THROUGH THE DETAILS OF THE LOAN.
SO THE LOAN WAS APPROVED AS I SAID BY THE MTA BOARD AS PART
OF THE TWO YEAR BUDGET AND THAT $200 MILLION FROM THE LOAN IS
AN IMPORTANT SET OF REVENUE FOR THE FIRST YEAR OF THAT TO YOUR
BUDGET. WHILE WE WAIT AND ANTICIPATE
LONG TERM REVENUE FROM POSSIBLE BALLOT MEASURES, THE LOAN WAS
AUTHORIZED BY AND REQUIRED BY ASSEMBLY BILL 101 17 WHICH
REQUIRED THE LOAN TO THE MTC ON OR BEFORE JULY 1ST WHICH IS
COMING UP QUICKLY AND THE TOTAL AMOUNT OF THE LOAN WAS 590
MILLION AND THAT'S DIVIDED AMONG THE FOUR LARGE OPERATORS
IN THE IMMEDIATE BARRIER AREA MUNI, MTA, BART CALTRAIN AND AC
TRANSIT. >> THE TERMS OF THE LOAN THE
LOAN GOES TO MTC AND THEN MTC DIVIDES IT TO THE OPERATORS.
THE LOANS WILL EACH HAVE A 12 YEAR TERM WITH TWO YEARS OF
INTEREST ONLY AND TEN YEARS THAT INCLUDE BOTH INTEREST
IN PRINCIPAL. WE ESTIMATE RIGHT NOW THAT THE
INTEREST PAYMENTS ARE 8 MILLION AND THE ANNUAL PAYMENTS WITH
BOTH INTEREST AND PRINCIPAL ARE ABOUT 30 MILLION.
THERE IS A VARIABLE INTEREST RATE TIED TO A NEW ACRONYM FOR
ME THE SMITH OR THE SURPLUS MONEY INVESTMENT FUND AT THE
STATE LEVEL AND THAT WILL FLUCTUATE.
IT IS A VARIABLE RATE ALL OF THE BOARDS ARE AUTHORIZING
THEIR EXECUTIVE DIRECTORS TO ENTER INTO THE LOAN AND OF
COURSE WE DID THAT WE RECOMMENDED TO THE BOARD TO
AUTHORIZE IT AND WE'RE HERE FOR YOUR AUTHORIZATION TODAY
IN ADVANCE OF THE EXECUTION OF THE AGREEMENT BETWEEN MTC
AND THE STATE AND THEN US AND MTC.
I WENT THROUGH THIS ALREADY ON THE STRUCTURE AND THE AND THE
REPAYMENT TERMS ARE PRESENTED HERE IN A MORE SUMMARY WAY
AND I DID WANT TO MENTION THAT THE REPAYMENT IS SECURED BY A
STATE FUNDING SOURCE THAT WE RECEIVE CALLED STATE TRANSIT
ASSISTANCE OR STAY AND THAT AMOUNT WE GET AS WELL OVER THE
30 MILLION ANNUALLY. AND SO IF FOR SOME REASON WE
DID NOT BUDGET OR PAY FOR THAT 30 MILLION ANNUAL PAYMENT THE
STATE WOULD WITHHOLD OUR STATE FUNDS.
THE OBLIGATION IS ABSOLUTE AND UNCONDITIONAL BUT LIMITED
TO THOSE STATE FUNDS AND WE ARE PERMITTED TO PREPAY THE LOAN
WITH A SHORT NOTICE. THAT'S MY PRESENTATION.
I KNOW YOU HAVE A REPORT FROM THE BUDGET ANALYST AND I'M ALSO
OF COURSE AVAILABLE TO ANSWER ANY QUESTIONS AND I'M HERE WITH
MY COLLEAGUES WHO ARE RAMOS AND ANTHONY BURTON.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
I DON'T SEE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS.
MR. BILA MR. MINOT, ALWAYS GOOD TO NICK MENARD FROM THE L A
REPORTING ON ITEM 20 ON YOUR AGENDA.
THIS IS A RESOLUTION THAT WOULD AUTHORIZE THE DIRECTOR OF
TRANSPORTATION TO ENTER INTO A LOAN AGREEMENT WITH THE
METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION.
THE LOAN HAS A 12 YEAR TERM AND A VALUE OF UP TO $200
MILLION. WE SHOWED THE LOAN TERMS ON
PAGE THREE OF OUR REPORT AND THEN THE FISCAL IMPACT ALSO
ON PAGE THREE YOU CAN SEE THAT MTA IS BUDGETING $8 MILLION
IN EACH OF THE NEXT TWO YEARS FOR DEBT SERVICE ON THE LOAN
AND THEN WOULD HAVE TO REPAY PRINCIPAL AND INTEREST OVER A
TEN YEAR PERIOD THAT ENDS JUNE 3RD 2038.
MTA IS BUDGETING ABOUT $30 MILLION A YEAR IN DEBT SERVICE
PAYMENTS AND AS WAS MENTIONED BY MTA STAFF, THE LOAN IS
SECURED BY STATE TRANSIT ASSISTANCE FUNDS MTA RECEIVES
ABOUT $65 MILLION A YEAR IN THOSE REVENUES AND SO THE
LOAN PAYMENTS REPRESENT ABOUT HALF OF THAT FUNDING.
>> THE CHARTER ALSO REQUIRES THAT MTA IDENTIFY A LOCAL
SOURCE OF FUNDING FOR ANY DEBT IT TAKES ON IN THIS CASE THE
LOCAL SOURCE OF FUNDING IS TO GENERAL FUND TRANSFERS TO MTA
WHICH EXCEEDS $600 MILLION A YEAR OVER THE NEXT FIVE YEARS.
SO THAT DOES FULFILL THAT CHARTER REQUIREMENT.
AND THEN FINALLY I'LL JUST NOTE ON PAGE FOUR OF OUR REPORT WE
DISCUSS HOW THIS LOAN IS ABOUT 13% OF MTA IS OPERATING
REVENUES NEXT YEAR AND THE BUDGET THAT IT'S BEEN APPROVED
BY MTA AND THE SECOND YEAR ASSUMES PASSAGE OF TWO NEW
REVENUES SOURCES ONE THE REGIONAL SALES TAX AND THEN
ALSO THE PARCEL TAX WHICH TOGETHER WOULD PROVIDE MTA OVER
$300 MILLION IN REVENUE STARTING IN THE SECOND YEAR OF
THE BUDGET AND 2728. SO THE PURPOSE OF THIS LOAN IS
REALLY TO PROVIDE INTERIM FUNDING FOR MTA TO GET THROUGH
NEXT YEAR AND TO THOSE NEW FUNDING SOURCES BECOME
AVAILABLE. HOWEVER IF THE REVENUE MEASURES
DON'T PASS MTA WILL STILL BE LIABLE FOR THIS LOAN AND WOULD
HAVE TO MAKE CUTS TO ITS SERVICES IN ADDITION TO ITS
$1.5 BILLION OF OPERATING REVENUES, MTA HAS ABOUT $300
MILLION IN FUND BALANCE AND BUDGET RESERVES THAT IT CAN
USE TO SMOOTH OVER THE TRANSITION TO A LOWER REVENUE
ENVIRONMENT. >> BUT WE DO RECOMMEND APPROVAL
OF ITEM 20. >> RIGHT?
THANK YOU MR. MINARD. >> COACH SUPERVISOR JEN THANK
YOU PRESIDENT MENDHAM IN JUST WANTED TO UNDERSTAND SHOULD
THIS IS WITH THE US SO ROUGHLY RIGHT NOW THE 70 HAS PUT ASIDE
ABOUT $8 MILLION IN YOUR BUDGET PROJECTED BUDGET FOR THE NEXT
TWO FISCAL OR FISCAL YEARS TO COME AND IN THE NEXT 12 YEARS
AND WITH THE ASSUMPTION THAT YOU'RE GOING TO MAKE A $31
MILLION ANNUAL PAYMENT BECAUSE IT'S ALSO TO ASSUME THAT
PASSAGE OF TO REVENUE MEASURE BOTH THE PARCEL TAX AND THE
REGIONAL SALES TAX UPCOMING HOW WE UNDERSTAND SHOULD SHOULD WE
AND I THINK IF I UNDERSTAND CORRECTLY FROM YOUR
PRESENTATION AND I DON'T SEE IT ON THE LEGISLATIVE FILE IS THAT
IT SEEMS LIKE YOU'RE ALSO ASSUMING IF THE CITY MUST
DEFAULT ON THE PAYMENT THEN THEY ARE GOING TO WITH HOW WELL
THE STATE IT'S GOING TO WITHHOLD A REVENUE FUND AND HOW
MUCH IS THAT YET? >> YES SUPERVISOR CHAN IF THE
MTA DID NOT PAY MTC THE REQUIRED PAY PAYMENT OF
INTEREST AND PRINCIPAL THEN MTC WOULD ESSENTIALLY WITHHOLD THE
STATE TRANSIT ASSISTANCE MONEY THAT WE GET FROM THE STATE
AND AS MR. MINARD SAID THAT IS ABOUT DOUBLE WHAT WE EXPECT THE
ANNUAL LOAN PAYMENT TO BE. SO THERE ISN'T A SCENARIO WHERE
WE WOULD DEFAULT, IT WOULD SIMPLY BE THAT ANOTHER FUND
SOURCE WOULD BE WITHHELD AND THE AGENCY WOULD YOU KNOW,
HAVE TO DEAL WITH THAT LACK OF FUNDING AND WHAT IS THE TERMS
AND CONDITIONS? WELL, WE HAVE 15 DAYS OF NOTICE
THAT WE CAN'T MAKE THE PAYMENT .
ARE THERE ARE THAT WITHIN THE AGREEMENTS?
ARE THERE TERMS AND CONDITIONS THAT WE HAVE A PROCESS TO
POTENTIALLY EITHER APPEAL TO AND BE ABLE TO GO THROUGH A
NEGOTIATION AND SAY WE COULD PERHAPS ASK FOR LOAN
FORGIVENESS AND YOU KNOW ALL THAT A CHURCH AND FORGIVENESS
IS A IS AN AMAZING THING AND WE WOULD CERTAINLY WELCOME
FORGIVENESS OF THE LOAN IN THE FUTURE.
>> BUT THAT WOULD REQUIRE, YOU KNOW, A FURTHER ACT
IN SACRAMENTO. BUT WE WOULD, YOU KNOW, WELCOME
THAT AND CONTINUE TO ADVOCATE FOR THAT WITH ALL OF OUR
PARTNERS. BUT WE WE THE 15 DAY NOTICE
JUST TO CLARIFY BRIEFLY WOULD IS A NOTICE OF PREPAYMENT.
SO IF WE DECIDE THAT WE ARE ABLE TO PREPAY A PORTION OF THE
LOAN AMOUNT OF THE PRINCIPAL THAT WE JUST PROVIDE THE NOTICE
IN ORDER TO PREPAY THAT UNDERSTOOD SO CURRENTLY IN THE
LONG AGREEMENT THERE IS NO WRITTEN IN MECHANISM OF HOW THE
CITY MAY APPROACH THE STATE FOR A POTENTIAL APPEAL OR POTENTIAL
PROCESS TO TO OBTAIN LOAN FORGIVENESS.
THAT'S CORRECT YOUR HAND THROUGH BECAUSE THERE'S NO
THERE'S NOTHING THAT WE WOULD DO IN THE LOAN AGREEMENT THAT
WOULD WOULD HAVE ANY FORCE OF LAW OR OR FORCE OF FORCE OF LAW
IN THE FUTURE ANY ANY EFFORT TO FORGIVE THE LOAN WOULD BE A
FUTURE LEGISLATIVE EFFORT A BUDGET BUDGETARY EFFORT AT THE
STATE LEVEL UNDERSTOOD. I MEAN I THINK WE HAVE A
SIMILAR ON THE LOCAL LEVEL TO JUST I JUST WANTED TO
UNDERSTAND AND CLARIFY. I APPRECIATE IT.
THANK YOU. I DO I AM IN SUPPORT OF THIS
LONG I THINK IT'S IN PAWN. IT'S CRITICAL.
WE NEED IT AND I APPRECIATE ALL OUR STATE LEGISLATURE
AND DELEGATES AND AS WELL AS THE GOVERNOR APPROVING THIS
LOAN AND OF COURSE ALL THE HARD WORK FROM US OF MTA AND OUR
AND OF COURSE MAYOR LEARY AND HIS TEAM I'M REALLY PLEASED
TO SEE THAT WE HAVE TODAY'S TERMS AND CONDITIONS OF THE
LONG AGREEMENT I KNOW IS ASSUMING THAT WE WILL HAVE THE
PASSAGE OF THE PASO AND A REGIONAL SALES TAX.
NONETHELESS THIS IS COME AT A CRITICAL TIME FOR FOR OUR
PUBLIC TRANSIT AGENCY AND WE NEED IT MORE THAN EVER.
>> SO THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THE WORK.
THANK YOU. >> SUPERVISOR MELGAR THANK YOU
FOR YOUR QUESTIONS CHAIR CHAN AND THANK YOU PRESIDENT THANKS
TO STAFF FOR THE PRESENTATION. IN ADDITION TO ALL THE PEOPLE
THAT WE THINK TO MAKE THIS HAPPEN I JUST WANTED TO
UNDERSCORE WHAT A UNUSUAL COLLABORATIVE EFFORT IT WAS TO
GET HERE WITH ALL OF OUR NEIGHBORS AND IT REQUIRED
PUTTING ASIDE OUR DIFFERENCES THAT HAVE ARISEN OVER THE YEARS
OVER THE OPERATIONS AND COLLABORATION BETWEEN
TRANSIT AGENCIES AND ALL ROWING IN THE SAME DIRECTION BECAUSE
WE NEEDED TO DO THAT. AND I THINK THAT THAT ALSO SETS
US UP WELL IN THE COLLABORATION THAT WE ARE ENGAGING IN TO GET
THE REGIONAL SALES TAX MEASURE PASSED AND SO I JUST WANTED TO
YOU KNOW IN ADDITION TO THANKING ALL THE COMMUNITY
ADVOCATES THAT PUT PRESSURE ON THE STATE TO MAKE THIS HAPPEN,
I WANTED TO THANK ALL MY COLLEAGUES ON THE EMPTY SEA
AND ALL OF THE BOARDS OF THE REGIONAL TRANSIT AGENCIES THAT
ALL COLLABORATED IN MAKING THIS HAPPEN AND I HOPE THAT WE GET
YOUR SUPPORT. THANK YOU.
>> GILL THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR MCGUIRE.
THANK YOU. MR. TRUE LET'S GO TO PUBLIC
COMMENT ON THIS ITEM. >> THE FLOOR IS NOW OPEN FOR
ANY MEMBER OF THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD
SPECIFIC TO ITEM 20 WHICH IS THE RESOLUTION THAT AUTHORIZES
THE DIRECTOR OF TRANSPORTATION TO ENTER INTO A LOAN AGREEMENT
WITH THE METROPOLITAN TRANSPORTATION COMMISSION AS
LENDER FOR SAN FRANCISCO MUNICIPAL TRANSPORTATION AGENCY
FOR PUBLIC TRANSIT OPERATING PURPOSES ARE THERE ANY SPEAKERS
? >> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT.
ALL RIGHT. PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED
AND THE MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD AND IS NOW FILED.
AND LET'S CONSIDER FOR ITEM 20. >> MADAM CLERK, CAN YOU CALL
THE ROLL ON ITEM 20 ON ITEM 20 SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD MAHMOOD I
SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI RANDLEMAN I SUPERVISOR MELGAR
MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SAUTER SAUTER I SUPERVISOR CHERYL
CHERYL EYES SUPERVISOR WALTON I WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG I WONG
I SUPERVISOR CHEN I CHIN I SUPERVISOR CHIN CHIN I
AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY I THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK LET'S GO TO
OUR NEXT 3 P.M. SPECIAL ORDER PLEASE CALL ITEM 21 ITEM 21 IS
A PUBLIC HEARING OF THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO CONVENE
IN THE SETTING AS A COMMITTEE OF THE WHOLE TODAY JUNE 16TH TO
CONSIDER THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH'S BUDGET REDUCING
MEDICAL AND HEALTH CARE SERVICES PROVIDED BY THE CITY
AND COUNTY FOR FISCAL YEARS 2026 THROUGH 27 AND 2027
THROUGH 28 PURSUANT TO THE CALIFORNIA HEALTH AND SAFETY
CODE SECTION 1442.5 SUB A THANK YOU MADAM CLERK AND AS YOU
INDICATED, OUR CALIFORNIA HEALTH AND SAFETY CODE REQUIRES
THAT BEFORE A COUNTY CAN CLOSE, ELIMINATE OR REDUCE MEDICAL
SERVICES, THIS BOARD OF SUPERVISORS MUST HOLD A HEARING
CALLED A BJORNSEN HEARING TO CONSIDER THE PROPOSED CUTS THE
MAYOR'S PROPOSED FISCAL YEAR 26 TO 28 BUDGET DOES INCLUDE
PROPOSED CUTS TO THE BUDGET AND THEREFORE WE HAVE TO HAVE
THIS HEARING AND AFFORD THE PUBLIC THE OPPORTUNITY TO BE
HEARD ON THE PROPOSED CUTS. WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM THE
DIRECTOR OF PUBLIC HEALTH DANZHAI WHO WILL PRESENT THEN
WE CAN TAKE ANY COMMENTS OR QUESTIONS FROM COLLEAGUES
AND THEN WE WILL HAVE PUBLIC COMMENT DIRECTOR SIDE THANK YOU
MR. PRESIDENT. GOOD AFTERNOON.
GOOD AFTERNOON. I'M DAN TSAI, THE DIRECTOR OF
THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH.
THANK YOU ALL FOR BEING HERE. AND TO MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC
AND OTHERS WHO ALL GIVE I THINK VERY IMPORTANT TESTIMONY
AND COMMENT SHORTLY ON THE BUDGET.
I'M GOING TO GO THROUGH JUST A LITTLE CONTEXT OF WHAT OUR
STATUTORY OBLIGATION IS HERE TO MAKE SURE WE'RE NOTING THAT FOR
FOR THE RECORD I WILL TALK THROUGH A BRIEF SUMMARY OF THE
BUDGET AND SOME OF THE SPECIFIC BUDGET REDUCTIONS THAT ARE PART
OF THIS HEARING. THERE WAS A SEPARATE BALANCE
AND HEARING ON SOME OTHER SERVICES BUT I BELIEVE YOU WILL
HEAR COMMENT ON THAT AS WELL. SO I WILL ALSO NOTE
AND SUMMARIZE THOSE PIECES AND SO THE BILLING BALANCE
AND HEARING REQUIREMENTS THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA ACT
REQUIRES A PUBLIC HEARING. >> MR. PRESIDENT, AS YOU
DESCRIBED, WHENEVER THERE IS ANY PLAN TO CLOSE, ELIMINATE OR
REDUCE HEALTH AND MEDICAL SERVICES, THE REQUIREMENT IS
FOR THE PERIODS TO HOLD A HEARING IN A RANGE OF FORUMS WE
USE THE HEALTH COMMISSION AND MAY FOR A SET OF PIECES
THAT I'LL TALK ABOUT AND THEN FOR CONTRA ACTED CBO PROVIDER
CUTS THAT IS THE FOCUS OF THIS HEARING.
BUT AGAIN I BELIEVE YOU WILL HEAR A RANGE OF COMMENTS THAT
ARE VERY PERTINENT TO THE BUDGET.
LET'S GO FORWARD. >> SO I THINK WE HAD OUR BUDGET
HEARING OH GOODNESS. WHAT DAY IS IT TODAY?
TUESDAY WHEN WE WERE HERE LAST THURSDAY LAST THURSDAY.
AND SO I'M NOT GOING TO GO THROUGH ALL OF THAT.
BUT JUST TO SET AS CONTEXT THE BIGGEST UNDERLYING PIECE FOR
THE CITY'S BUDGET AND THE BUDGET IS VERY, VERY LARGE CUTS
TO MEDICAID HERE IN CALIFORNIA KNOWN AS MEDI-CAL THAT ARE
PRIMARILY THE RESULT OF MASSIVE UNPRECEDENTED VERY TERRIBLE
CUTS TO THE MEDICAID PROGRAM THAT WERE VOTED ON BY CONGRESS
AND SIGNED BY THE PRESIDENT. THEY RESULT IN THE LARGEST CUTS
TO THE MEDICAID PROGRAM SINCE THE PROGRAMS INCEPTION IN 1965
AND IN ADDITION, THE STATE BUDGET HAS ALSO MADE A SET OF
CUTS TO MEDICAL WHERE NEIGHBORS WITH CERTAIN IMMIGRATION STATUS
WILL BE LOSING THEIR MEDI-CAL ELIGIBILITY AND SO THAT IS
SEVERAL HUNDRED MILLION DOLLARS OF LOST FEDERAL AND STATE
REVENUE TO THE D H IN THIS BUDGET CYCLE THAT ALONE IS A
SUBSTANTIAL PORTION OF THE ENTIRE CITY'S BUDGET DEFICIT
WITH A LOT OF DISCUSSION WITH THE MAYOR OVER THE PAST SEVEN
MONTHS WE MADE A DECISION WHERE D H WOULD NOT HAVE TO BEAR THE
FULL BRUNT OF THAT SEVERAL HUNDRED MILLION DOLLAR
REDUCTION BY OURSELVES IF WE WERE AND I'VE BEEN ON WITH
OTHER COUNTIES IN CALIFORNIA AND PUBLIC HOSPITAL SYSTEMS
ACROSS THE COUNTRY WE WOULD BE LOOKING AT MASSIVE, MASSIVE
CLOSURES TO CLINICAL SERVICES, CBO CONTRACT CUTS, LAYOFFS ALL
ACROSS THE CITY, THINGS THAT ARE ABSOLUTELY UNTENABLE AND SO
THE MAYOR'S BUDGET DIRECTION ASKED ALL CITY DEPARTMENTS TO
FIND REDUCTIONS THAT HELP TO SUPPORT THE SAFETY NET.
>> H THAT'S THE GOOD NEWS. THE BAD NEWS IS WE DON'T FEEL
ANY OF THAT MEANING AND ACTUALLY IF YOU GO TO THE
NEXT PAGE OUR BUDGET IF YOU LOOK AT THIS PAGE THIS IS OUR
BUDGET THAT WE HAVE SUBMITTED. THE BOTTOM ROW IS OUR OVERALL
BUDGET TODAY WE ARE AT $3.3 BILLION BY THE SECOND YEAR OF
THIS BUDGET CYCLE. IF YOU LOOK AT THAT WE WILL BE
AT $3.7 BILLION. THE FIRST ROW IS THE PORTION OF
OUR BUDGET THAT WE RELY ON LOCAL TAX REVENUE FOR GENERAL
FUND. THE REST OF IT WE FUND BASED ON
MEDICAL REIMBURSEMENT, MEDICARE REIMBURSEMENT, THE THINGS THAT
ARE BEING CUT AND SO WE ARE GETTING A 32% INCREASE IN OUR
GENERAL FUND GROWING FROM 779 MILLION TO $1.03 BILLION THAT'S
LARGER BY PERCENT AND DOLLAR AMOUNT THAN ANY OTHER CITY
DEPARTMENT PRECISELY TO HELP PRESERVE THE SAFETY NET.
THE PART ABOUT ALL OF THIS IS NONE OF US FEEL THE BENEFIT OF
THAT BECAUSE THAT MASSIVE INCREASE IS SIMPLY TO BACKFILL
AND OFFSET CUTS TO OFFSET THE CUTS FROM THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AND FROM THE STATE IN OUR BUDGET DOES ASSUME FOR
EXAMPLE WE ARE GOING TO PROVIDE HEALTH CARE COVERAGE
AND SUPPORT TO OUR NEIGHBORS WHO LOSE THEIR MEDI-CAL BECAUSE
OF THEIR IMMIGRATION STATUS. WE WILL SEE THEM AT THE
GENERAL. WE WILL BRING THEM COVER THEM
THROUGH HEALTHY SAN FRANCISCO. WE'LL MAKE SURE OUR CLINICS
AND OUR COMMUNITY CLINICS, OUR CBOS ARE ABLE TO SEE THOSE
FOLKS. BUT WE WILL ABSORB ALL OF THAT
PURE GENERAL FUND DOLLARS BECAUSE THE STATE AND FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT HAVE STEPPED BACK FROM THOSE PIECES.
MANY COUNTIES WERE ON THE FRONT OF SAN FRANCISCO GENERAL
HOSPITAL THE OTHER WEEK INCLUDING OUR UNION PARTNERS
ADVOCATING THAT THE STATE NEEDS TO STEP IN TO HELP US HERE.
WE AS THE COUNTY CANNOT DIG OUT OF ALL OF THESE CUTS BY
OURSELVES. SO THAT'S THE UNDERLYING
CONTEXT AND WE HAVE A LARGE BUDGET INCREASE RELATIVE TO
GENERAL FUND SUPPORT BUT WE WILL NOT FEEL THAT IMPACT
AND WE HAVE HAD TO MAKE MANY DIFFICULT DECISIONS AS EVEN
IN SPITE OF THAT BECAUSE OF THE FEDERAL AND STATE CUTS.
>> NEXT PAGE PLEASE. SO THE FOCUS OF THIS BALANCING
IS ON THE CBO CONTRACT PIECES. I WILL THEN BRIEFLY MENTION
WHERE WE WERE ON THE FTE IS AND SOME PIECES THAT I BELIEVE
YOU'LL HEAR SOME COMMENT ON AS WELL.
SO A PORTION OF OUR CONTROL OF OUR BUDGET AS I SAID WE BOTH
GOT A BUNCH AND WE'VE HAD TO TIGHTEN OUR BELTS AND WE'VE
CALLED ON THE STATE TO HELP STEP IN.
BUT JUST IF YOU ZOOM OUT WE HAD TO IDENTIFY $20 MILLION OF
REDUCTIONS TO OUR CBO CONTRACTS, OUR COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATIONS AND I JUST THE 20 MILLION YOU SEE HERE IS OFF OF
A GROWING NUMBER. SO WE WOULD HAVE OUR CBO
CONTRACTS WOULD HAVE GROWN BY $100 MILLION IN THIS BUDGET
CYCLE AFTER THE $20 MILLION REDUCTION OUR CBO CONTRACTS
GROW BY $80 MILLION. NEXT PAGE PLEASE.
ONE PIECE I WANT TO MENTION IS BECAUSE THERE HAD BEEN A LOT OF
DISCUSSIONS WITH OUR COMMUNITY ON THE HIV PIECE AND I WANT TO
NOTE AND ACKNOWLEDGE BOTH REAL CHALLENGING CUTS WE'VE HAD TO
MAKE AND ALSO NOTE HOW HARD WE AS A TEAM AND MY STAFF WHO ARE
DEEPLY COMMITTED TO THIS WORK, HOW WE FOUGHT TO DO EVERYTHING
POSSIBLE TO MAINTAIN AS MUCH FUNDING AND SUPPORT FOR HIV AS
POSSIBLE. ONE REALLY IMPORTANT PIECE ON
THE HIV CONTEXT THIS CHART ILLUSTRATES A STEADY DECREASE
OF FEDERAL GOVERNMENT FUNDING FOR HIV IN SAN FRANCISCO OVER
THE COURSE OF 25 YEARS. IT'S A $23 MILLION REDUCTION
IN RYAN WHITE PART A FUNDING IN THE CITY NEXT PAGE WE AS THE
CITY HISTORICALLY HAVE MADE A COMMITMENT FOR HIV SERVICES TO
BACKFILL THROUGH THE GENERAL FUND.
THOSE LOSS OF FEDERAL REVENUES. AND SO IF YOU LOOK ON THIS
SLIDE THE HIV HEALTH SERVICES WHICH IS FOR HIV TREATMENT THAT
SECOND ROW THE GENERAL FUND BACKFILL THE MAYOR HAS
MAINTAINED THAT WE WILL MAINTAIN THE GENERAL FUND
BACKFILL WHAT YOU SEE THIS YEAR IS $28.7 MILLION THAT'S
BACKFILLING FOR FEDERAL CUTS AND THAT GENERAL FUND BACKFILL
WILL GROW TO $30 MILLION OR OVERALL HIV TREATMENT SERVICES
WILL INCREASE HIV PREVENTION WHICH THERE ARE REDUCTIONS ON
THAT WE WILL TALK THROUGH AROUND THAT.
BUT IN AGGREGATE EVEN WITH VERY PAINFUL DECISIONS WHICH ARE NOT
WHY ANY OF US DO THIS WORK THE PREVENTION BUCKET DECREASES
FROM 34.5 TO 34 SO WHEN YOU ADD UP OVERALL HIV SPENDING AT THE
DEPARTMENT TODAY WE ARE 84.1 MILLION BY THE SECOND YEAR OF
THIS BUDGET CYCLE WE WILL BE SLIGHTLY MORE THAN WE ARE NOW.
I THINK OUR CBO'S WOULD APPROPRIATELY SAY THAT $300,000
INCREASE ON $84 MILLION DOES NOT KEEP UP WITH INFLATION
AND THE ABILITY TO SERVE FOLKS AND THEY WOULD BE RIGHT ABOUT
THAT AS WELL. BUT BUT IT'S IMPORTANT TO NOTE
JUST WHERE WE ARE WHERE MEANT WE FOUGHT TO MAINTAIN THE
CITY'S GENERAL FUND BACKFILL AND THE MAYOR HAS HAS HAS PUT
HIS SUPPORT BEHIND THAT GENERAL FUND BACKFILL PIECE AS WELL.
SO IF WE GO TO THE NEXT PAGE SO AGAIN THE SUBJECT OF THIS
BALANCING IS ON THE CONTRACT CBO REDUCTIONS.
>> LET ME WALK THROUGH THE OVERALL CBO FUNDING LINES
AND WE'VE HIGHLIGHTED THE ITEMS THAT ARE REQUIRED THE BALANCE
IN AND THEN WE'LL BRIEFLY WALK THROUGH EACH THAT I'LL COME TO
SOME OF THE OTHER ITEMS AND THE CLINIC CLOSURES THAT HAVE COME
UP. SO ON THE CONTRACT REDUCTIONS I
MENTIONED $20 MILLION THE EXACT NUMBER IS $19.9 MILLION.
AGAIN THESE ARE REDUCTIONS TO OUR GENERALLY NONPROFIT
PROVIDERS IN THE COMMUNITY. THEY'RE VERY IMPORTANT PARTNERS
WITH US. MOST OF THE $20 MILLION WE
WORKED REALLY HARD TO IDENTIFY THROUGH THINGS THAT WOULD NOT
IMPACT SERVICES. SO IF YOU LOOK AT THIS FIRST
BUCKET 7.148 MILLION THERE ARE A RANGE OF CONTRACT
RENEGOTIATIONS THAT WILL NOT IMPACT SERVICES.
I WANT TO COMMEND AS ONE EXAMPLE UCSF JEFF HERE WHO IS A
VERY IMPORTANT PARTNER TO US ACROSS THE D H IN SAN FRANCISCO
GENERAL HOSPITAL WE WENT TO THEM, WE SAID THIS IS THE
SITUATION WE'RE IN. WE NEED TO FIND EFFICIENCIES
IN YOUR CONTRACT AND WE DON'T WANT THAT TO IMPACT SERVICES.
TO THEIR CREDIT THEY LEANED IN, THEY'VE WORKED WITH US AROUND
THAT. YOU'LL SEE TWO LINES THERE
ADDING TO $2.795 MILLION THAT WE'VE WORKED ON WITH UCSF.
THOSE ARE THE TYPES OF THINGS THAT WE'VE GONE TO FIRST TO NOT
IMPACT SERVICES ON THE SECOND BUCKET YOU'LL SEE TWO THINGS
HIGHLIGHTED THAT ARE THE SUBJECT OF THIS BALANCE
AND HEARING WHERE WE'VE HAD CHANGES TO FUNDING SOURCES
AND PRIMARILY THE CHANGES TO FUNDING SOURCES.
I WANT TO NOTE FOR THE BALANCE IN PIC WE DID NOT PROPOSE FOR
BUDGET REASONS VARIOUS CUTS TO SOMETHING FUNDED CALLED FUNDED
THROUGH THE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES ACT PROP ONE HERE
IN THE STATE BUT THE STATE HAS MADE A RANGE OF POLICY
DECISIONS WHERE WHAT WE AS A CITY ARE ALLOWED TO FUND WITH
PROP ONE STATE PROP ONE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES ACT
FUNDING HAS CHANGED AND HAS REDUCED A CERTAIN SET OF
SERVICES OF THINGS THAT GO UPSTREAM.
SO YOU WILL SEE A SET OF CONTRACTS LISTED HERE AND ONE
OF THE UPCOMING SLIDES FOR BALANCE AND BECAUSE THEY MEET
THE REQUIREMENT OF LEADING TO A REDUCTION IN SERVICES, THOSE
CONTRACT REDUCTIONS ARE BECAUSE THE STATE THOSE ARE ALL STATE
FUNDED. THE STATE HAS CHANGED THEIR
ALLOCATION CRITERIA AND WHAT WE ARE ALLOWED TO SPEND AS A
RESULT FOR THAT FOR OUR BUDGET PURPOSES WHAT THE STATE ALSO
DID WAS ALLOW FOR INCREASED USE FOR HOUSING AND HOUSING
SUPPORTS AND SO WE CERTAINLY TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THAT.
THAT'S HOW WE HAVE FUNDING IN HERE.
BUT THAT IS WHY THE BEHAVIOR HEALTH SERVICES ACT PROP ONE
FUNDING THAT IS A STATE PIECE WIDE FACTORS INTO THIS
DISCUSSION RELATIVE TO THE BUDGET.
NEXT PAGE PLEASE. AND THEN ON THIS PAGE YOU'LL
SEE A RANGE OF LINES ALL HIGHLIGHTED HERE IN BLUE.
THIS IS A PAGE OF THE SUM TOTAL OF OUR REMAINING CBO REDUCTIONS
FOR THIS BUDGET CYCLE YOU'LL SEE A SET OF THINGS AROUND HARM
REDUCTION SUPPLY POLICY. I WALK THROUGH THESE SHORTLY
AND A RANGE OF OTHER PIECES HERE THE BLUE ONES ARE THE ONES
THAT HAVE SOME SORT OF IMPACT TODAY THAT ARE PART OF THE
BALANCE AND NOTABLY I WANT TO KNOW BECAUSE I'VE HAD MANY
DISCUSSIONS WITH OUR CBO PARTNERS AND SOME OF THE BOARD
ON WHAT WE CALL OUR HEALTH ACCESS POINTS A REALLY CRITICAL
PIECE FOR HIV PREVENTION. THERE'S A 6% PERCENT 6.6%
REDUCTION IN THOSE SERVICES WITH OUR HAP PARTNERS.
WE DO NOT HAVE THOSE CUTS. THE 6.6% GO INTO EFFECT UNTIL
NEXT FISCAL YEAR JULY 1ST OF 2027.
WE HOPE TO WORK WITH THEM TO DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE TO MINIMIZE
SERVICE IMPACT INCLUDING MEDICAID BILLING AND SO THEY
ARE NOT IN THE BALANCE AND NOW BUT WE WILL HAVE TO DO A
BALANCE AND IF IN THE WORK OVER THE NEXT YEAR THERE ARE ACTUAL
SERVICE REDUCTIONS AS A RESULT. SO THAT IS WHY THAT IS NOT
HIGHLIGHTED IN BLUE. OKAY.
SO THAT'S THE OVERALL ZOOM OUT OF WHICH PIECES ARE HERE AS
PART OF THE BUDGET. NEXT PAGE PLEASE.
RAGHU AND I THINK I ALREADY MENTIONED THIS PIECE AROUND BE
IT JUST SAY AND AGAIN TODAY'S OKAY SO TODAY'S HEARINGS ARE
ABOUT THE CONTRACTED PIECE WHAT I'M GOING TO SPEND A MOMENT ON
IF WE GO TO THE NEXT PAGE IS WE HELD A BALANCE IN ON MAY MAY
18TH FOR PROGRAMMATIC CHANGES AT THE D H THAT INVOLVE OUR OWN
STAFF. AND SO ONE THING I WANT TO NOTE
FROM A BUDGET STANDPOINT IS WE HAD TO REDUCE 130 FTE BUDGETED
FTE POSITIONS IN THIS BUDGET. MY DIRECTION TO OUR LEADERSHIP
TEAM AND STAFF WAS TO DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE EVEN IF WE
DIDN'T LAND AT THE PERFECT POLICY ANSWERS TO MINIMIZE
LAYOFFS AND TO HELP PRESERVE CIVIL SERVICE STAFF ABILITY TO
MAINTAIN THEIR JOBS ALL OF THAT IN THE H AND SO OF THE 134
YEARS WE DID 100 VACANCIES OF ELIMINATION WE DID ROUGHLY 25
TO 27 REASSIGNMENTS AND WE ARE STILL WORKING WITH OUR LABOR
PARTNERS AND UNIONS. WE'RE DOWN TO TWO LAYOFFS NOW
OUT OF 8000 STAFF AT THE H. I THINK WE HAVE A LITTLE BIT
MORE OF CONTINUED WORK TO DO WITH OUR LABOR PARTNERS AROUND
THAT THE CLINIC CONSOLIDATIONS AND I SEE SOME OF OUR STAFF
AND MAYBE SOME PATIENTS IN OTHER AREAS.
I WANT TO RECOGNIZING THAT YOU WILL HEAR FROM THEM.
I THINK IT IS IMPORTANT TO HEAR THAT TESTIMONY FROM THEM FOR
FOLKS TO UNDERSTAND THE IMPACT OF THIS BUDGET AND WHAT IT HAS
ON REAL PEOPLE. WE MADE A DECISION A VERY
DIFFICULT DECISION TO CONSOLIDATE A SET OF CLINICS
THAT ARE LOWER VOLUME AND HAVE THE STAFF NO LAYOFFS BUT BE
REASSIGNED TO OTHER CLINICS, CONTINUING TO SEE PATIENTS
AND TO HELP WORK THROUGH MAKE SURE WE COULD TRANSITION
PATIENTS. WE HELD THAT BALANCE AND ON MAY
18TH I WOULD ACKNOWLEDGE A FEW THINGS TOO BECAUSE I KNOW SOME
OF THE TEAM AND I THINK SOME OF THE OTHER COMMUNITY BASED
ORGANIZATIONS IN THE SPACE ARE HERE.
YOU WILL HEAR ACCURATELY THAT THE PEOPLE THAT ARE CARED FOR
IN THESE CLINICS ARE DEEPLY, DEEPLY VULNERABLE.
IN SOME CASES THEY HAVE NOT WANTED TO GET CARE AND OTHER
PARTS OF THE DELIVERY SYSTEM THEY HAVE LONG STANDING
RELATIONSHIPS WITH CLINICIANS AND THE PLACES THAT THEY ARE
GOING AROUND THAT AND THESE ARE VERY, VERY DIFFICULT PIECES
AND THEY WOULD BE RIGHT ON EVERY SINGLE ONE OF THOSE
PIECES. AND SO THIS IS NOT WHY I TOOK
THIS JOB A YEAR AGO AND I HOPE YOU ARE SEEING AS WE TRY TO
SOLVE THE BUDGET ONE GOAL I HAVE HAD IS TO MINIMIZE LAYOFFS
AND TO MAKE SURE WE CAN REASSIGN THAT HAS LED TO THINGS
WHERE WE IN A FACT BASED WAY TRIED TO MAKE REASSIGNMENTS BUT
YOU WILL HEAR ACCURATELY THE IMPACT OF THAT AND THAT IS
IMPORTANT FOR EVERYBODY TO KNOW AND TO SEE AND TO RECOGNIZE
AND I'M APPRECIATIVE THAT THEY ARE HERE TODAY AND YOU WILL
HEAR FROM THEM ON THE SPECIFICS.
I WON'T WALK THROUGH IT BECAUSE THE REST OF THIS I THINK TO
SATISFY THE STATUTORY REQUIREMENT IS TO MAKE SURE WE
ARE LEAVING SPACE FOR PUBLIC COMMENT.
THERE'S NO ACTION NEEDED ON THAT FROM THE BOARD TODAY BUT
THE STATUTORY REQUIREMENT IS WE HOLD PUBLIC COMMENT AND THEN WE
ARE ABLE TO CONSIDER ALL THOSE COMMENTS AS WE WORK THROUGH
IMPLEMENTING THESE PIECES. YOU'LL SEE HERE A RANGE OF
SUBSTANCE USE AND OTHER RELATED SERVICES AND I CAN GET INTO
DETAILS AS NEEDED AROUND THAT NEXT PAGE.
ROG, THE SET OF CHANGES AND SAFER USE SUPPLY POLICY
AND A RANGE OF OTHER PROGRAM REDUCTIONS FOR SOME OF OUR
LARGER CONTRACTORS THAT WE'VE BEEN WORKING WITH NEXT PAGE
AND I'M TRYING TO GO THROUGH QUICKLY JUST TO THEN FINISH
WHAT WE ARE REQUIRED TO DO HERE AND THEN TURN IT OVER TO
COMMENT AND QUESTIONS THIS PAGE I JUST WANT TO BE REALLY CLEAR
THE SERVICES HERE ARE REALLY IMPORTANT SERVICES.
THESE ARE WITHIN THE STATE PROP ONE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH SERVICES
ACT OTHERWISE KNOWN AS BE HSA CHANGES WHERE THE STATE IS
REDUCING THE AMOUNT OF FUNDING THAT WE GET FOR WHAT OUR
UPSTREAM KIND OF PREVENTATIVE TYPE OF SERVICES.
AND SO THIS IS WHERE OUR TEAM HAD TO MAKE DIFFICULT DECISIONS
BASED ON THAT NEW STATE DIRECTION.
THEY ARE NOT THINGS THAT WE DID OF OUR OWN VOLITION FROM A
BUDGET STANDPOINT BUT WE ARE INCLUDING THEM HERE BECAUSE
THEY ARE EFFECTUATED ON THE SAME BUDGET CYCLE IN OUR
INTERSECTING HERE AND THAT IS THERE ONE MORE PAGE NOW?
THANK YOU. OKAY.
WITH THAT I JUST WANT TO THANK MANY OF OUR COMMUNITY PROVIDERS
STAFF OTHERS WHO HAVE VERY VOCALLY EXPRESSED THEIR
THOUGHTS AND I ON THAT RESPECT THAT HEAR THAT AND ALSO OUR
STAFF WHO NONE OF THEM GOT INTO THIS WORK FOR PUBLIC SERVICE TO
WORK ON PROBABLY THE MOST DIFFICULT BUDGET THAT HAS HAD
AS I UNDERSTAND FROM STAFF THAT HAVE BEEN HERE SINCE 2008.
AND SO IT'S TAKING A TOLL ON EVERYONE NOT LEAST OF WHICH
IMPACTED STAFF AND PROGRAMS AND I APPRECIATE THEIR
PERSEVERANCE AND TRYING TO FIND MY FRAMEWORK HAS BEEN DO THE
LEAST HARM POSSIBLE AND WE NEED HELP FROM THE STATE TO HELP US.
WE AS THE COUNTY IN SAN FRANCISCO CANNOT OFFSET EVERY
FEDERAL AND STATE CUT BY OURSELVES.
SO WITH THAT I THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU DIRECTOR SIGH I DO
NOT SEE ANYONE IN THE QUEUE AND SO WE WILL OPEN THIS UP TO
PUBLIC COMMENT. THANK YOU MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC
IF YOU ARE HERE TO PARTICIPATE IN THE BALANCE IN HEARING
BEFORE THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS TO PROVIDE YOUR COMMENTS ON THE
REDUCTIONS OF OR CUTS FROM THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH
THIS IS YOUR OPPORTUNITY. WE ARE SETTING THE TIMER FOR
TWO MINUTES AS FROM THE PRESIDENT.
IF YOU ARE STEPPING UP TO THE PODIUM PLEASE NOTICE THAT THERE
IS A TIMER ON THE PODIUM WHICH WILL ALLOW YOU TO SPEAK FOR
TIME FOR TWO MINUTES AND THAT IS THE PODIUM TO YOUR TO YOUR
RIGHT SIR. >> THAT PODIUM HAS THE TIMER.
YOU ARE WELCOME TO USE EITHER PODIUM AND BEGIN YOUR TIME NOW
. GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS. MY NAME IS OMAR FALLING I'M TO
SAN FRANCISCO FIELD DIRECTOR OF SEIU LOCAL 1021 REPRESENTING
FRONTLINE PUBLIC HEALTH WORKERS AND MANY EMPLOYEES ACROSS THE
CITY REGARDING THE DEPARTMENT OF PUBLIC HEALTH BUDGET
REDUCTION, SEIU STRONGLY BELIEVE THAT THIS PROPOSED CUT
NOT ADMINISTRATIVE ADJUSTMENT THEY ARE DISMANTLING OF
CRITICAL LIFESAVING SERVICES CLOSING CLINIC LIKE THIS
SOUTHEAST MICHIGAN GERIATRIC CLINICS ELIMINATE TO ONLY
OUTPATIENT PSYCHIATRIC CARE ESPECIALLY SERVING OLDER ADULTS
IN THE CITY. THERE IS NO EQUIVALENT SYSTEM
WAITING TO ABSORB THIS PATIENT. SIMILARLY YOU HAVE CLINIC LIKE
IN AND CALL SERVING HIGHLY SPECIALIZED POPULATION UNHOUSED
YOUTH LGBTQ YOUTH AND YOUNG PEOPLE IN CRISIS WHO CANNOT
SIMPLY BE REDIRECTED INTO GENERAL CARE.
THESE PROPOSALS ALSO DO NOT REPRESENT FISCAL RESPONSIBILITY
WHEN CLINIC LIKE SOUTHEAST MISSION GENERATES A SIGNIFICANT
PORTION OF THEIR REVENUE THROUGH MEDICARE BILLING
CUTTING SERVICES MEAN FORFEITING FEDERAL DOLLARS
WHILE INCREASING DOWNSTREAM COSTS IN EMERGENCY ROOM
HOSPITALIZATION AND CRISIS RESPONSES INSTEAD OF
STABILIZING SERVICE IN THE FRONT IN THE FACE OF THE STATE
LEVEL REDUCTION THE CITY IS LAYERING ADDITIONAL LOCAL CUTS
ON TOP OF ACTUAL HARM TO THE VERY COMMUNITY MOST AT RISK
COMMUNITY BASED ORGANIZATION BUILT OVER A DECADE WITH
TRUSTED PARTNERS LIKE FELTON HEALTH CARE 360 AND OTHER
CANNOT BE REBUILT. WHAT DISMANTLE THE LOSS OF
PROVIDERS RELATIONSHIP AND TRUST WILL IMMEDIATE WOULD
BE IMMEDIATE AND LONG LASTING. THIS CUT WILL AFFECT THOUSANDS
OF RESIDENTS SENIORS PEOPLE EXPERIENCING HOMELESSNESS,
INDIVIDUALS STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE ABUSE AND MENTAL
CONDITION. FOR MANY THERE'S NO REALISTIC
ALTERNATIVE ACCESS TO CARE. WE URGE YOU TO REJECT THIS
REDUCTION AND RESTORE FUNDING. >> DO NOT PASS A BUDGET THAT
CLOSES EVERYTHING. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
SIR. ALL RIGHT.
CAN WE HAVE THE NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE?
>> GOOD AFTERNOON. MY NAME IS FRANCISCO ROBISON
AND I'M A CLINICIAN AT SOUTHEAST MISSION GERIATRIC
SERVICES. I'VE BEEN THERE FOR 25 YEARS.
I'VE SEEN THIS CLINIC GROW AND SUFFER 25 YEARS OF CLOSURE
AFTER ATTEMPTED CLOSURE. AND IT IS MY POSITION THAT IF
YOU ALLOW THIS CLINIC TO BE CLOSED THEN WHILE IT'S DEFINITE
THIS WILL BE THE LAST GERIATRIC OUTPATIENT MENTAL HEALTH CLINIC
FOR OUR SENIORS. THIS IS A POPULATION THAT'S
VERY VULNERABLE THAT ALL OVER 60 ARE WITH MENTAL, PHYSICAL
AND OTHER CONDITIONS THAT THEY NEED THE OUTPATIENT SERVICES
IN THEIR COMMUNITIES. I WILL SAY THAT WE WERE
IDENTIFIED FOR CLOSURE BECAUSE THEY SAY WE WERE LOW VOLUME.
>> IN FACT THOSE STATISTICS THOSE NUMBERS WERE COMPLETELY
INCORRECT. THEY'VE BEEN SINCE RAISED TO
DOUBLE WHAT THEY SAID WHEN THEY TOLD US WE HAD TO BE CLOSED
BECAUSE OF LOW VOLUME. >> I WOULD ARGUE THAT THOSE
INACCURATE KEYS IN THEIR EPIC SYSTEM WHERE WE ARE NOW
CURRENTLY BILLING THAT WE JUST STARTED BILLING ABOUT A YEAR
AND A HALF OR SO ARE INACCURATE BECAUSE THERE WAS LITTLE
ATTENTION PAID TO THE KIND OF SERVICES OUTPATIENT MENTAL
HEALTH PROVIDES. AND THUS THERE'S A PERIOD
IN WHICH ALSO THE TO THE POSITIONS THAT ARE FULL TIME
WERE NEW INTERNS AND WE WERE TRAINING THEM APART FROM THE
FACT THAT TWO OF THE CLINICIANS ARE OUT OF THE CLINIC IN TOTAL
. >> OUR CLIENTS ARE BEING TOLD
THAT THEIR SERVICES ARE NOT IMPORTANT, THAT THEIR CARE IS
NOT IMPORTANT. PLEASE PLEASE DON'T ALLOW THIS
CLINIC TO BE CLOSED. WE BILL MEDICARE MEDICARE IS
NOT BEING CLOSED IS NOT BEING TERMINATED AT ALL.
IT'S 80% OF OUR BILLING. AND SAN FRANCISCO'S ONLY
GETTING OLDER. ABOUT A THIRD OF SAN FRANCISCO
IS GOING TO BE OVER 60 IN THE NEXT FEW YEARS.
WE ARE THE LAST OLDER ADULT MENTAL HEALTH CLINIC.
>> YOU'RE ESSENTIALLY TERMINATING ELIMINATING
CLIENTS. >> AND IF WE HAD SAN FRANCISCO
WE SAID THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND INTERRUPT.
>> WHAT CAN WE HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER?
PLEASE BE BEFORE THE NEXT SPEAKER BEGINS.
>> I WILL SAY WE HAVE A BOARD RULE AN APPROVED BOARD RULE
WHICH DOES NOT ALLOW ANY CLAPPING OR BOOING ON ONE SIDE
OR THE OTHER. >> BUT IF YOU MUST PROVIDE SOME
SIGNAL OF SUPPORT YOU ARE WELCOME TO DO YOU WAIVE YOUR
HANDS? >> ALL RIGHT.
WELL THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THAT SUPPORT.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER .
>> OH, HERE YOU GO. MY NAME IS LESLIE.
MANY WHETHER I'M A BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CLINICIAN AT MISSION
SOUTHEAST MICHIGAN GERIATRIC CLINIC.
I'M IMPRESSED BY THE BOARD OF SUPERVISORS.
I USED TO WORK FOR A CONGRESSMAN IN D.C..
>> I'M IMPRESSED BY THE POWER THAT YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO
CHANGE, RECONSTRUCT, HELP OR NOT HELP.
I'M ASKING THAT YOU KEEP OUR CLINIC OPEN BECAUSE I MYSELF AM
A SENIOR AND I KNOW THE IMPACT THAT CLOSING OUR CLINIC WILL
HAVE ON THE SENIORS THAT SIT IN THIS ROOM TODAY.
WE ARE A SPECIALIZED CLINIC THE ONLY ONE AND THE LAST ONE.
>> WE'RE NOT ASKING FOR MUCH. >> OUR BUDGET IS NOT THAT MUCH
. >> WE BILL MEDICARE
AND MEDI-CAL AND THE NUMBERS THAT WE'RE GIVEN TO YOU
ESTEEMED SUPERVISORS WERE WRONG AND THEY CONTINUE TO BE WRONG
BECAUSE THE REPORTING SYSTEM IN EPIC DOES NOT EXIST.
IT IS BEING CREATED. SO I'M ASKING YOU PLEASE I'M
I'VE COME TO A LOT OF THESE DIFFERENT MEETINGS BUT THIS IS
THE ONE THAT I GUESS IS THE MOST IMPACTFUL.
SO I'M ASKING YOU PLEASE WE'RE BEGGING LITERALLY BEGGING THAT
YOU KEEP US OPEN AND LET US PROVIDE THE SERVICES THAT WE
CONTINUE TO PROVIDE FOR OUR SENIORS.
THE ONE THING THAT I HEAR FROM OUR SENIORS MORE THAN ANYTHING
IS THAT THEY FEEL SAFE COMING TO US.
AND FOR A VULNERABLE POPULATION SAFETY IS ALWAYS GOING TO BE
THE MOST IMPORTANT THING. >> THANK YOU FOR LISTENING.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER PLEASE.
>> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS MARNI REGAN LARKIN STREET YOUTH
SERVICES AND CHAIR OF HEZBOLLAH.
WE URGE YOU TO HALT THESE REDUCTIONS AND THE CLOSURE OF
THREE CLINICS THAT POOR AND HOMELESS YOUTH AND ELDERS.
THE MOST THE MOST IN NEED IN THIS CITY DEPEND ON TO
SURVIVE. HOMELESSNESS AND HEALTH ARE
INSEPARABLE. YOUR SERVICE CUTS DON'T SAVE
MONEY. THEY SHIFT THE COST TO
EMERGENCY ROOMS, JAILS AND CRISIS RESPONSE WHILE
WORSENING SUFFERING ON OUR STREETS.
WHEN ACCESS SHRINKS, PEOPLE WITH UNTREATED NEEDS ARE PUSHED
FURTHER FROM CARE AND NOT CLOSER.
HOW DO WE EXPECT PEOPLE TO GET WELL BECOME STABLE
AND SELF-SUFFICIENT? IF WE REDUCE HEALTH SERVICES
AND ACCESS TO CARE NONE OF THIS MAKES SENSE.
THIS IS A POLICY CHOICE. WE NEED CONTINUITY, LOW BARRIER
ACCESS AND TRUST. >> DISRUPTING SERVICES BREAKS
THAT TRUST AND UNWINDS A HARD WON PROGRESS.
THIS IS A POLICY CHOICE. WE HAVE A $400 MILLION FEDERAL
AND STATE RISK RESERVE THAT YOU ALL APPROVED LAST YEAR FOR THIS
PURPOSE. >> PLEASE USE IT AND URGE YOU
TO PROTECT THESE SERVICES AND KEEP THE CLINICS OPEN.
I WORK FOR LARKIN STREET. WE HAVE BEEN OPERATING WE'VE
BEEN HOUSING AND COVERING THE OVERHEAD AT THE YOUTH THE
MICHAEL BAXTER CLINIC FOR DECADES.
>> WE WE PAY FOR ALL THE OVERHEAD PAYS FOR STAFF.
IT IS A HUGE COST SAVING RESOURCE FOR THE CITY AND TO
CLOSE IT FOR VULNERABLE HOMELESS YOUTH AND MINORS IS
UNACCEPTABLE TO ALL OUR CITY'S VALUES DEMAND THAT WE RESPOND
WITH CARE, STABILITY AND DIGNITY NOT RETRENCHMENT.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER WHEN I CAME OUT MY PARENTS AND HAVE ALL THE TOOLS
OR KNOWLEDGE THAT THEY NEEDED TO SUPPORT ME.
>> I WAS DEALING WITH TRANSPHOBIA A FREQUENT
MICROAGGRESSIONS AND INVISIBILITY THAT THEY
HADN'T BEEN TAUGHT TO UNDERSTAND AND IT WAS TAKING A
SIGNIFICANT TOLL ON MY MENTAL HEALTH AND WELL TO LIVE.
>> WHEN WE LOOKED FOR SUPPORT WE FOUND LYRIC WHEN I SHOW UP
AT MY FIRST PUBLIC COMMENT LYRIC WAS THERE TO SUPPORT ME
AND MY FRIENDS. I'VE MET MY CLOSEST FRIENDS AT
THE S.F. LGBT CENTER AND ALWAYS FELT SAFE INSIDE THAT BUILDING.
I'M VERY FORTUNATE IN MY FAMILY AND FINANCIAL SITUATIONS TO
HAVE OTHER OPTIONS SUCH AS THERAPY BUT I CAN STILL COUNT
THE TIMES IN MY LIFE THAT THIS CENTER, THAT HOTLINE OR THAT
ORGANIZATION HAS SAVED ME. I STILL NEEDED THESE RESOURCES
WHICH EMPHASIZES HOW ESSENTIAL AND LIFESAVING THESE
ORGANIZATIONS ARE FOR MYSELF AND EVERYONE ELSE IN MY
COMMUNITY. >> AS LGBTQ PLUS ORGANIZATIONS
ACROSS THE COUNTRY INCLUDING SAN FRANCISCO ARE ALREADY
FACING FEDERAL FUNDING CUTS AND HOSTILITY.
NOW IS NOT THE TIME TO MAKE THESE CUTS.
SAN FRANCISCO A CITY KNOWN FOR ITS RICH HISTORY
AND ACCEPTANCE OF THE LGBTQ PLUS COMMUNITY SHOULD NOT BE
THE ONE TO DEFUND THESE PROGRAMS.
I URGE YOU TO FUND SERVICES LIKE LYRIC AND HELP SAN
FRANCISCO CONTINUE TO BE AS CHRIS VERDUGO EARLIER PUT IT,
THE INCREDIBLE BEACON OF LIGHT AND HOPE THAT WE'VE BEEN FOR
THIS COUNTRY AND THE WORLD. THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER.
>> HELLO, MY NAME IS LESLIE COOPER.
I AM COMING TO YOU WEARING SEVERAL DIFFERENT HATS.
I OWN A CONDO IN SAN FRANCISCO ON THE 1300 BLOCK OF STEVENSON
STREET. >> I AM A CITY AND COUNTY OF
SAN FRANCISCO GBH EMPLOYEE SEIU MEMBER AND I CURRENTLY WORK AS
A SENIOR BEHAVIORAL HEALTH CLINICIAN ON THE STREET HEALTH
TEAM. PROVIDING ESSENTIAL SERVICES TO
FOLKS WHO ARE ON THE STREETS WHO ARE HIGHLY PRIORITIZED.
>> WE NEED SOMEONE SOMEWHERE FOR THEM TO GO.
MOST FOLKS ON THE STREETS ARE HAVING SOME PRETTY SIGNIFICANT
MENTAL HEALTH ISSUES SYMPTOMS AND MANY OF THEM ARE OUR
SPECIALTY POPULATIONS AT EITHER END OF THE AGE SPECTRUM.
I CAN THINK OF FOUR CLIENTS OUT OF 20 WHO ARE EITHER SENIORS OR
TRANSITION AGE YOUTH WHO ARE SEVERELY UNDERSERVED, WHO WE
ARE SPENDING A LOT OF EFFORTS AND ENERGY TO TRY TO HELP.
>> IT BEND IN IMPACTS THE REST OF THE SYSTEM OF CARE.
IF WE DON'T HAVE PLACES LIKE SOUTHEAST MICHIGAN GERIATRIC.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
>> I'M LAURA THOMAS AND WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO DEPARTMENT
FRANCISCO AIDS FOUNDATION. THAT WAS A LONG TIME AGO
AND I'M ONE OF THE CO-CHAIRS OF THE HIV AIDS PROVIDER NETWORK.
AS YOU WILL NOTICE FROM THE LIST OF FUNDING CUTS, THE SAN
FRANCISCO AIDS FOUNDATION IS FACING SUBSTANTIAL CUTS THIS
YEAR INCLUDING THE ONES THAT ARE UP FOR THIS HEARING INCLUDE
CLOSING SOME OF OUR VERY LONG STANDING HIV PREVENTION
HEPATITIS PREVENTION, OVERDOSE PREVENTION AND LINKAGE TO CARE
SERVICES IN NEIGHBORHOODS AROUND THE COUNTY AND WITHOUT
THESE SERVICES, NEIGHBORHOODS AND COMMUNITIES ARE GOING TO BE
UNDERSERVED. THESE HAVE BEEN LIFELINES TO
PEOPLE CONNECTING TO TREATMENT FOR DECADES AND WITHOUT THEM
PEOPLE ARE NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO KNOW WHERE TO GO TO ACCESS
SERVICES. WE'RE ALSO FACING THE
ELIMINATION OF OUR SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER COORDINATOR
POSITION WHICH DESPITE WHAT IT SAYS IN THE OFFICIAL DOCUMENT
IS NOT AT ALL UNDERUTILIZED. THIS IS SOMEBODY WHO WORKS
WITHIN OUR TREATMENT PROGRAM AND HELPS TO MOVE PEOPLE ON TO
MORE INTENSIVE LEVELS OF TREATMENT AND ADDRESS OTHER
NEEDS THAT THEY HAVE. THEY PERFORM A VERY CORE
FUNCTION IN ENSURING THAT PEOPLE ARE ABLE TO ACCESS
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER TREATMENT AND STAY IN THAT
SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER TREATMENT.
ALSO NOT ON THIS LIST. OUR PARTNERS AT THE ALLIANCE
HEALTH PROJECT IN THEIR CLEARINGHOUSE CONTRACT IT
INCLUDES SOME OF THEIR HIV TESTING CAPACITY WHICH THE CITY
WILL BE LOSING WITH THESE BUDGET CUTS WITH HIV GETTING TO
ZERO IS WITHIN REACH AND NOW IS NOT THE TIME FOR US AS A CITY
TO BE GOING BACKWARDS AND CUTTING THESE CORE
ESSENTIAL LIFE SAVING HIV PREVENTION SERVICES.
THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
NEXT SPEAKER. >> MY NAME IS STEVEN TORRES.
I'M A NIGHTLIFE WORKER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
I AM REFLECTING UPON THE COMMENTS EARLIER DURING THE
SPECIAL ORDER ABOUT HOW THIS IS A PLACE OF HOPE FOR SO MANY
FROM ACROSS OUR NATION AND ACROSS THE WORLD.
THERE ARE SEEKING A PLACE TO BE WHERE THEY CAN BE THEMSELVES.
BUT WHEN YOU MAKE CUTS LIKE THIS, IT SIGNALS THAT THAT
SUPPORT IS CONDITIONAL, THAT IT'S ONLY A PLACE FOR PEOPLE
WHO CAN TAKE CARE OF THEMSELVES.
YOU TELL US THAT YOU SUPPORT US AND YOU'RE GOING TO PROTECT US
FROM THIS ADMINISTRATION. AND YET THIS LEAVES OUR MOST
VULNERABLE BEHIND. IT'S PRIDE RIGHT NOW.
MANY OF YOU WILL BE IN THE PARADE AT THE END OF THE MONTH
. SOME OF YOU ARE MEMBERS OF OUR
COMMUNITY. WILL YOU BE ABLE TO FACE OUR
COMMUNITY KNOWING THAT YOU HAVE TAKEN CUTS TO THE VERY PEOPLE
WHO NEED IT THE MOST? OUR ELDERS, OUR KIDS, THOSE
WHO ARE LIVING WITH LONG TERM CONDITIONS LIKE HIV, THOSE WHO
ARE STRUGGLING WITH SUBSTANCE USE.
>> PLEASE. YOU CANNOT LEAVE US BEHIND.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
>> I'VE LOST MY ELOQUENCE IN PUTTING TOGETHER THESE
COMMENTS BECAUSE I JUST FEEL PAIN NOW WHEN I HEAR AND SEE
PEOPLE'S LIVES REDUCED TO NUMBERS AND BUDGETS.
>> IS THIS WHAT THE COMEBACK IS FOR SAN FRANCISCO TO GET RID OF
POOR PEOPLE, HOMELESS PEOPLE, PEOPLE, SENIORS, DISABLED
PEOPLE, PEOPLE WITH HIV SUBSTANCE USE DISORDER.
>> IS THIS THE COMEBACK OF. IT FEELS LIKE YOU ARE GOING TO
COMMIT A MASSACRE AGAINST US AND I DON'T KNOW HOW TO STOP
THAT. WE DON'T KNOW HOW TO STOP THAT
BECAUSE IF WE DID WE WOULD HAVE STOPPED IT ALREADY YEARS AGO.
THIS DIDN'T START WITH LAURIE. >> WHAT DO WE NEED TO DO TO
STOP YOU? WHAT DO WE NEED TO DO TO STOP
THE MAYOR? WHAT DO WE SERIOUSLY NEED TO
DO? BECAUSE WORDS AREN'T WORKING.
CONVERSATIONS AREN'T WORKING. AND THEN THAT REDUCES THE
OPTIONS LEFT OVER. SO I REALLY WANT TO KNOW WHAT
DO WE NEED TO DO TO STOP YOU? WHAT DO WE NEED TO DO TO STOP
THE MASSACRE? >> YOU KNOW, WE SEE THESE
THINGS OF DRONES AND MISSILES BRINGING DOWN CITIES
AND KILLING MASSES AND MASSES AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN OTHER
LANDS. BUT I FEEL LIKE THE SAME THING
THE SAME BLOODLESS MASSACRE IS GOING TO HAPPEN HERE.
BUT YOUR HANDS DON'T HAVE TO GET BLOODY BUT OURS WILL.
FIGHTING YOUR YOUR POLICY ASSAULTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
I WOULD LIKE TO ONCE AGAIN POINT OUT THAT THESE CUTS WILL
AFFECT SPECIFICALLY ORGANIZATIONS THAT SERVE THE
UNIVERSITY THAT IS LYRIC HUCKLEBERRY LOGGING STREET
CLINIC AND THAT I KNOW THAT YOU ALL ARE MOVING ABSOLUTE
MOUNTAINS WITH THIS BUDGET DEFICIT THAT YOU TAKE NO PRIDE
OR JOY IN CUTTING THESE SORTS OF THINGS BUT THAT I THINK THAT
IT IS AN OPPORTUNITY TO RESTRUCTURE THE BUDGET AND THE
THINGS THAT OUR CITY SPENDS MONEY ON AND SPECIFICALLY THE
THINGS THAT WE PRIORITIZE AND THAT'S AN OPPORTUNITY AS
MUCH AS IT IS A CRISIS. >> I THINK SPECIFICALLY DURING
PRIDE MONTH IT IS IMPORTANT TO AGAIN REMEMBER THAT THE PEOPLE
WHO ARE MOST VULNERABLE ALL DESERVE THE MOST HELP.
AND EARLIER IN THIS MEETING YOU SAW A A MOVEMENT TO SPEND I
THINK SOMETHING LIKE $25,000 ON PUTTING UP BANNERS IN THE
SO-CALLED TRANSGENDER DISTRICT THAT SORT OF STUFF.
>> WELL, HELPFUL AND VERY IMPORTANT IS USELESS WHEN YOU
ARE DENYING NECESSARY CARE TO THE VERY PEOPLE WHOM YOU CLAIM
TO TOUT AND THAT IS ALL. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. NEXT SPEAKER OH GOOD AFTERNOON.
>> MY NAME'S CATHY BURKE. I'M A LONG TIME SAN FRANCISCO
RESIDENT CITY COLLEGE TEACHER. >> I KNOW IT'S LIKE A COMMENT
THAT IS SO OBVIOUS IT SHOULDN'T BE SAID BUT I FELT LIKE I HAD
TO WHEN I LOOKED AT THE JUNE 1ST STATEMENT FROM THE MAYOR'S
OFFICE THAT THIS WAS A BUDGET THAT STRENGTHENS THE SOCIAL
SAFETY NET AND THEN I SAW WHAT WAS BEING CUT FROM IT IN HEALTH
CARE AND SENIOR SERVICES AND ON AND ON AND ON.
>> I'M JUST ASKING YOU TO PLEASE STRENGTHEN THE SAFETY
NET FOR THE PEOPLE IN TOWN WHO REALLY NEED IT.
THESE CUTS JUST DO THE OPPOSITE.
THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
MY NAME IS SUSAN ZEIGER. I HAVE BEEN A BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
CLINICIAN AT THE DEPARTURE RANK CALLED STREET YOUTH CLINIC FOR
19 YEARS. I'M HERE TO CONTEST THE CLOSURE
OF THE DEEP, DEEP CHIP'S CLINIC.
CHIP WAS BUILT BY MICHAEL BAXTER, A GAY MAN LIVING WITH
HIV WHO WATCHES COMMUNITY DIE AND DECIDED TO DEDICATE HIS
LIFE TO MAKING SURE NO YOUNG PERSON WOULD FACE THAT ALONE.
WHAT MAKES OUR CLINICS VALUABLE IS NOT JUST THE MEDICAL,
REPRODUCTIVE AND MENTAL HEALTH CARE WE PROVIDE.
BOTH CLINICS ARE EMBEDDED INSIDE COMMUNITY ORGANIZATION
HUCKLEBERRY AND LARKIN WHERE YOUNG PEOPLE CAN ALSO ACCESS
MUCH NEEDED CASE MANAGEMENT, FOOD, HOUSING SUPPORT
AND EMPLOYMENT RESOURCES. IN A SINGLE VISIT ON A SINGLE
DAY WITHOUT NEEDING MULTIPLE APPOINTMENTS IN DIFFERENT PARTS
OF THE CITY THEY CAN ADDRESS THE FULL COMPLEXITY OF THEIR
LIVES. THIS INTEGRATED CARE IS THE
ONLY MODEL THAT ACTUALLY WORKS FOR THIS POPULATION.
WE ARE ALSO IN THE MIDST OF A YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH CRISIS.
THESE CLINICS PROVIDE ON THE SPOT LOW BARRIER MENTAL HEALTH
SUPPORT TO YOUNG PEOPLE WHO WOULD OTHERWISE HAVE NOWHERE TO
TURN. THERE ARE NO OTHER CLINICS LIKE
THESE IN SAN FRANCISCO. ADULT CLINICS ARE NOT EQUIPPED
TO SERVE THIS POPULATION AND THERE IS NO TRANSITION
PLAN. THERE ARE THEY ARE UNIQUE BUILT
OVER 30 YEARS SPECIFICALLY FOR THIS POPULATION IN SPACES WHERE
THESE YOUNG PEOPLE FEEL SAFE. ONCE THEY'RE GONE, THEY'RE GONE
. NOW CONSIDER WHAT CLOSING THESE
CLINICS ACTUALLY SAVES. DEEP SPACE ZERO RENT.
OUR COMMUNITY PARTNER COVER THE OVERHEAD.
THE STAFF ARE BEING REASSIGNED NOT LAID OFF.
AS PER DPA OWN CALCULATION THE SAVING IS ABOUT $700,000 PER
CLINIC A ROUNDING ERROR AGAINST A BUDGET SHORTFALL IN THE
HUNDREDS OF MILLION. BUT THE LOSSES FOR THESE
VULNERABLE YOUTH ARE IMMEASURABLE.
YOUNG PEOPLE WILL NOT GO SOMEWHERE ELSE.
THEY WILL GO WITHOUT ASKING THIS BOARD TO RESTORE FUNDING
AND KEEP THESE CLINICS OPEN. >> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS.
MY NAME IS SOFIA PADILLA AND I'M A BEHAVIORAL HEALTH
CLINICIAN WITH THE MICHAEL BAXTER LARKIN STREET CLINIC.
>> I'M HERE TODAY BECAUSE THE JUSTIFICATION FOR CLOSING OUR
KIBBY CLINICS IS BASED ON A FALSE PREMISE THAT THESE
CLINICS ARE UNDERUTILIZED. THE REALITY IS THAT WE HAVE
BEEN CHRONICALLY UNDERSTAFFED AND UNSUPPORTED FOR YEARS.
YOU CANNOT REDUCE STAFFING WHO LEAVE POSITIONS VACANT, LIMITED
AVAILABLE APPOINTMENTS, REDUCE CLINIC HOURS AND THEN POINT TO
LOWER SERVICE NUMBERS AS EVIDENCE THAT A CLINIC IS NOT
NEEDED. WHAT WE ARE SEEING IS NOT
UNDERUTILIZATION BUT IT IS THE PREDICTABLE RESULT OF
UNDERINVESTMENT. OUR DEDICATED CHIPPIE STAFF
HAVE CONTINUED TO SERVE THE YOUTH OF THE HAIGHT TENDERLOIN
AND BEYOND DESPITE ONGOING STAFF SHORTAGES AND RESOURCE
CONSTRAINTS. INSTEAD OF RECEIVING THE
SUPPORT NEEDED TO MEET COMMUNITY DEMAND, THESE CLINICS
ARE NOW BEING PUNISHED FOR THE CONSEQUENCES OF THOSE
SHORTAGES. I'M ALSO DEEPLY CONCERNED BY
THE LACK OF A CONCRETE TRANSITION PLAN FOR THE
PATIENTS THAT CURRENTLY RELY ON THESE CLINICS.
THROUGHOUT THIS PROCESS WE HAVE HEARD COUNTLESS ASSURANCES THAT
PATIENTS WILL EXPERIENCE A SMOOTH TRANSITION BUT
ASSURANCES ARE NOT A PLAN. TO DATE THERE HAS BEEN LITTLE
PUBLIC INFORMATION ABOUT WHERE PATIENTS WILL GO, WHETHER THE
RECEIVING PROGRAMS HAVE THE CAPACITY TO ABSORB THEM OR HOW
THE CITY WILL ENSURE THAT VULNERABLE PATIENTS DO NOT FALL
OUT OF TREATMENT. ANY PLAN DISCUSSED BY EACH
COMES AS THE RESULT OF ADVOCACY AND PRESSURE FROM STAFF CBOS
AND COMMUNITY MEMBERS DECLARING THAT OUR PATIENTS DESERVE
BETTER. AND IT IS STILL NOT ENOUGH.
>> IF THE CITY'S GOAL IS TO IMPROVE ACCESS TO CARE AND USE
RESOURCES WISELY FOR A HEALTHIER SAN FRANCISCO, THE
ANSWER IS NOT TO CLOSE THESE CLINICS.
THE ANSWER IS TO ADEQUATELY STAFF AND SUPPORT THEM SO THEY
CAN OPERATE AT THEIR FULL CAPACITY.
CLOSING THESE CLINICS WILL NOT SOLVE THE UNDERLYING PROBLEM.
IT WILL REDUCE ACCESS TO CARE, DISRUPT MEANINGFUL
RELATIONSHIPS AND DISPLACE PATIENTS.
I URGE YOU TO REJECT THE NARRATIVE OF UNDERUTILIZATION.
LOOK AT THE REALITY OF CHRONIC UNDERSTAFFING
AND UNDERINVESTMENT AND DO EVERYTHING YOU CAN TO RESTORE
FUNDING AND KEEP THESE CLINICS OPEN.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
OKAY. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER.
I'LL JUST REVISIT REALLY QUICKLY.
>> THERE IS NO APPLAUSE IN THE AUDIENCE PLEASE.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT. >> WELCOME.
HI. FIRST OFF, I'VE NOTICED SINCE
BEING IN LINE THAT MOST BOARDS I GUESS THE SUPERVISORS HAVE
EITHER BEEN ON THEIR PHONES AND NOT PROVIDING THE GOOD
PEOPLE HERE THAT ARE SPEAKING WITH RESPECT.
>> SO IF YOU COULD PLEASE AT LEAST LOOK AT ME WHEN I'M
SPEAKING. >> THAT WOULD BE REALLY, REALLY
GREAT. SOMETHING THAT I'D LIKE TO
SHARE IS MY NAME IS DALIA MARTINEZ AND I'M A BILINGUAL
COMMUNITY HEALTH EDUCATOR WITH HUCKLEBERRY WHICH MEANS THAT I
DO A LOT OF DIFFERENT THINGS. I FACILITATE WORKSHOPS
IN SCHOOLS. I TALK ABOUT BOUNDARIES
AND CONSENT. I TALK ABOUT S'S PROTECTION
METHODS, HOW TO USE A CONDOM CORRECTLY.
THESE ARE SOME THINGS THAT I GO INTO SCHOOLS AND I TALK TO
YOUNG PEOPLE ABOUT MEANING I DO OUTREACH IN PERSON.
>> THAT IS HOW A LOT OF THE YOUNG PEOPLE WHO ARE SERVED BY
HUCKLEBERRY COME RIGHT BECAUSE I'M IN THE SCHOOLS AND I'M
PROVIDING THIS INFORMATION COME TO HUCKLEBERRY TO SEE THE
CLINIC, GET SEXUAL REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH CARE FOR FREE.
IT'S CONFIDENTIAL. >> NO, YOUR PARENTS DON'T NEED
TO KNOW. RIGHT?
THESE ARE THE THINGS THAT I DO AND A LOT OF WHAT THE STAFF DO
WHERE I WORK AT SOMETHING THAT'S REALLY IMPORTANT TO NOTE
IS THAT PEOPLE MIGHT COME IN FOR STI TESTING, THEY MIGHT
COME IN FOR A PREGNANCY TESTING WHATEVER IT IS AND I OFTEN FIND
MYSELF IN THESE CLINICAL SPACES WITH YOUNG PEOPLE FINDING OUT
THAT THE REASON WHY THEY'RE GETTING STI TESTING IS BECAUSE
THEY WERE COERCED INTO THAT SEXUAL ENCOUNTER WITH A
PARTNER. >> THESE ARE REALLY IMPORTANT
CONVERSATIONS THAT I AM HAVING WITH YOUNG PEOPLE WITH STAFF.
THEY'RE PRESENT. I'M ABLE TO HAVE THESE
CONVERSATIONS IN ENGLISH AND IN SPANISH.
IT'S REALLY, REALLY UPSETTING TO STAND HERE AND TELL YOU
ABOUT HOW IMPORTANT THIS WORK IS THAT I DO AND HAVE YOU ON
YOUR PHONES NOT LOOKING ACTING AS IF YOU'D RATHER LEAVE.
IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT THAT YOU'RE LISTENING TO THESE
PEOPLE WHEN THEY'RE TELLING YOU WHAT'S WRONG.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS AND I WILL INVITE MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC IF YOU ALL HAVE A MOBILE PHONE YOU TWO CAN LOOK
AT THE FILE IN THE FILE FOR THIS ITEM CONTAINS THE CUTS
THAT ARE BEING REDUCED OR THE COMMUNITY CENTERS THAT ARE
BEING UH MOVED AND OTHER BITS AND PIECES OF INFORMATION THERE
AS WELL. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> MY NAME IS JACKIE AND I WORK
AT THE HUCKLEBERRY COLE STREET CLINIC.
>> IT'S INCREDIBLY DISHEARTENING TO HEAR THE PLAN
TO MOVE FORWARD WITH THE CLINIC CLOSURE.
I'M TIRED OF ACTING LIKE THEY'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO
SMOOTHLY TRANSITION OUR CLIENTS THE ADULT PRIMARY CARE
FACILITIES. >> HAVE YOU FORGOTTEN THE
REASON TO BE CLINICS WERE CREATED?
>> BECAUSE WE KNOW THIS IS A POPULATION THAT NEEDS
SPECIALIZED CARE FROM ORGANIZATIONS AND PROVIDERS WHO
ARE TRAINED AND EXPERIENCED WORKING WITH YOUTH.
THERE ARE MANY CLIENTS WHO COME TO COLE AND LARKIN BECAUSE OF
THE TRUST THAT WE'VE BUILT WITH THEM.
IF YOU CLOSE OUR CLINICS, MANY OF THESE CLIENTS WILL SIMPLY
STOP ACCESSING MEDICAL CARE. THIS IS THE DEPARTMENT OF
PUBLIC HEALTH. THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO KEEP OUR
COMMUNITY SAFE. >> THEIR MISMANAGEMENT
AND INABILITY TO STAFF OUR CLINICS HAS BEEN OUR BURDEN TO
BEAR FOR YEARS AND NOW THEY'RE THREATENING TO CLOSE OUR DOORS
PERMANENTLY. >> DO NOT CUT COSTS IN THE
BACKS OF OUR MOST VULNERABLE POPULATIONS.
>> I'M ALSO GOING TO READ A STATEMENT FROM A YOUNG PERSON
WHO WANTS TO REMAIN ANONYMOUS. >> I'M CURRENTLY A 22 YEAR OLD
STUDENT AND HAVE BEEN ACCESSING THE HUCKLEBERRY COLE FREE
CLINIC SINCE HIGH SCHOOL. THE THERAPY IN THE MEDICAL
SERVICES HAVE MADE A HUGE IMPACT ON MY LIFE DURING VERY
DIFFICULT SITUATIONS. IT IS NOT GOOD FOR YOUTH TO NOT
HAVE THESE SERVICES BECAUSE IT LEAVE THEM ALONE AND SCARED
WHEN THEY HAVE HEALTH RELATED EXPERIENCES OR QUESTIONS.
ESPECIALLY WHEN YOUTH HAVE GUARDIANS OR PARENTS THAT MAY
BE OVERBEARING OR UNAWARE OF THEIR CONCERNS AND SAFETY.
>> THIS ENDS UP LEAVING ALL OF THAT STRESS ON THE YOUTH
SHOULDERS. WHEN ADULTS SHOULD UPLIFT
AND GUIDE THEM WHEN YOU TAKE AWAY HEALTH SERVICES YOU ARE
TAKING AWAY THEIR ACCESS AND ABANDONING THEIR BASIC
RIGHT TO MEDICAL SERVICES AND HEALTH EDUCATION.
>> DEFUNDING THE CLINIC IS GETTING RID OF A SAFE SPACE FOR
YOUTH WHERE THEY TALKED WITH AND NOT TALKED TO WHERE WE FEEL
EMPOWERED AND NOT JUDGED. >> DO NOT CLOSE THIS CLINIC.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
. >> HI JESSICA PASCOE ARE AN
EXPERT WITNESS, LEGAL REPRESENTATIVE AND DISTRICT
SENATE CANDIDATE. BEFORE WE CLOSE ANYTHING I'M
ASKING HAS THE CITY EXHAUSTED EVERY FUNDING OPTION?
>> ARE WE ACTIVELY PURSUING STATE BEHAVIORAL HEALTH GRANTS?
FEDERAL YOUTH MENTAL HEALTH DOLLARS AND PRIVATE FOUNDATION
SUPPORT TO KEEP THESE DOORS OPEN AND TO ANYONE LISTENING
TODAY WHO HAS THE MEANS A FOUNDATION OR DONOR, A
PHILANTHROPIST WHO CARES ABOUT YOUNG PEOPLE IN THIS CITY.
>> THESE CLINICS NEED A CHAMPION.
IF YOU CAN CREATE OR FUND A GRANT TO SUSTAIN YOUTH HEALTH
CARE IN THIS AREA WHETHER IT BE IN THE HAIGHT OR IN THE
TENDERLOIN, THIS IS YOUR MOMENT .
>> IF THE CITY'S GOAL IS TO IMPROVE ACCESS TO CARE FOR A
HEALTHIER SAN FRANCISCO, THE ANSWER IS NOT TO CLOSE THESE
CLINICS. THE ANSWER IS TO ADEQUATELY
STAFF AND SUPPORT THEM SO THEY CAN FULLY OPERATE AT FULL
CAPACITY. >> CLOSING HUCKLEBERRY
AND LARKIN STREET WILL NOT SOLVE THE UNDERLYING PROBLEM.
>> IT WILL REDUCE ACCESS TO CARE, DISRUPT MEANINGFUL
RELATIONSHIPS HIPS AND DISPLACE THE YOUNG PEOPLE WHO DEPEND ON
THEM. >> I URGE YOU TO REJECT THE
NARRATIVE OF UNDERUTILIZATION. LOOK AT THE REALITY OF CHRONIC
UNDERINVESTMENT AND KEEP THE HUCKLEBERRY AND LARKIN STREET
CLINICS OPEN. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU. AND JESSICA.
THERE IS NO NEED FOR YOU TO MENTION THAT YOU'RE A DISTRICT
TEN CANDIDATE HERE. THERE'S NO ELECTIONEERING
IN THIS CHAMBER. I'M SORRY.
OKAY. THANK YOU KINDLY.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> HI THERE, MARION.
CITY COUNCIL. >> I'M HOMELESS.
CAN YOU SPEAK DIRECTLY INTO THAT MICROPHONE?
WE'RE HANGING OUT WITH HER RIGHT HERE.
I'M HOMELESS AND I'VE LIVED HERE NOW FOR ABOUT A WEEK.
AND THE THING IS WHAT I LOVE ABOUT SAN FRANCISCO IS THAT YOU
GUYS HAVE A CALIFORNIA HAS SO MUCH BIODIVERSITY IN EVERYTHING
HERE IT'S JUST A MARGE PODGE OF JUST A A COLLECTION OF OF
CULTURE AND INCLUSIVITY. I BRING THAT UP BECAUSE WHEN
I'M HEARING THIS SUBJECT COME UP I FEEL EMPOWERED BECAUSE
THERE'S WAYS THAT WE CAN BE DOING THINGS BETTER.
BECAUSE LET'S SAY THE STREET THE STREET TEAM THAT COMES
IN THAT ENGAGES OTHER THAN THE HOMELESS.
IF WE DID A PARTNERSHIP WITH THEM INSTEAD OF MAKING IT AN
ADVERSARIAL ROLE, MAYBE THE MONEY THAT WE WOULD SAVE
IN LITIGATION FROM THE TURMOIL THAT'S HAPPENING BETWEEN THESE
TWO GROUPS THAT ARE CONVERGING ON THE STREET, WHAT COULD BE
USED TO KEEP THIS CLINIC OPEN? SO THERE'S THESE THINGS WHERE
WE CAN FIND WIN WINS. IT'S JUST WE'RE GOING TO DIG
THEM OUT. AND WHAT'S COOL ABOUT THIS KIND
OF FORUM IS THAT WHEN YOU PUT US ALL TOGETHER AND WE'RE ALL
WORKING CONSTRUCTIVELY AND WE'RE ON A PLANE, WE'RE ALL
GOING TO HIT TURBULENCE. NO MATTER WHAT WE DO.
I MEAN IT'S GOING TO BE BUMPY. BUT WE'RE ALL GOING TO MAKE IT
. AT THE END OF THE DAY WE'RE ALL
GOING TO MAKE IT. THAT'S JUST THAT.
HOW ARE WE GOING TO MAKE THAT A SMOOTH AS RIGHT AS POSSIBLE?
THE THING IS I'M NOT TRYING TO GET INTO IT BUT ONE OF THE
OFFICERS STOLE A BIKE FROM ANOTHER GENTLEMAN THOSE OD'ING
ON THE SIDEWALK AND THEY TOLD ME I WAS INAPPROPRIATE.
I'M LIKE DUDE, THAT'S HIS TRANSPORTATION.
AND THEN HE WENT ABOVE AND THREW THE BIKE AWAY.
AFTER I TOLD HIM THAT I DIDN'T WANT IT I HATE TO DO THIS BUT I
PUT HIM UNDER CITIZEN'S ARREST .
I'M LIKE, YOU KNOW WHAT? YOU'RE JUST THIS IS HOW IF
YOU'RE GOING TO MEET FORCE WITH FORCE, THIS IS HOW THIS IS
GOING TO GO. NOW THE OFFICE OF CIVIL RIGHTS,
THE CALIFORNIA DEPARTMENT IS GOING TO BE OVERSEEING THIS
WHOLE ISSUE. WE HAVE ANOTHER I'M WRAPPING
UP. THE OTHER ONE IS I MEAN PEOPLE
ARE OUT LOOKING FOR WORK AND THE GUARDS ARE COMING UP
THING. YOU GOT TO GO.
YOU CAN'T PULL WEEDS IF THEY CAN'T SUPPORT THEMSELVES.
YOU CAN'T HAVE THE GOVERNMENT DOING A PUSH DOWN AND A PULL UP
AT THE SAME TIME. ANYWAY, I'M LOOKING FORWARD TO
EMAILING YOU AND ENGAGING THIS IN CONVERSATION MORE.
AS A HOMELESS PERSON THAT'S WILLING TO GET SOME AIRTIME.
>> THANK YOU GUYS. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD AFTERNOON.
I AM TAB BUCKNER AND I HAVE WITNESSED THE ENTIRE AIDS
EPIDEMIC ALL 45 YEARS CLOSE UP. I SPENT MY EARLY ADULTHOOD
ATTENDING THE FUNERALS OF CONTEMPORARIES MORE OFTEN THAN
BIRTHDAY PARTIES. >> WHAT I LEARNED LONG AGO IS
SERVICES SAVE LIVES. CULTURALLY, CULTURALLY RELEVANT
ACCESS OUTREACH AND HEALTH CARE MAKE THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
LIFE AND DEATH. CUTTING ANY HARM REDUCTION
PROGRAMS WILL INCREASE NOT LOWER OVERDOSES AND OTHER
LETHAL HEALTH SITUATIONS. >> NOT ALLOCATING ADEQUATE
SERVICES FOR LONG TERM HIV SURVIVORS WILL RESULT IN SEVERE
ISOLATION AND INCREASED MEDICAL CRISES FOR COUNTLESS
INDIVIDUALS WITHOUT TRADITIONAL FAMILIES OR SURVIVING PEERS.
>> PLEASE MAKE SURE THAT PEOPLE IN MY COMMUNITY THE LGBTQ
COMMUNITY AS WELL AS ALL TRADITIONALLY MARGINALIZED
COMMUNITIES HAVE THE TOOLS TO SURVIVE AND THRIVE.
BEFORE YOU EVEN THINK ABOUT WRITING IN THIS YEAR'S PRIDE
PARADE, THANK YOU VERY MUCH. >> THANK YOU.
TAB BUCKNER FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER
. >> MY NAME IS ZANDER BRIER
AND I WANT YOU TO SIT WITH THE WEIGHT OF WHAT THESE CUTS
ACTUALLY MEAN TO OUR COMMUNITY. AT THE BEGINNING OF THE YEAR I
CAME HERE BEGGING YOU TO NOT CUT OUR PROGRAMS BECAUSE OF A
MEMO THAT WAS SENT OUT. >> THE LINE ITEM SPECIFICALLY
WAS S.F. CHC AND IT WAS CAPACITY BUILDING PROGRAMS.
>> OH THAT'S NOT FRONTLINE SERVICES.
MY ENTIRE SUPPORT GROUP WAS CUT.
>> I AM NOW AT RISK OF HOMELESSNESS.
I AM NOW ON FOOD STAMPS. >> I NO LONGER HAVE THE SUPPORT
SYSTEMS THAT I WAS BUILDING OUT FOR FOUR YEARS AND SEVEN
MONTHS. >> THIS WAS MY ABILITY TO GIVE
BACK TO MY COMMUNITY AFTER CASE MANAGER AFTER CASE MANAGER
DECIDED MY LIFE WAS STILL WORTH IT.
BUT APPARENTLY Y'ALL DON'T BELIEVE IN THAT BECAUSE I NO
LONGER HAVE A JOB. I NO LONGER HAVE STABILITY.
I NO LONGER HAVE THAT SAFETY NET.
I AM TRANS AND I AM VULNERABLE .
AND THIS ADMINISTRATION WANTS TO LITERALLY KILL US.
THEY HAVE SAID IT POINT BLANK PERIOD.
THEY WANT US DEAD. SO WHY ARE YOU CONTINUOUSLY
CUTTING TRANSGENDER SERVICES KNOWING WE ARE AT THE MOST RISK
OF MARGINALIZATION FROM OUR FEDERAL GOVERNMENT?
I WANT YOU TO SIT WITH THAT WEIGHT BECAUSE IF I END UP ON
THE STREETS AGAIN IT IS BECAUSE OF YOUR DECISIONS.
I WAS GOOD AT MY JOB. I WAS MAKING SURE THAT I WAS
DOING ALL OF MY P'S AND Q'S. I WAS TURNING IN ALL OF MY
FORMS THAT I WAS DOING EVERYTHING THAT I NEEDED TO DO
TO BE A GOOD SUPPORT GROUP LEADER BECAUSE THAT WAS THE
BEST THAT I KNEW HOW TO DO TO GIVE BACK TO MY COMMUNITY.
AND NOW NOBODY IS THERE FOR ME .
>> NONE OF YOU. >> THANK YOU XANDRA BRYANT FOR
YOUR COMMENTS EVERYONE, I'LL JUST REVISIT.
WE DO HAVE AN APPROVED BOARD RULE WHICH THERE IS NO SUPPORT
OR AGAINST ANY AUDIBLE SOUNDS IN THIS CHAMBER.
AGAIN, IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO SHOW YOUR SUPPORT, PLEASE SHOW
YOUR SUPPORT AS SUCH. >> WELCOME, SIR.
GOOD AFTERNOON BOARD SUPPORTERS.
>> I'M JIM BENNETT. >> I'M 56 THROUGH OR KNOW ON
FRASER ROAD AND SHARE BOTH HOUSES.
>> YEAH. >> I'LL BE SEVEN 0 IN 2010
AND I LOVE MY WHOLE FAMILY IN GEORGIA BUT I CAME FOR SOME
KIND OF LEGAL SERVICE. LEGAL?
I'VE LIVED IN THE PRIVACY OF RELIGIOUS BELIEFS AND IN HEY
YOU KNOW HOW I'M FROM THE HORNE COMMUNITY FOR IS A FOUNDATION.
I'M PAUL. I'M BROTHER.
>> THERE THERE ARE A FEW FIRST AND THE FIRST CHARITY PROJECT.
>> YEAH. YEAH.
HEY WENDY. COMMUNITY HAS SO MUCH SUPPORT
AND YEAR ROUND THESE SURGERIES I MEAN, PEOPLE ARE HERE FOR
SPOKEN THE PEOPLE WHO CAME BEFORE TODAY.
BUT BUT I WILL SAY, YOU KNOW, I BELIEVE I TRULY BELIEVE IT'S
EVERY SINGLE PAST AND LIVING IS FUTURE.
YEAH I BELIEVE YOU DO THE RIGHT THING.
YEAH, YEAH, YEAH. REALLY?
YEAH. I BELIEVE.
>> DID YOU DID YOU NOT? COULD WE VOUCHER SOME MORE
DRUGS? WE THANKSGIVING BREAK.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS OR CAN WE HAVE THE NEXT SPEAKER
PLEASE? >> HELLO MY DEAR ARI AND I'M
THE OWNER OF THE BUILDING AT THE CLINIC ON MISSION STREET 40
YEARS AGO OR SO MYSELF AND JOE RUSKIN ESTABLISHED A CLINIC.
AND ALL THESE YEARS I'VE TAKEN CARE OF THE CLINIC CONSTRUCTION
WISE HELP WISE WHATEVER I COULD .
AND I'VE KEPT MY RENTS REALLY LOW.
I THINK THE LAST TIME I RAISED MY RENT WAS LIKE EIGHT YEARS
AGO. SO BECAUSE I FEEL THAT THE
SERVICE THAT ARE THERE AND THEY'RE THERE ARE VERY
IMPORTANT TO ALL PEOPLE AND INTERACT AND I THINK
ANYBODY THAT DOES DIDN'T APPRECIATE HOW OLD PEOPLE
VULNERABLE ARE. THEY CAN'T TAKE CARE OF
THEMSELVES AND NOW THEY HAVE MENTAL PROBLEMS AND HOW THEY
CAN'T BE ALONE AND THEY NEED HELP.
AND THAT'S THE REASON WHY I SUPPORT THE CLINIC.
YOU KNOW, I ALWAYS HAVE BY SHUTTING THE DOOR ON THESE
PEOPLE YOU'RE GOING TO LITERALLY CUT OFF BOTH THEIR
LIFE SUPPORT AND I DON'T THINK THAT'S RIGHT BECAUSE THESE
PEOPLE COULD HAVE BEEN YOUR PARENTS.
THEY COULD BE YOU IN A FEW YEARS.
SO BY CUTTING THESE SERVICES YOU'RE REALLY HURTING THE
COMMUNITY AND THE MOST VULNERABLE PART OF OUR
COMMUNITY PEOPLE THAT WORK FOR THE COMMUNITY AND MADE THEIR
COMMUNITY POSSIBLE AND NOW YOU'RE ANYWHERE BY CLOSING THE
CLINIC YOU'RE SHUTTING THEIR DOOR IN THEIR FACE.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THANK YOU, SIR, FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> YES, HE CAN USE THAT MICROPHONE.
>> JUST PULL IT CLOSE PLEASE SO WE CAN HEAR YOU BEST.
CERTAINLY. SO MA'AM, THE WAY IT WORKS IS
HE SPEAKS FOR TWO MINUTES AND THEN YOU PROVIDE THE
INTERPRETATION FOR TWO MINUTES AT A PROFESSIONAL.
>> IT'S A BOARD RULE SO IF I WILL SAY IF IF IF IF YOU DO IT
THAT'S OKAY. >> I'M JUST BREAKING THE RULES
ON BEHALF FOR THIS GENTLEMAN AND FOR YOUR ABILITY
. >> GOOD AFTERNOON, LADIES
MANDELMAN. I AM A SURVIVOR OF SEVERAL
SUICIDE ATTEMPTS AND THE PEOPLE IN THIS CLINIC HAVE HELPED ME
SURVIVE. HE WANTED TO ALSO SAY THAT THIS
IS A COMMUNITY AND HE NOT ONLY GETS SUPPORT AND SERVICES FROM
THE CLINICIANS HE ALSO FINDS LOVE AND SUPPORT CARING
ENVIRONMENT AND WITHOUT THEM HE DOESN'T KNOW WHAT HE WILL DO.
>> PLEASE KEEP THE CLINIC OPEN. KEITH ROCCO, 30, WHO TAKE
IN HISTORY WAS COULD SO IT'S IMPORTANT FOR THE COMMUNITY TO
KEEP THESE CLINICS OPEN SO THAT PEOPLE WITH MENTAL HEALTH
ISSUES CAN SURVIVE AND CONTINUE LIVING IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> THANK YOU. >> THANK YOU.
YES PURSE WAS COMENTARIOS THANK YOU.
WHY DO WE HAVE ANOTHER SPEAKER? MA'AM?
DO YOU HAVE ANOTHER INDIVIDUAL WHO IS REQUESTING AN
ACCOMMODATION? OKAY.
WELCOME. WOULD AFTERNOON.
THANK YOU FOR GIVING US THE OPPORTUNITY TO SPEAK ABOUT
SOUTHEAST AND THE OTHER TWO CLINICS I'M BEING WORKING.
>> SO IS FOUR OVER 20 YEARS AND I THINK CROSSING THIS OUT
IS MISSION DID WE HAD THREE IS GOING TO BE A BIG MISTAKE THIS
IS THE LAST PSYCHIATRY OUTPATIENT CLINIC FOR SENIORS
IN SAN FRANCISCO IF WE CLOSE IF YOU CLOSE IS SEEING AS A
DISBURSING CUT SO THE CITY MOST VULNERABLE ELDERLY WHAT WILL
HAPPEN WITH THEIR SENIORS IS THAT THEY WILL HAVE MORE
EMERGENCY VISITS EARLY PLACEMENT.
>> WE HAD TO BE LOOKING FOR BOARDING CARE FACILITY THERE
WILL DIE ALONE BECAUSE AS YOU MOST OF THEM WILL BE SENIORS
SOMEDAY THEY WILL BE MORE ISOLATED.
>> SOME OF THE CLIENTS SAY THEY WILL STOP EATING IF THEY CLOSE
THE CLINIC. SO I'M BEGGING YOU TO KEEP OPEN
THIS CLINIC. >> I DON'T KNOW ABOUT NUMBERS
BUT I WAS CHECKING THE NUMBERS. YOU KNOW HOW MUCH THEY WANT TO
GIVE TO THE TO THE TRANSIT. >> YOU KNOW, MILLIONS
AND MILLIONS. >> I HEARD ALSO THAT THE POLICE
OFFICERS ARE GETTING AN INCREASE BUT WE DON'T HAVE
MONEY TO PAY FOR THE SENIORS. >> I'M BEGGING YOU PLEASE TO
CONSIDER YOU KNOW THAT THIS CLINIC SHOULD BE OPEN
AND REMEMBER YOU WANT TO BE SEEN HERE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT. SO WE'RE GOING BACK TO THE LINE
MA'AM. >> MA'AM, DOES SHE REQUIRE AN
ACCOMMODATION OTHERWISE WE NEED TO GO TO THE LINE.
>> MY APOLOGIES. WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER
IN LINE. >> WELCOME, SIR.
>> HELLO. MY NAME'S TREY TURNER.
I WORK FOR THE SAN FRANCISCO AIDS FOUNDATION AS A MANAGER OF
THE CLINICAL ASSISTANCE JOB DEVELOPMENT PROGRAM AND PUBLIC
HEALTH. I'M HERE TO ASK THAT YOU ALL
RECONSIDER YOUR CUTS TO PUBLIC HEALTH.
WE KNOW THAT THE IMPACTS OF THESE PROGRAMS AND SERVICES ARE
TREMENDOUS, ESPECIALLY SINCE THEY MAKE UP SOME OF OUR MOST
VULNERABLE VULNERABLE POPULATIONS IN SAN FRANCISCO
SPECIFICALLY PEOPLE THAT ARE WORKING DIRECTLY WITH FOLKS THE
CUTS TO CLINICS LIKE ARKANSAS AND HUCKLEBERRY.
THESE ARE VITAL, VITAL LIFESAVING SERVICES.
I THINK THAT, YOU KNOW, IF WE ARE GOING TO MAKE THESE CUTS
THEN THE MAYOR SHOULD BE HONEST ABOUT THESE CUTS THAT ARE
HAPPENING AND NOT TRY TO PAT HIMSELF ON THE BACK.
WE KNOW THAT THE TRANS COMMUNITY IS UNDER ATTACK.
THE MAYOR IS SAYING HE'S RESTORING THE FUNDING BUT HE'S
NOT RESTORING THE FUNDING. SO LET'S BE HONEST ABOUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING. I DON'T THINK THE MAYOR SHOULD
GO INTO A ROOM OF BLACK PEOPLE TO SAY THAT THE CITY CARES
ABOUT BLACK PEOPLE AND HE'S MAKING MAJOR CUTS TO PUBLIC
HEALTH FOR THE BLACK COMMUNITY. WE KNOW THAT THE LATINO
COMMUNITY IS UNDER ATTACK BY THIS ADMINISTRATION THAT THEY
HAVE HUGE DISPROPORTIONATE OUTCOMES OF HEALTH.
THE MAYOR SAYS HE CARES ABOUT THESE COMMUNITIES BUT YET THAT
COMMUNITY'S GETTING A MAJOR CUT.
SO LET'S REALLY BE HONEST ABOUT WHAT'S HAPPENING HERE.
AND IF YOU ALL HAVE THE POWER TO DO SOMETHING, I THINK IT'S A
LOT HARDER TO FIX THE PROBLEM AND OUTCOMES THAT ARE GOING TO
HAPPEN FROM THESE CUTS THAN TO INVEST IN MORE PREVENTATIVE
MEASURES. YOU CAN'T THE MAYOR CAN'T SAY
HE'S CREATING A RESET CENTER AND THEN CUTTING FUNDING FOR
THE THERAPISTS, CLINICIANS AND THE PEOPLE WHO ARE GOING TO
BE SERVING IN THAT RESEARCH CENTER.
SO WHAT'S REALLY GOING ON THERE ?
>> ASK FOR US TO BE TRANSPARENT.
THANK YOU, TREY TURNER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. THANK YOU BOARD.
MY NAME IS JERRY COFFEE. SOON TO BE 74 YEARS OLD IN FIVE
DAYS. AND I'VE BEEN A 38 YEAR LONG
TERM SURVIVOR WITH HIV AND AIDS SO BORED IN HALF MY LIFE I'VE
HAD HIV. SO I'M SPEAKING ABOUT LONG TERM
SURVIVING AND AGING. LAST WEEK THE DEPARTMENT OF
AGING SERVICES APPROPRIATE IT AND I'M GOING TO USE THAT WORD
GENTLY APPROPRIATED $150,000 TOWARDS LONG TERM SURVIVORS
AND WITH HIV WHO ARE 50 YEARS AND OLDER.
THAT WAS TAKEN OUT OF A FUND CALLED THE DIGNITY FUND.
THAT'S $3 MILLION. THERE ARE 11,500 PEOPLE PLUS
LIVING IN SAN FRANCISCO WITH HIV WHO ARE OVER 50 YEARS OLD.
>> IF YOU DO THE MATH, THAT IS $13 PER PERSON LIVING IN SAN
FRANCISCO WITH HIV. THAT'S OVER 50 YEARS OLD.
$13. DO I LOOK LIKE I'M ONLY VALUED
AT $13? >> WHERE IS THE REST OF THE
MONEY THAT CAN BE USED FOR SERVICES FOR HIV?
AND LONG TERM SURVIVORS WANT BEING A LONG TERM SURVIVOR
MEANS THAT I HAVE CO-MORBIDITIES A HIGHER CHANCE
OF ATTAINING DIABETES, HEART ATTACK, KIDNEY DISEASE
AND OTHER ISSUES. >> THESE FUNDS WOULD SERVE TO
HELP OTHERS LIKE MYSELF TO LIVE THE REST OF THEIR LIVES WITH
DIGNITY. I'M ALREADY PAST 73 WHICH IS
WHEN I WAS SUPPOSED TO NOT BE HERE.
I WAS SUPPOSED TO NOT BE HERE 38 YEARS AGO BUT I'M STILL HERE
AND I'M STILL FIGHTING. AND I DIDN'T COME THIS FAR JUST
TO COME THIS FAR. >> SO HELP ME KEEP GOING.
>> THANK YOU JERRY DUFFY FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO THE NEXT SPEAKER. >> MA'AM, ARE YOU INTERPRETING
WE'RE HERE TOGETHER. MY NAME IS JUNEBUG.
BEFORE YOU TO JUNEBUG YOU KNOW THE RULES HERE YOU SPEAK FOR
TWO MINUTES AND THEN THE INDIVIDUAL WILL SPEAK FOR TWO
MINUTES BUT YOU CAN'T CROSS OVER.
>> OKAY? OKAY.
SO PLEASE BEGIN. I MEAN, YOU'RE WELCOME TO HAVE
HIM STAND BY YOU OKAY? >> YOU WANTED TO STAND WITH ME
THEN WHY I DO THIS? OKAY.
>> AWESOME. MY NAME IS JUNEBUG AND I'M BORN
AND RAISED HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO.
>> OH, AND I SUPPORT THE ASK OF THE HIV ADVOCACY NETWORK.
IT'S VERY CRITICAL THAT WE HAVE FUNDING FOR HIV PREVENTION.
WE NEED TO THINK OF THE GENERATIONS THAT COME BEHIND US
TO MAKE SURE THAT THEY HAVE THE PREVENTION IN PLACE AND ACCESS
TO SERVICES. IT'S VITAL.
WE NEED TO BE ABLE TO SAVE SEX ADVOCACY WORK.
WE NEED TO BE ABLE TO SAVE HARM REDUCTION.
>> AND CURRENTLY RIGHT NOW I'M WORKING WITH TRANSITIONAL ADULT
YOUTH AT THE GLIDE SOCIAL JUSTICE ACADEMY WITH THE TAY
FELLOWSHIP. AND I JUST WANT TO SAY THAT
SAVING THESE TWO YOUTH CLINICS IN SAN FRANCISCO ARE SUPER
VITAL AS WELL. I KNOW THAT WHEN I WAS A
YOUNGSTER HERE IN SAN FRANCISCO, THE HUCKLEBERRY
STREET CLINIC HELPED SAVE MY LIFE.
AND I JUST WANT US TO THINK ABOUT NOT JUST OUR ELDERS
BEFORE US BUT THINK OF THE YOUTH BEHIND US.
>> THANK YOU. AND THIS IS ONE OF THE YOUTH
BEHIND US. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS,
JUNEBUG. >> HELLO EVERYONE.
MY NAME IS ERIC. I AM WITH THE SOCIAL JUSTICE
ACADEMY AT GLIDE TRANSITIONAL H YOUTH COHORT.
>> UM. >> FIRSTLY I WOULD LIKE TO
CONGRATULATE MADAME SUPERVISOR CONNIE CHAN ON HER WIN ON THE
PRIMARIES. I WAS ONE OF THE PERSONS WHO
WORKED WITH THE UAW. >> YOU HAVE SIR.
PLEASE CURB YOUR COMMENTS TO THE SUBJECT MATTER BEFORE THIS
PUBLICATION. >> OKAY.
I JUST WANTED TO SAY I REALLY LUCKY TO HAVE BEEN ABLE TO UM
TAKE IN BENEFITS FROM THE LGBTQ SERVICES HERE IN THE CITY AS
WELL AS HARM REDUCTION. I HAVE HAD PERSONAL FRIENDS WHO
HAVE PASSED AWAY FROM THINGS SUCH AS LIKE OVERDOSE AND I
THINK PEOPLE, IMMIGRANT PEOPLE AND UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE WE ARE
THE PEOPLE WHO MAKE THIS CITY BEAUTIFUL AND WE REALLY
APPRECIATE IF YOU GUYS COULD SUPPORT US.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT.
LET'S HEAR FROM OUR NEXT SPEAKER.
>> PLEASE WELCOME. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS THE RESCUE. I'VE BEEN A RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO FOR THREE YEARS, 23 OF THOSE WITH HIV.
I LIVE IN DISTRICT SIX. >> I WOULD NOT BE HERE TODAY
WITHOUT THE SERVICES THAT ARE PROVIDED BY MANY AGENCIES THAT
OPERATE IN THE CITY CATERING TO PEOPLE WITH HIV AND AIDS.
>> SOME OF THE SERVICES THAT ARE AVAILABLE OVER THE LAST 20
YEARS HAVE INCLUDED MENTAL HEALTH THROUGH ALLIANCE HEALTH
PROJECT AND NEW LIFE SERVICES HARM REDUCTION FOR SUBSTANCE
USE INCLUDING STONEWALL PROJECT OFFERED BY THE SAN FRANCISCO
INSTALLATION. QUALITY OF LIFE SERVICES
OFFERED BY THE SHANTI PROJECT AND JOB SEARCH SERVICES OFFERED
BY THE LGBT COMMUNITY CENTER AS WELL AS PRC TO NAME A FEW.
>> SAN FRANCISCO HAS BEEN A MODEL NATIONALLY
AND INTERNATIONALLY FOR HIV, AIDS AND LGBT SERVICES AND AS
THESE ARE BEING RAISED IN DC, I HOPE THAT SAN FRANCISCO STAND
FIRM AND NOT SUCCUMB TO THE PRESSURE AND CONTINUE OFFERING
SERVICES FOR PEOPLE WITH HIV AIDS AND LGBT BOOKS.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU.
THE BEST OUTCOME FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> HELLO.
MY NAME IS GEORGE ROY TAN. THANK YOU FOR THE CHANCE TO
SPEAK TODAY. I AM A GAY AND TRANSGENDER MALE
TRANSITIONAL AGED YOUTH BORN AND RAISED IN SAN FRANCISCO.
AND WITHOUT THE SERVICES OF HUCKLEBERRY THERE IS A CHANCE I
WOULD NOT BE STANDING HERE TODAY.
THERE IS NOT A CHANCE THERE'S A CERTAINTY THAT WITHOUT THE
SERVICES OF HUCKLEBERRY AND THE LURGAN STREET CLINIC THAT AT
LEAST FIVE OF MY VERY CLOSE FRIENDS WOULD NOT BE ALIVE OR
HOUSED TODAY. I STAND HERE BEFORE YOU TELLING
YOU THAT THE CUTS PROPOSED BY MARY LAURIE AND THE BOARD OF
SUPERVISORS TARGETED SPECIFICALLY VULNERABLE
COMMUNITIES. THE PEOPLE WHO ARE SUFFERING
ARE THE ELDERLY, THE UNHOUSED, THE CHRONICALLY ILL
AND DISABLED AND THE YOUTH OF TOMORROW.
IF YOU WANT A SAFE SAN FRANCISCO, IF YOU WANT A CLEAN
SAN FRANCISCO, IF YOU WANT A SAN FRANCISCO THAT TAKES CARE
OF ITS CITIZENS THEN YOU WILL NOT PASS THIS BUDGET AS IT AS
NOW. >> IF YOU THINK THAT YOU DON'T
HAVE A STAKE IN THIS IF YOU ARE NOT AT RISK FROM THESE SERVICES
BEING CUT, I CAN GUARANTEE YOU THAT SOMEONE YOU LOVE IS
AND THAT YOU WILL BE SOON. I HAVE SO MUCH MORE THAT I WANT
TO SAY BUT MANY MANY PEOPLE WHO ARE ALSO HERE IN PROTEST HAVE
SAID IT FOR ME AND I JUST WANT TO THANK JUST EVERYONE HERE FOR
TURNING OUT AND FOR SAYING THEIR PIECE SAN FRANCISCO.
PLEASE TAKE CARE OF YOUR OWN. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, GEORGE WRIGHT FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. I'M SORRY ABOUT THAT.
>> HELLO BOARD. MY NAME IS JUSTICE DOOM LAO.
I HAVE BEEN LIVING WITH HIV FOR EIGHT YEARS NOW AND WORK AT THE
SAN FRANCISCO AIDS FOUNDATION. I'LL BE READING AN EXCERPT FROM
MY LIVING OBITUARY TO REALLY MAKE CLEAR WHAT POLICY
DECISIONS CAN DO TO OUR COMMUNITY MEMBERS.
THESE LOCAL CUTS STUNG LIKE A STAB IN THE BACK A BETRAYAL TO
THE LEGACY CREATED ON THESE VERY STREETS BY HIV LONG-TERM
SURVIVORS WHO BUILT OUR CURRENT HEALTH CARE SYSTEM SAFETY NETS
AND LIFELINES CUT AS IF THAT WAS THE ONLY SOLUTION TO
BALANCE THE BUDGET ON THE BACKS OF OUR COMMUNITY.
LIKE IT WOULD HAVE NO CONSEQUENCES FOR JUSTICE.
THE CONSEQUENCES BECAME ALL TOO REAL.
JUSTICE DIED NOT BECAUSE SCIENCE FAILED TO CREATE
TREATMENT BUT BECAUSE ACCESS TO THAT TREATMENT AND A SAFETY NET
MEANT TO CATCH HIM WAS WITHERED AWAY BY POLICY DECISIONS MASKED
AS COST SAVING MEASURES. $3.4 MILLION CUT FROM OUR
SOCIAL SAFETY NET ON THE LOCAL LEVEL.
>> CUTS TO HEALTH ACCESS POINTS ALL ACROSS SAN FRANCISCO
SERVING MARGINALIZED COMMUNITIES LIKE STRUTS LIKE
GRAFFITI COALITION. MOU HAP.
>> CUTS TO OUR HOUSING OPPORTUNITIES FOR PERSONS WITH
AIDS OR HOPE FOR PREVENTING THE EXPANSION OF THE PROGRAM CUTS
TO LIFE SAVING LOW BARRIER EVIDENCE BASED HARM REDUCTION
SERVICES BUT EXTRA FOR THE SHAMEFUL SHERIFF RON RESET
CENTER. DESPITE JUSTICE HAVING LIVED A
HEALTHY LIFE WITH HIV AND BEING UNDETECTABLE FOR NEARLY EIGHT
YEARS, THE DECISIONS MADE BY BOTH NATIONAL AND CITY LEADERS
ENSURED THAT JUSTICE WOULD NEVER GET TO CELEBRATE LONG
TERM HIV SURVIVOR DAY FOR HIMSELF.
JUSTICE IS LIFE SERVES A REMINDER TO ALL OF US THAT
POLICY DECISIONS CANNOT BE NEUTRAL AND THAT COST SAVING
MEASURES LEAD TO QUIET DEATHS SENTENCES ALL AROUND THIS CITY.
>> JUSTICE LEAVES US WITH A CALL TO ACTION TO KEEP FIGHTING
FOR HIS NAMESAKE THAT TRUE JUSTICE WILL NEVER DIE SO LONG
AS WE ARE HERE TO HOLD THE TORCH, TO HONOR OUR HISTORY SO
THAT WE ARE NOT DOOMED TO REPEAT IT AND TO CREATE A
COMMUNITY THAT CARES FOR EVERY SINGLE PERSON AND LOUDLY SPEAK
TRUTH TO POWER. >> THANK YOU, JUSTICE DON LEMON
FOR YOUR COMMENTS. >> GLAD YOU'RE ALIVE.
>> WE ARE LETTING A PANEL SET UP TO DO.
>> SHE HAS A QUESTION FOR ALL OF YOU AND THAT IS HOW MANY OF
YOU WANT TO BE OLDER AND THINK ABOUT YOURSELF AS AN OLDER
PERSON WITH HEALTH ISSUES, MENTAL HEALTH ISSUES.
IF THIS GOES THROUGH THEN THE SAFETY NET FOR OLDER ADULTS
WILL NOT BE HERE FOR YOU. SHE WANTS YOU TO REALLY THINK
ABOUT THAT FACT BECAUSE THAT'S REALLY THE QUESTION AT HAND FOR
OUR LITTLE CLINIC TODAY. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR INTERPRETATION.
CURRENCY US VERSUS COMENTARIOS .
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. GOOD AFTERNOON SUPERVISORS MY
NAME IS CARRIED ALL I'M THE UNION REPRESENTATIVE WITH SEIU
10 TO 1 FOR THE NURSES IN THE AFFECTED THREE CLINICS THAT ARE
FACING CLOSURE DUE TO HIS MISMANAGEMENT.
>> I THINK THERE ARE A COUPLE OF THINGS THAT NEED TO BE
POINTED OUT HERE. THE FIRST ONE IS THAT THERE IS
NOT A CONTINUITY OF CARE THAT HAS BEEN SHARED WITH THE UNION
ABOUT WHAT IS GOING TO HAPPEN TO FOLKS UTILIZING THESE
CLINICS. THIS IS KEY TO US INSOFAR AS
THE CLINICS ARE BEING PLANNED TO MOVE YOUNG FOLKS INTO
IN HOSPITAL ALL PRIMARY CARE CLINICS IN THE TENDERLOIN
IN THE MAXINE HALL THAT ARE JUST NOT GOING TO BE APPLICABLE
TO THAT POPULATION. FURTHERMORE, TO INSINUATE THAT
GERIATRIC CLIENTS FROM SOUTHEAST GERIATRIC WOULD THEN
GO TO MISSION MENTAL HEALTH. IF YOU'VE BEEN TO THESE CLINICS
YOU KNOW THAT THAT IS JUST NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
AND SO WE'RE DEEPLY TROUBLED BY THE INATTENTION FROM MANAGEMENT
TO THIS CORE CONCERN. WE DO NOT ABIDE THE CUTTING OF
SOCIAL SERVICES IN SUCH A WAY THAT PEOPLE ARE JUST GOING TO
BE THROWN WITHOUT. SO WE URGE YOU TO RECONSIDER
DEVIATIONS, RECOMMENDATIONS HERE.
AND ONE MORE POINT IS SIMPLY THAT THE CLINICS ACROSS THE
BOARD ARE SUFFERING FROM HIGH RATES OF VACANCY IN A NUMBER OF
CLASSIFICATIONS MOST NOTABLY SOCIAL WORK.
THE CITY HAS GOT A CRISIS IN TERMS OF ITS ABILITY TO
MAGNETIZE TALENT TO COME TO WORK AND PROVIDE THE SERVICES
NECESSARY TO MAKE THIS CITY BOTH LIVABLE FOR PEOPLE THAT
ARE SUFFERING BUT ALSO FOR THE REST OF US OUT IN THE COMMUNITY
THAT ARE AMONG FOLKS THAT ARE SUFFERING SO I REALLY WOULD
LIKE TO SEE YOU ALL CALL IT MANAGEMENT AND REIN THEM IN AND
MAKE THEM ACCOUNTABLE FOR THEIR INABILITY TO STAFF UP AN
ADEQUATE LEVEL. >> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, KERRY DOYLE FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER SERVICES.
>> GOOD EVENING. MY NAME IS DEREK ARTHUR.
I AM A FIELD REP AT SEIU 10 TO 1 I REPRESENT OVER 1200 HEALTH
CARE WORKERS AT LAGUNA HONDA HOSPITAL.
I WAS PROVOKED TO SPEAK TODAY AFTER HEARING THAT DIRECTOR CI
TESTIFIED THAT OUT OF 8000 WORKERS WE ARE ONLY LOOKING AT
TWO EMPLOYEES LEFT SERVE THOSE TWO EMPLOYEES HAVE NAMES.
THEY ARE MARIA ELENA HEALY AND LORNA ROSE.
BOTH ARE CLINICAL NURSE SPECIALISTS AT LAGUNA HONDA.
>> THE DEPARTMENT HAS GUTTED THAT DEPARTMENT WITH PLANS TO
ELIMINATE THE ROLE OF CLINICAL NURSE SPECIALIST AT LAGUNA.
THIS DECISION WILL HAVE SEVERE NEGATIVE IMPACTS ON PATIENT
AND RESIDENT OUTCOMES AND IS ALSO GOING TO STYMIE THE VOICE
OF NURSES AT LAGUNA. BOTH OF THESE EMPLOYEES ARE
UNION LEADERS AND HAVE BEEN ACTIVELY OUTSPOKEN ABOUT OTHER
BAD DECISIONS THAT HAVE THE POTENTIAL TO PUT RESIDENTS AT
LAGUNA AT RISK, RAISING THE SPECTER THAT THEIR ELIMINATION
HAS BEEN TARGETED PROFESSIONALLY BOTH RETAIN
CERTIFICATION AND EXPERTISE THAT WILL OTHERWISE NOT EXIST
AT LAGUNA HONDA HOSPITAL, WHICH TO US SAYS THAT THEIR
ELIMINATION WHICH TO US SAYS THAT THROUGH THEIR ELIMINATION
THE DEPARTMENT BELIEVES THAT THE RESIDENTS OF LAGUNA DON'T
DESERVE THAT KIND OF CARE. MARIA ELENA HEALY IS A
CARDIOVASCULAR EXPERT CERTIFIED DIABETES EDUCATOR, EMERGENCY
MANAGER WHO PROVIDES EMERGENCY MANAGEMENT AT THE BEDSIDE.
LORNA IS A DEMENTIA DEMENTIA CARE WITH BEHAV DOES DEMENTIA
CARE WITH BEHAVIORAL CONSULTATIONS AND ADULT
GERONTOLOGY BY ELIMINATING THESE ROLES IS GAMBLING WITH
THE LIVES OF RESIDENTS SOMETHING THAT THE CITY IS
FAMILIAR WITH AND HAS PAID FOR WITH LIVES AND MONEY IS MAKING
BAD DECISIONS AND SENSELESS SERVICE REDUCTIONS.
>> THEY'RE TARGETING THESE THESE NURSES FOR LAYOFF AND WE
ARE ASKING THE BOARD TO ADD THOSE POSITIONS BACK.
>> THANK YOU ERIC ARTHUR FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> WE ASK THAT YOU HOLD YOUR
APPLAUSE PLEASE. THANK YOU.
>> WELCOME. HI, MY NAME IS KENDRA COMO
AND I AM A GAY TRANS MAN. >> I BELIEVE THE BUDGET FOR
2027 2020 IS $16.9 BILLION OR SORRY TWO BILLION OR MILLION.
>> I DON'T KNOW WHERE IS THAT MONEY GOING BECAUSE I THOUGHT
THAT WE ELECTED YOU GUYS INTO OFFICE SO THAT IMMIGRANTS TRANS
PEOPLE, PEOPLE IN GENERAL COULD BE SAFE.
>> I GREW UP IN THE CASTRO BEING TAUGHT THAT EVERYONE
DESERVES THE RESOURCES THEY NEED TO THRIVE NO MATTER YOUR
AGE, GENDER ORIENTATION OR RACE.
>> SO WHERE DID THAT GO? CUTTING HAM REDUCTION RESOURCES
IS THE EXACT OPPOSITE OF WHAT YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO DO.
WHAT WE WHAT YOU WERE ELECTED INTO OFFICE FOR I'VE BEEN
SEEING A LOT OF CUTS TO HARM REDUCTION PROGRAMS RECENTLY
AND A LOT MORE PEOPLE ASSIGNED TO CLEARING OUT UNHOUSED
INDIVIDUALS. >> S.F. PD IS LOOKING PRETTY
PADDED RIGHT NOW. >> REMEMBER YOUR MAIN SUPPORT
SYSTEM WILL NOT ALWAYS BE THE PEOPLE POURING MONEY INTO YOUR
CAMPAIGN BUT THE PEOPLE KEEPING SAN FRANCISCO ALIVE.
>> DON'T FORGET WHY SAN FRANCISCO IS THE CITY IT IS
IT'S BECAUSE OF THE PEOPLE CAST ASIDE AFTER BEING OUTED
IN WORLD WAR TWO THEY DECIDED TO OPT.
THEY OPTED TO STAY IN SAN FRANCISCO BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T
WANT TO FACE THE STIGMA OF GOING BACK HOME.
THAT IS WHY SAN FRANCISCO HAS GROWN INTO THE ROBUST COMMUNITY
THAT IT IS TODAY. >> WHY ARE WE HERE?
THE OPIATE THE MAYOR SAYS OPIOID USE AND HOMELESSNESS IS
THE PROBLEM. SO WHY ARE YOU TRYING TO CUT
FUNDING FOR THE PLACES FIGHTING THAT?
>> PARDON ME BUT NERVOUS. OKAY.
SORRY. >> WHEN YOU CUT RESOURCE
RESOURCES FOR LGBTQ YOUTH THE NUMBER OF HOMELESS PEOPLE YOU
HAVE TO CLEAR OUT OR DEAL WITH GETS BIGGER.
>> IT'S NOT DOING IT'S JUST DOING HARM.
>> DON'T PRETEND TO CARE ABOUT THE LIVES OF YOUNG PEOPLE
AND THE PEOPLE IN SAN FRANCISCO .
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS .
>> THANK YOU. THIS LOOKS LIKE THE LAST
SPEAKER IF THERE ARE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE PUBLIC WHO'D
LIKE TO SPEAK TO THE BALANCE IN HEARING THAT IS THE CUTS
THAT H IS PRESENTING THIS AFTERNOON TO THE BOARD FOR THIS
PUBLIC HEARING PLEASE COME OVER TO THE RIGHT HAND SIDE OF THE
CHAMBER OTHERWISE THIS MAY BE OUR LAST SPEAKER WELCOME.
>> HI, I'M ON YOUR WALL-E SEGMENT WITH THE SAN FRANCISCO
PEOPLE'S BUDGET COALITION AND SHARING FROM THE
PERSPECTIVE OF A YOUNG PERSON IN SAN FRANCISCO THAT WE FEEL
AS YOUNG PEOPLE. >> IT IS OUR JOB AND IT IS OUR
MORAL OBLIGATION TO UPHOLD THE GETTING TO ZERO PROMISE.
>> THAT IS WHY WE ARE HERE REGARDLESS OF WHETHER OR NOT WE
WERE THERE DURING THE HIV AND AIDS CRISIS.
WE CARRY THAT WITH US EVERY SINGLE DAY AND WE CONTINUE TO
FIGHT FOR IT. AND SO WHEN DEEPA OR THE
MAYOR'S ADMINISTRATION OFTEN TAKES CREDIT FOR 25 YEARS OF
FUNDING AND BACKFILLING HIV SERVICES AT NO POINT WAS IT HIS
DECISION OR LEADERSHIP THAT LED TO THAT.
IT HAS ALWAYS BEEN COMMUNITY WHO MADE THAT DECISION.
IT HAS ALWAYS BEEN COMMUNITY BEGGING FOR THE CITY TO TAKE
NOTICE AND SO IT IS COMMUNITY WHO WE NEED TO LISTEN TO
IN THIS COMMUNITY WHO DESERVES THE CREDIT FOR THE YEARS
AND YEARS OF FUNDING THAT WE HAVE BEEN GIVING TO HIV.
AND YOU HAVE TO RECKON WITH THE FACT THAT THESE CUTS ARE
SENDING A MESSAGE AND THEY ARE SENDING A VERY CLEAR ONE THAT
IS STRIKING RIGHT AT THE CORE OF WHAT IT MEANS TO BE IN SAN
FRANCISCO. >> IT IS TELLING US A VERY
CLEAR MESSAGE OF WHEN TIMES ARE HARD IT WILL BE YOU.
YOU WILL BE THE FIRST TO GO. WE ARE IN THE FIRST COUPLE OF
YEARS OF THIS BUDGET CRISIS AND ALREADY YOU ARE CUTTING
SERVICES THAT OUR LEADERS AND OUR ELDERS ARE SAYING ARE
ESSENTIAL. >> WE HAVE NO CHOICE BUT TO
LOOK AT YOUR ACTIONS AND TO JUDGE YOU BY THEM AND IN YEARS
LIKE THIS YOU WILL BE JUDGED BY YOUR BUDGET CUTS.
>> WE WILL WEIGH THEM AGAINST YOU ALL OF YOUR CAMPAIGN
PROMISES, ALL OF YOUR PLATFORMS, ALL OF IT COMES DOWN
TO MOMENTS LIKE THESE AND IT'S NOT EASY AND IT'S CERTAINLY A
BIG CHALLENGE. >> BUT THAT IS YOUR
RESPONSIBILITY AS ELECTED OFFICIALS WE WILL HOLD EVERY
CUT AGAINST YOU BECAUSE WHAT ELSE CAN WE DO?
>> WE DO NOT HAVE YOUR POWER. YOU HAVE THAT POWER AND YOU
HAVE TO USE IT TO PROTECT PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU. THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW CLOSED ON NO MORE PUBLIC MR. RIGHT THIS
ISN'T GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT. >> THIS IS JUST SPECIFIC TO THE
MEDICAL HEALTH CARE CUTS. >> THIS IS WHAT I'M GOING TO
TALK ABOUT. >> OKAY?
OKAY. MEDICAL CUTS NO MEDICAL CUTS
BECAUSE OF THE MOLD TYPE BILLION DOLLAR NEGATIVE CASH
FLOW IS YOUR OWN FAULT WHEN YOU LET PEOPLE WHO ARE NOT ELIGIBLE
FOR THE MEDICAL INSURANCE PROGRAMS THAT THE CITY PROVIDES
AND YOU TAP INTO THE FEDERAL INSURANCE COMPANY PROGRAMS
CORPORATIONS, UNITED STATES MEDICAL PROGRAMS AND AS A
RESULT YEAH PEOPLE THAT'S NOT ELIGIBLE AND YOU OVERLOADED THE
PROGRAM AND NOW YOU HAVE A MULTI MILLION BILLION DOLLAR
NEGATIVE CASH FLOW AND YOU DO THIS ALL THE TIME NOT ONLY
IN THE MEDICAL INSURANCE BUT EVERY ASPECT OF THE CITY.
AND THEN WHEN YOU TALLY UP THE MONEY AND YOU HAVE A
MULTIMILLION BILLION DOLLAR NEGATIVE CASH FLOW, YOU ALWAYS
WANT PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE A THING TO DO THE PROBLEM YOU
WANT THEM TO PAY FOR YOUR EFFORT.
IT'S NOT FAIR. >> IT'S A VIOLATION OF DUE
PROCESS AND CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS.
YOU'RE NOT SUPPOSED TO BE PUTTING PEOPLE THAT ARE NOT
CITIZENS FROM 192 DIFFERENT COUNTRIES SNEAK INTO THE UNITED
STATES AND GET MEDICAL INSURANCE AS IF THEY ARE BORN
AND RAISED IN OUR JURISDICTION. WE'RE NOT AND THEN YOU HAVE A
NEGATIVE CASH FLOW AND THEN AT THE END OF THE FISCAL YEAR WHEN
YOU ADD UP THE NUMBERS THEN YOU TURN AROUND AND HAVE A NEGATIVE
CASH FLOW AND YOU WANT OTHER PEOPLE THAT DON'T HAVE NOTHING
TO DO WITH THE PROBLEM TO PAY FOR IT IS UNFAIR,
UNCONSTITUTIONAL AND IT'S A VIOLATION OF THE AMERICAN
DISABILITIES ACT BECAUSE THESE AND WANT THOSE PEOPLE THAT WERE
BEING CUT NOT ONLY THE MEDICAL INSURANCE FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE
INFESTED WITH INFECTED WITH DISABILITIES SUCH AS HIV MENTAL
DISABILITIES ALL DISABILITIES HEART HIGH BLOOD PRESSURE
AND EVERY DAY YOU'RE VIOLATING AMERICAN DISABILITIES ACT TWO
IS A MISAPPROPRIATION OF FUNDS AND IF ANYBODY SHOULD BE PAYING
FOR IT, IT SHOULD BE YOU GUYS FAULT.
YOU SHOULD PAY FOR IT. >> THANK YOU MR. RIGHT FOR YOUR
COMMENTS. MR. WASHINGTON LET ME YOU KNOW
I'M TALKING ABOUT THAT AND I CAN COME SPEAK ON BUT LET ME
GET A LITTLE BIT ON IT. I'LL BEGIN THE TIME FOR THEM.
BUT RIGHT NOW THESE WHEN IT IS TRUE AND THIS IS TRUE BECAUSE
CITY AND COUNTY ALWAYS SAY WE GOT DEFICITS.
WE AIN'T GOT NO MONEY. YOU GOT MONEY, YOU GOT
DISCRETIONARY FUNDS YOU CAN USE YOU GOT EMERGENCY RESERVES.
SO I'M TRYING TO FIND OUT BECAUSE WELL THAT'S RUMOR TALK
ABOUT YOU SITTING CURRENTLY AIN'T GOT NO MONEY
PARTICULARLY WHEN IT COMES DOWN TO BLACK FOLKS.
BUT YOU GOT MONEY FOR EVERYBODY ELSE.
YOU GOT THIS KIND OF FUND THAT CAN FUND.
>> I WANT TO FIND OUT WHAT KIND OF MONEY YOU GOT.
MR. WHITE DISCRETIONAL FUNDS. >> MR. WASHINGTON THIS IS ABOUT
REDUCTION TO MEDICAL HEALTH SERVICES.
>> OH YEAH, BUT IT'S TALKING ABOUT DOLLARS THAT WAS OKAY.
AND WITH THAT, MR. PRESIDENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW REALLY CLOSED ON THIS ITEM AND SEE NO
OTHER NAMES ON THE ROSTER. THIS MATTER HAS BEEN HEARD
AND IS NOW FILED. >> MADAM CLERK, LET'S GO BACK
TO ROLL CALL. YES, WE LAST LEFT OFF WITH
PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN AND NOW WE'LL GO TO SUPERVISOR MELGAR
ROLL CALL FOR INTRODUCTIONS. >> I THINK WE GOT SUPERVISOR
OKAY OKAY THANK YOU SO MUCH THOUGHT FOR APOLOGIES
SUPERVISOR SAUTER SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHERYL SMITH
SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR WALTON SUBMIT THANK YOU
SUPERVISOR WONG SUBMIT THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHAN SUBMIT
THANK YOU. SUPERVISOR CHEN SUBMIT.
THANK YOU AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK. COLLEAGUES TODAY I AM
SUBMITTING A LEGISLATIVE DRAFTING REQUEST TO UPDATE
AND MODERNIZE SAN FRANCISCO'S TGA ANTHONY CATASTROPHIC
ILLNESS PROGRAM WHICH PROVIDES A LIFELINE FOR CITY EMPLOYEES
FACING SERIOUS MEDICAL CHALLENGES AFTER THEY HAVE
EXHAUSTED THEIR AVAILABLE LEAVE.
NAMED FOR T.J. ANTHONY, A LONGTIME CITY HALL STAFFER
AND LGBTQ PLUS ACTIVIST SOMEONE I ACTUALLY MET A FEW TIMES
IN THE EARLY 90S. T.J. PASSED AWAY FROM HODGKIN'S
DISEASE IN 1996 AT THE AGE OF JUST 37 AND THE PROGRAM THAT
STANDS AN ENDURING TRIBUTE TO HIS MEMORY ENABLES CITY
EMPLOYEES LIKE US TO DONATE OUR LEAVE TIME TO A GENERAL POOL
THAT HELPS OUR FELLOW CITY WORKERS REMAIN FINANCIALLY
STABLE DOING IT DURING EXTRAORDINARILY DIFFICULT
CIRCUMSTANCES. SO IT COMES AS NO ADDED WITH NO
ADDED COSTS TO CITY TAXPAYERS WHILE SUCCESSFULLY HAVING
HELPED HUNDREDS OF OUR FELLOW CITY WORKERS OVER THE YEARS TO
AVOID HARDSHIPS THEY MIGHT OTHERWISE HAVE BEEN FORCED TO
ENDURE. UNFORTUNATELY THE CURRENT
DEFINITION OF CATASTROPHIC ILLNESS ENSHRINED IN THE
RELEVANT PORTION OF OUR ADMINISTRATIVE CODE IS FAR
NARROWER THAN THE ONE USED BY THE STATE OF CALIFORNIA
AND MANY OTHER PUBLIC EMPLOYERS .
UNDER CURRENT LOCAL LAW AN EMPLOYEE MUST GENERALLY SUFFER
FROM A LIFE THREATENING ILLNESS OR INJURY TO QUALIFY.
AS A RESULT, EMPLOYEES WHO FACE SEVERE, DEBILITATING OR LIFE
ALTERING MEDICAL CONDITIONS ILLNESSES THAT ARE CATASTROPHIC
BY ANY RATIONAL DEFINITION OF THE TERM MAY BE EXCLUDED FROM
THIS WORTHY PROGRAM. ONE CASE THAT HAS BROUGHT
ATTENTION TO THIS ISSUE IS THAT OF SAN FRANCISCO POLICE
SERGEANT KEVIN BROOK. A LETTER IN 2020 FOR SERGEANT
BROOK. A LETTER WAS SERIOUSLY INJURED
IN THE LINE OF DUTY WHEN HE WAS STRUCK BY A FALLING TREE DURING
AN ATMOSPHERIC RIVER STORM. IN FACT, SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN
WHO WAS SERVING AS ACTING MAYOR AT THE TIME JOINED ME
IN VISITING S.F. GENERAL HOSPITAL TO EXPRESS OUR SUPPORT
TO SERGEANT BROOK A LETTER THAT HIS FAMILY AND COLLEAGUES
SERGEANT BROOK LEOTA IS NOW PARALYZED FROM THE CHEST DOWN
BUT HE CONTINUES TO WORK TOWARD RECOVERY DESPITE THE SEVERITY
OF HIS CONDITION. HE HAS APPLIED TO THE PROGRAM
TWICE BEEN DENIED TWICE AND HAS LOST TWO APPEALS.
WHILE SERGEANT BROOK ABOUT HIS EXPERIENCE CERTAINLY
HIGHLIGHTED THE SHORTCOMINGS OF THE CURRENT STANDARD, THIS
LEGISLATION IS NOT ABOUT ANY ONE INDIVIDUAL.
RATHER IT IS ABOUT ENSURING THAT THE PROGRAM WORKS AS
INTENDED FOR ALL CITY EMPLOYEES WHO FACE A CATASTROPHIC ILLNESS
OR INJURY THAT PREVENTS THEM FROM WORKING AND THAT CREATES
SIGNIFICANT FINANCIAL HARDSHIP. THE LEGISLATION I AM PROPOSING
WOULD BETTER ALIGN SAN FRANCISCO'S DEFINITION OF
CATASTROPHIC ILLNESS WITH CURRENT CALIFORNIA LAW BY
FOCUSING ON INCAPACITY EXTENDED ABSENCE FROM WORK AND THE
EXHAUSTION OF AVAILABLE LEAVE RATHER THAN REQUIRING THAT THE
CONDITION BE LIFE THREATENING. EMPLOYEES WOULD STILL NEED TO
PROVIDE MEDICAL DOCUMENTATION OR EXHAUST AVAILABLE PAID LEAVE
AND SATISFY ALL OF THE PROGRAM REQUIREMENTS.
THE EXISTING APPEAL PROCESS WOULD REMAIN UNCHANGED AT ITS
CORE. THIS PROGRAM RECOGNIZES THAT A
CATASTROPHIC MEDICAL CONDITION CAN BE DEVASTATING FOR AN
EMPLOYEE AND THEIR FAMILY EVEN WHEN IT IS NOT IMMEDIATELY LIFE
THREATENING. THIS LEGISLATION WOULD UPDATE
LOCAL LAW TO REFLECT THAT REALITY.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO WORK WITH THE CITY ATTORNEY'S
OFFICE AND TO COLLABORATING WITH THE DEPARTMENT OF HUMAN
RESOURCES, OUR LABOR PARTNERS AND OTHER STAKEHOLDERS
AND COLLEAGUES AS WE CRAFT THIS LEGISLATION MOVING FORWARD.
AND THE REST I SUBMIT. >> THANK YOU, SUPERVISOR
DORSEY. MR. PRESIDENT, SEEING NO NAMES
ON THE ROSTER, THAT CONCLUDES THE INTRODUCTION OF NEW
BUSINESS. >> LET'S GO TO GENERAL PUBLIC
COMMENT. >> ALL RIGHT.
FOR THOSE OF YOU STILL LEFT IN THE CHAMBER, IT IS NOW TIME
TO ADDRESS THE BOARD ON GENERAL MATTERS.
YOU MAY SPEAK TO THE MINUTES AS PRESENTED ITEMS 24 THROUGH 26
ON THE ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE REFERENCE CALENDAR OF
THE AGENDA AND OTHER GENERAL MATTERS NOT ON THE PUBLISHED
AGENDA. >> MR. RIGHT WE'RE SETTING THE
TIMER FOR TWO MINUTES AND YOU ARE UP SIR.
SUPERVISORS JUST SPOKE THAT PHILOSOPHY THAT YOU'RE USING
FOR PEOPLE IN HIGH INCOME BRACKETS IS THE SAME PHILOSOPHY
YOU SHOULD BE USING FOR THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE.
>> MR. RIGHT JUST KEEP YOUR COMMENTS TO THE BOARD AS A
WHOLE. YES, SIR.
THANK YOU. IS THE WHOLE BOARD ALL OF YOU
KNOW WHAT I CAN'T DO? >> I'M SPEAKING TO EVERYBODY.
EVERYBODY IS WATCHING ME USE THAT PHILOSOPHY FOR PEOPLE WHO
ARE MOST VULNERABLE WHO ARE HOMELESS OUT ON THE STREET YOU
REDUCE THE HOMELESS POPULATION AND REDUCE THE DRUG ADDICTION
PROBLEM. YOU SHOULD BE THE POSTER PERSON
TO ADVOCATE REHABILITATE OPTION FOR DRUG ADDICTS.
YOU WENT TO A REHABILITATION PROGRAM YOURSELF A TRUE
AND CORRECT REHABILITATION PROGRAM WHERE THEY DIDN'T LET
YOU USE CRACK COCAINE NO HEROIN ,NO SPEECH, CRYSTAL METH,
AMPHETAMINES AND DID NOT LET YOU DRINK NO ALCOHOL OR SMOKE
NO CIGARETS. BUT PEOPLE WHO ARE IN LOW
INCOME BRACKETS WHO ARE HOMELESS THE MOST YOU WANT TO
DO IS A SAFE INJECTION SITE AND THEN YOU SUPPLY THE
PARAPHERNALIA FOR THEM TO USE DRUGS ON THE TAXPAYERS MONEY ON
CITY FACILITIES TO A IN A BET DRUG REHABILITATION TO
COUNSELING AND SABOTAGE TO REHABILITATION.
AND THE PHILOSOPHY THAT THIS BOARD ATTENTION MR. DORSEY JUST
USE YOU SHOULD APPLY IT TO THE MOST VULNERABLE PEOPLE.
YOU ALWAYS CAMPAIGN WHEN YOU GET NEW JOB THAT YOU'RE GOING
TO TAKE CARE OF THE HOMELESS AND THE MOST VULNERABLE AS A
WHOLE. MR. RIGHT PLAN BOARD AS A WHOLE
DON'T USE YOU AS A WHOLE. >> I'M TALKING AS A WHOLE.
ALL OF YOU KNOW THAT I MADE THAT CLEAR.
IT'S DISGUSTING AND I WANT MY TIME BACK TOO.
AND BY THE SAME RESPONSE YOUR BUDGET CUTS PERTAINING TO
TEENAGERS AS HOMELESS IT'S UNCONSTITUTIONAL.
THOSE TEENAGERS DON'T HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH YOU $1.5
BILLION NEGATIVE CASH FLOW. >> SAME FOR THE SENIORS CITIZEN
PROGRAM. THEY DON'T HAVE NOTHING TO DO
WITH THAT BUDGET PROGRAM NEGATIVE CASH FLOW DEBT THAT'S
YOUR FAULT. >> THANK YOU MR. RIGHT WELCOME
TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. >> GOOD EVENING.
MY NAME IS BARRY PEARL. I'M A LIFELONG RESIDENT OF SAN
FRANCISCO. MY WIFE AND I ARE BOTH RETIRED
CITY EMPLOYEES AND WE WANT TO BRING TO YOUR ATTENTION
SOMETHING THAT WAS VERY UPSETTING TO US.
WE'RE BOTH COVERED UNDER MEDICARE AND THROUGH BLUE
SHIELD OF CALIFORNIA AND OVER THE LAST SEVERAL DAYS WE
RECEIVED MULTIPLE NOTICES ADVISING US OF AN UPDATE TO OUR
NETWORK AND WE WERE TOLD THAT OUR LONG TERM PRIMARY CARE
PHYSICIANS AND SPECIALISTS WERE NO LONGER COVERED BY THE
PROGRAM. WE CONTACTED THE HEALTH SERVICE
SYSTEM. THEY WERE UNAWARE OF THESE
NOTICES. WE IN TURN CONTACTED BLUE
SHIELD OF CALIFORNIA AND THEY INFORMED THAT THIS THAT THESE
NOTICES WERE ALL ISSUED IN ERROR AND THAT THEY WERE
ISSUED TO MORE THAN RETIRED SAN FRANCISCO EMPLOYEES.
THEY WERE ISSUED TO PEOPLE THROUGHOUT CALIFORNIA THAT
THESE NOTICES WERE ISSUED IN ERROR.
I RECOMMENDED THAT THIS BOARD CALL A BLUE SHIELD TO TESTIFY
BEFORE THIS BOARD TO FIND OUT WHAT WAS THE CAUSE OF THIS
ERROR AND HOW DO THEY PREVENT THIS IN THE FUTURE BECAUSE
THESE ARE PEOPLE THAT WE HAVE RELIED ON FOR MEDICAL CARE WITH
LONG TERM RELATIONSHIPS. MY WIFE HAS LONG TERM HEALTH
ISSUES SUCH AS DIABETES AND ULCERATIVE COLITIS SO THIS
IS A MAJOR DISASTER AND THE BOARD NEEDS TO INVESTIGATE
THIS. >> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU. MR. CARROLL.
DO YOU HAVE A COPY OF THAT LETTER THAT WE COULD ADD TO THE
FILE? I CAN WE CAN MAKE A COPY OF
YOUR ORIGINAL YES. >> THE ONLY THING IS THAT MY ID
NUMBER IS CAN YOU DO THAT? >> CERTAINLY.
OKAY. ARTHUR WILL TAKE CARE OF YOU.
HE'S COMING AROUND. THANK YOU, MR. WASHINGTON.
OKAY, BEFORE YOU GIVE ME MY TIME, I WANT THE SCREEN TO SHOW
WHAT I'M TALKING ABOUT ON THE FIRST MINUTE OF TV, PLEASE.
>> OKAY. SO THAT THERE IS A IT'S AN
ARTICLE FROM THE SAN FRANCISCO POST OFFICIAL IN SO I'M
STARTING YOUR TIME NOW. OKAY.
START MY TIME CAN I GET SOME ACTION ON WHAT I'M TALKING
ABOUT I SO GO TV PLEASE. YES BECAUSE IT'S NOT SHOWING
ANYWAY I'M HERE TO TALK ABOUT THE JUNE 18TH 19TH WESLEY
JOHNSON WHITE HORSE AWARD. THAT'S HAPPENING THIS FRIDAY
AND NOT EVEN UP THERE YET. SO I DON'T EVEN KNOW WHAT'S
HAPPENING. THE AWARDS IS GO CELEBRATE WITH
SHUG KNIGHT AND WILLIE BROWN JUNIOR DOCTOR AMOS BROWN
AND FORMER WASHINGTON. >> I'M PAUSING YOUR TIME.
OKAY, WE'RE CHECKING ON THAT PROJECTOR TO DETERMINE IF IT IS
IN FACT OKAY. >> PLEASE.
THANK YOU. I JUST THOUGHT THANK YOU.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH. THIS WEEK EVERY GO APOLOGIES
MR. WASHINGTON. >> APPRECIATE IT.
OH, THAT'S A GOOD THING. ALL RIGHT.
I'M GOING TO RESTART YOUR TIME. HERE WE GO.
>> OKAY. SO WITH THAT HERE IS A CROWN IS
THE SAN FRANCISCO POST STATING A JUNETEENTH CELEBRATION TO BE
HELD AT THE NEWLY REOPENED HERITAGE CENTERED.
DOGGONE IT, THE WHOLE CITY KNOWS ABOUT THIS THING AND I'M
HERE BEGGING THEM PLEASE AND SOME SOME SUPPORT FROM THE
CITY AND COUNTY THEY HELPED ME PULL THIS THING OFF.
>> AND EVERYWHERE I GO WE DON'T GET ENOUGH MONEY.
>> WE WHEN YOU GOT DISCRETIONARY FUNDS IT MAKES NO
SENSE. EVEN MY SUPERVISOR SAID WE
AIN'T GOT NO FUND. YOU GOT FUNDS?
THERE WAS THE HELL'S GOING ON HERE.
I'M BUSTING MY BUDDY. MY STAFF IS MAKING THIS THING
HAPPEN HISTORICALLY FOR THE JUNETEENTH MARCH THERE AND I
CAN'T GET A DIME AND I GOT PAPERS.
I'M MISSING OUT TO EVERYBODY ALL I NEED A FEW BUCKS.
SO ANYWAY, LET'S GO BACK TO WHAT'S THE OTHER THING I GOT AN
EMAIL THAT THERE IS A MEETING HAPPENING ON THE 21ST OR SECOND
AT LSU HUTCH CITY THE COUNTY IS DOING IT AND THEY TOLD ME
NOTHING WOULD THE ONLY THINK THEY'RE GOING ON TRYING TO DO
IT MY COMMUNITY SUPERVISOR YOU KNOW ABOUT IT YOU SAID YOU
DIDN'T YOU TOLD A FEW OF YOU KNOW ABOUT THIS BOARD AS A
WHOLE IS OH AS A WHOLE HE KNOWS ABOUT IT.
THE MAYOR KNOWS EVERYBODY KNOWS ABOUT I'M SICK AND TIRED OF
BEING SICK AND TIRED IN THIS CITY.
I'VE BEEN IN THIS BOARDROOM LONGER THAN EVERYBODY IN HERE
AND I'M TIRED. >> I NEED RESPECT.
I AM THE FILLMORE COURTROOM AMBASSADOR NOT THE.
ANYTHING THAT SHAKES YOU RATTLES AND ROLLS IN THE STILL
MORE NEEDS TO COME TO MY OFFICE.
THE SUPERVISOR YOU JUST BEEN THERE?
THE MAYOR JUST BEEN THERE A YEAR.
>> THEY DON'T KNOW A THING ABOUT WHAT'S GOING ON IN MY
COMMUNITY. >> YOU KNOW I'M SICK AND TIRED
OF IT NOW. I THOUGHT I WAS ME REAL JOB BE
ABLE TO SAY IT'S A FOUR LETTER WORDS ALL DAY LONG ONE OF YOU
YOU BECAUSE OF THAT JOB THIS BOARD DON'T KNOW NOTHING ABOUT
DEBT I'M 72 YEARS OLD AND I'M SICK AND TIRED OF TRYING TO
MAKE MY COMMUNITY AIN'T GOT NO HELP FROM THE SUPERVISORS.
THE MAYOR NOBODY MY NAME IS ACE AND I'M NEW PEOPLE HAPPY
WITH WITHOUT YOU. >> THANK YOU, MR. WASHINGTON.
WELCOME TO OUR NEXT SPEAKER. PLEASE.
OH, YOU THINK? >> AND GIVE ME A NAME.
EXCUSE ME. I'M NOT UPSET.
MY BLOOD PRESSURE IS UP. ALL RIGHT, NEXT SPEAKER, BOARD
PRESIDENT MAN, WOMAN AND BOARD MEMBERS AT A HALL ONCE AGAIN I
NOTICE THAT THE SEAT FOR DISTRICT NINE IS EMPTY AND I
REALLY HAVEN'T BEEN READING MUCH ABOUT IT IN THE PAPER.
NONE OF THE LOCAL NEWSPAPERS REALLY COMMENT ON AND MAYBE IS
THERE A BACKROOM DEAL THAT'S GOING ON WITH THE CAMPUS CREW
WHICH ESSENTIALLY HOLDS THE DISTRICT NINE AT THE MOMENT?
WHAT DOES THE MAYOR ARE DOING? BUT ANYWAY, I WANT TO THANK THE
PEOPLE THAT REALLY BROUGHT UP THE PROBLEMS OF OUR CLINICS.
I MEAN I'VE BEEN IN THE HAIGHT-ASHBURY FOREVER.
>> THAT IS NOT THE TOPIC OF THIS PORTION OF THE AGENDA.
>> WE ALREADY HAD THE MEDICAL SERVICES CUT JUST HALF WAY.
>> I ALL RIGHT. WELL I'M GOING TO JUST LEAVE
THANK YOU. >> ALL RIGHT.
WELL, THANK YOU FOR COMING TODAY.
>> I'M EXHAUSTED TO THIS MEETINGS GO ON.
>> YOUR ACADEMY AWARDS ARE RIDICULOUS IN THE SENSE THAT
NOBODY FROM DISTRICT NINE SEEMS TO BE REPRESENTED.
I THINK YOU'RE GOING IN IN THE WRONG WAY.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR COMMENTS. ALL RIGHT, MR. GAMBRELL, ARE
YOU COMING? WHO'S NEXT?
>> I'M HERE AGAIN. WELCOME.
LEAH. >> OKAY.
HELLO. I AM TRANS SPECIFICALLY
NONBINARY BISEXUAL AND I'M MARRIED TO A BRILLIANT,
BEAUTIFUL TRANS WOMAN. I WORKED FOR THE S.F. GIANTS
FOR A FEW MONTHS THIS YEAR. >> I GOT THE FREE HAT AS WELL
AND WAS ENJOYING IT UNTIL JOSHUA KUSHNER BOUGHT A STAKE
IN THE TEAM A CULTURAL ASSET. >> I QUIT FOR MORE MORAL
REASONS S.F. GIANTS PLAYERS LANDON, JT AND RYAN USED THE
GIANTS PRIDE GAME TO INVOKE THEIR RELIGION TO PROTEST THE
EXISTENCE OF LGBTQ KIDS AND ADULTS.
>> SHAME ON THEM SHAME ON THE OTHER GIANTS EMPLOYEE SAM FOR
DISRESPECTING THEIR AUDIENCE. >> OH SHAME ON THE GIANTS FOR
DISRESPECTING A STADIUM FULL OF PEOPLE CELEBRATING PRIDE WHOSE
ATTENDANCE AND PURCHASING OF GIANTS MERCHANDISE MAKES THEM
MONEY. >> HOPEFULLY FRIDAY WAS THEIR
LAST GAME AND PURCHASE THESE S.F. GIANTS PLAYERS THESE
EMPLOYEES THESE MEN JEWS CHOSE TO DO THIS WHEN 10% OF LGBTQ
PLUS YOUTH ATTEMPTED SUICIDE THIS PAST YEAR WHEN SUICIDE IS
THE SECOND LEADING CAUSE OF DEATH AMONG LGBTQ PLUS KIDS AGE
10 TO 14, ONE IS THE THIRD LEADING CAUSE AMONGST LGBTQ
PLUS YOUTH AGES 15 TO 24 WHEN LGBTQ PLUS YOUTH ARE FOUR TIMES
MORE LIKELY THAN THEIR PEERS TO ATTEMPT SUICIDE FOR SHAME
THESE MEN DID THIS TO KIDS IN THE NAME OF GOD.
>> THEY DID THIS IN THE NAME OF A MAN WHO PREACHED THE LOVE THY
NEIGHBOR. >> THEIR STUNTS CONTRIBUTED TO
THE TOXIC ENVIRONMENT THAT MAKES KIDS FEEL ALIENATED
AND ASHAMED MAKING THEM WANT TO KILL THEMSELVES.
SHAME ON THESE MEN. SHAME ON THE OWNERS AND SHAME
ON LARRY BEAR SOME LEADERSHIP, SOME CULTURE.
>> WHAT A LOSER ASSET PERFECT FOR YOUR BILLIONAIRE
STAKEHOLDERS. >> IS THAT WHAT BEING A MAN IS
TO YOU ALL BULLYING KIDS TO DEATH ON WHAT TURNED OUT TO BE
MY LAST GAME BEFORE I QUIT I ACTUALLY CRIED DURING THE
NATIONAL ANTHEM BUT I CRIED WHEN I HEARD THE LINE.
>> LAND OF THE FREE BECAUSE I DID NOT FEEL FREE AT ALL.
>> THANK YOU LIAM MCKEEVER FOR YOUR COMMENTS.
>> MR. GAMBRELL GIDEON LADIES MANDELMAN OF THE BOARD I WAS
IN HERE LAST WEEK. I WANT TO APOLOGIZE TO YOUR I
HAD AN ATTITUDE WHEN I CAME THE FIRE YOUR SUPPORT I NEED YOUR
SUPPORT VERY DEARLY. I LIVE IN 11 NINE IN MISSION
STREET AND I WAS THERE FOR QUITE SOME TIME IN THE PAST.
WHEN I COME TO YOUR WORK AND I HAD AN ATTITUDE AND I APOLOGIZE
AGAIN BUT THE SITUATION YOU GUYS ON ME RIGHT NOW I GOT A
THREE DAY CONVICTION NOTICE I HAVE TO REPORT HERE MY HAND
THAT TO TIME THE MAN WHO STAYED IN MY BUILDING TRIED TO RAPE MY
MY CHILDREN'S MOTHER PUT HER IN THE HALLWAY AND TO TELL ME
THAT HE DID IT. I TRY TO GET HELP FROM SOMEBODY
TO NOT LET THIS HAPPEN AGAIN. THE POLICE WAS CALLED HERE TACK
MY WOMAN AND CHILD TO RAPE JUST RESILIENTLY HE CAME TO MY DOOR
AND ME AND MY FAMILY WAS IN THE HOUSE SLEEPING AND I WALKED UP
BY MY DAUGHTER CRYING AND SAYING DADDY, DADDY,
SOMEBODY IS TRYING TO BREAK IN THE HOUSE.
SO WENT UP TO THE DOOR. I SEEN THAT GUY THE SAME GUY
WHO TRIED TO PULL MY WIFE DOWN AND RAPED TWICE.
SO AFTER HE STOPPED KNOCKING ON HER DOOR I GOT MY FAMILY
TOGETHER, LET THEM GET HIS STUFF AND I DIDN'T WANT A 20 OR
4 AND I'M HANDICAPPED NOW WITH BRACES ON MY LEG.
SO WE WALKED DOWN AND I GOT HIM OUT OF THE BUILDING TO SAFETY
GROUND AND I WENT IN OPPOSITE NON-MATERIAL SOMETHING
MANDELMAN I HAD A BASEBALL BAT WITH ME FOR MY FAMILY.
I WAS COMING DOWN 25 STAIRS. I DIDN'T KNOW WHAT WAS GOING TO
GO ON DOWN THE STAIRWAY BUT JUST SO THE PROPERTY MANAGER
INSTEAD AS YOU CALL THE POLICE WHEN THE MAN TRIED TO RAPE MY
WIFE THE FIRST TIME THEY DIDN'T DO ANYTHING.
BUT NOW THAT I HAD A BASEBALL BAT TRYING TO PROTECT ME AND MY
FAMILY, THEY STABBED ME WITH A THREE DAY NOTICE OF CONVICTION.
NOTICE FOR ME PROTECTING MY WIFE AND MY CHILDREN BUT THIS
MAN NOT TO RAPE MY CHILDREN AND NOT TO DO NOTHING TO ME NOW
I'M ON EARTH TO GET GETTING PUT OUT.
I WANT TO KNOW I APOLOGIZED FOR THE FIRST TIME I HAD ATTITUDE
BUT I'M NOT RIGHT NOW. THANK YOU, MR. GAMBRELL.
THANK YOU. >> I WILL COME AROUND AND SPEAK
TO YOU IN JUST ONE MOMENT. ARE THERE ANY OTHER MEMBERS OF
THE PUBLIC WHO WOULD LIKE TO ADDRESS THE BOARD DURING
GENERAL PUBLIC COMMENT? >> OKAY, MR. PRESIDENT, ALL
RIGHT. >> PUBLIC COMMENT IS NOW
CLOSED, MADAM CLERK, WE HAVE THE FOR ADOPTION COMMITTEE
REFERENCE AGENDA BUT I FEEL LIKE MOST OF THESE THESE ITEMS
REQUIRE A LITTLE ATTENTION. SO WHY DON'T YOU JUST CALL THEM
ONE BY ONE ITEM 24 TWO THROUGH 26 ITEM 24 WELL LET'S SAY ITEMS
24 THROUGH 26 WERE INTRODUCED FOR ADOPTION WITHOUT COMMITTEE
REFERENCE A UNANIMOUS VOTE IS REQUIRED FOR ADOPTION OF A
RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TODAY ANY MEMBER MAY REQUIRE A
RESOLUTION ON FIRST READING TO GO TO COMMITTEE ITEM 24 THIS IS
A RESOLUTION TO RECOGNIZE THE DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL'S ROLE
IN STRENGTHENING COMMUNITY AND GENERATIONAL BONDS THROUGH
CULTURAL CELEBRATION AND TO SUPPORT ASSEMBLY CONCURRENT
RESOLUTION 123 INTRODUCED BY ASSEMBLYMAN PHILLIP CHEN AND TO
RECOGNIZE JUNE 19TH, 2026 AS DWAN WU JIA DAY IN STATE OF
CALIFORNIA AND TO FURTHER DECLARE JUNE 19TH, 2026 AS
DRAGON BOAT FESTIVAL DAY IN THE CITY AND COUNTY SUPERVISOR CHEN
THANK YOU PRESENT AMENDMENTS I AM I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A
MOTION TO AMEND ITEM 24 FILE NUMBER 2606 EIGHT SUPPORTING
CALIFORNIA'S ASSEMBLY CONCURRENT RESOLUTION 123
DOGWOODS YET DRAGON BALL FESTIVAL DATE JUNE 19TH, 2026
TO MAKE MINOR CLERICAL CORRECTIONS ALL OF US HAVE
RECEIVED AT EVENTS COPIES OF THE PROPOSED IT AMENDMENTS.
THE AMENDMENTS ARE AS FOLLOWS PAGE ONE NINE NUMBER FIVE
CHANGE COMMA AND TO SEMICOLON AT PAGE ONE 917 CAPITALIZE F
IN FESTIVAL PAGE ONE LINE 18 WE MOVE ALSO PAGE ONE 921 CHANGE
IN TO DURING THE PAGE TWO LINE SEVEN AT THE PAGE TO NIGHT
NUMBER I CAPITALIZED IN FESTIVAL PAGE TWO 918
CAPITALIZED AS IN STATE PAGE TWO LINE 23 AT THE PAGE THREE
911 CHANGE DIRECT TO DIRECTS PAGE THREE NINE THIRD TEEN
CHANGE MY TO MONIQUE NEWMAN'S PAGE THREE 914 AT MEMBERS THANK
YOU THANK YOU SUPERVISOR CHEN IS THERE A SECOND FOR THIS
MOTION SECONDED BY CHAN CAN WE TAKE THAT MOTION WITHOUT
OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION THE THE RESOLUTION IS AMENDED
AND THEN CAN WE TAKE THE RESULT LET'S CALL THE ROLL ON THE ON
THE RESOLUTION ON ITEM 24 AS AMENDED SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD
MAHMOOD EYES SUPERVISOR RANDLEMAN HI GENTLEMEN I
SUPERVISOR MELGAR MELGAR I SUPERVISOR SADR SADR I
SUPERVISOR CHERYL CHERYL I SUPERVISOR WALTON ALL RIGHT
WALTON I SUPERVISOR WONG WONG I SUPERVISOR CHAN CHIN I
SUPERVISOR CHEN CHIN I AND SUPERVISOR DORSEY DORSEY
HIGH THERE ARE TEN EYES WITHOUT OBJECTION THE AMENDED
RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL I AM 25 ITEM
20 FIVE RESOLUTION TO CELEBRATE JUNETEENTH AS A DAY OF
REFLECTION, EMPOWERMENT AND COMMEMORATION OF BLACK
FREEDOM AND EXCELLENCE IN THE CITY AND COUNTY AND TO URGE ALL
SAN FRANCISCANS TO JOIN IN HONORING THIS IMPORTANT DAY
. >> SUPERVISOR WELL THANK YOU
PRESIDENT BENJAMIN I JUST WANTED TO SAY THANK YOU TO ALL
OF MY COLLEAGUES WHO CO-SPONSORED THIS RESOLUTION AS
YOU KNOW IN 2021 JUNETEENTH WAS MADE A FEDERAL HOLIDAY AND OF
COURSE THIS IS A TIME OF CELEBRATION.
WE ARE IN JUNETEENTH WEEK AND JUST APPRECIATE ALL OF THE
SUPPORT EVERY YEAR. THANK YOU.
SUPERVISOR MAHMOOD CO SPONSOR NOTED THANK YOU.
>> GREAT LET'S TAKE THIS ITEM SAME HOUSE SAME CALL WITHOUT
OBJECTION THE RESOLUTIONS ADOPTED MADAM CLERK PLEASE CALL
ITEM 26 ITEM 26 THIS IS A MOTION TO APPROVE A PHASED
FINAL MAP NUMBER 1268 ONE CANDLESTICK POINT MAJOR PHASE
TWO RELATING TO PORTIONS OF THE CANDLESTICK POINT HUNTERS POINT
SHIPYARD PHASE TWO PROJECT FOR CONDOMINIUM PURPOSES A MERGER
AND RE SUBDIVISION RESULTING IN A TOTAL OF 50 LOTS
CONSISTING OF 12 DEVELOPMENT LOTS 24 LOTS INTENDED FOR
PUBLIC RIGHT OF WAY USE AND 14 REMAINDER LOTS AND TO AUTHORIZE
UP TO 440 441 RESIDENTIAL CONDOMINIUM UNITS AND UP TO 15
COMMERCIAL CAM INDIAN CONDOMINIUM UNITS SUBJECT TO
SPECIFIED CONDITIONS AND TO APPROVE A PUBLIC IMPROVEMENT
AGREEMENT RELATED TO FINAL MAP NUMBER 12681 AND TO ADOPT THE
APPROPRIATE FINDINGS SUPERVISOR WALTON THANK YOU PRESIDENT MY
COLLEAGUES YOU HAVE ALL RECEIVED AN AMENDMENT FOR THIS
ITEM AND SO I WOULD LIKE TO MAKE A MOTION TO AMEND TO
REMOVE THE FINDINGS AND THE LONG TITLE ON PAGE ONE LINES
NINE TO LEVEL 11 REMOVING THE WORDS AND ADOPTING FINDINGS
PURSUANT TO THE GENERAL PLAN COMMA AND THE EIGHT PRIORITY
POLICIES OF PLANNING CO COMMA SECTION 101.1 PERIOD THERE'S
MOTION IS BEEN SECONDED BY SUPERVISOR CHAN AND COLLEAGUES
. CAN WE TAKE THE MOTION WITHOUT
OBJECTION WITHOUT OBJECTION THE RESOLUTION IS AMENDED.
AND THEN I THINK WE CAN TAKE THE AMENDED RESOLUTION SAME
HOUSE, SAME CALL. >> WITHOUT OBJECTION THE
AMENDED RESOLUTION IS ADOPTED APPROVED THAT IT'S A MOTION THE
WELL THE MOTION WAS APPROVED. THE MOTION WAS APPROVED.
SO WHAT I DID MADAM CLERK WELL, THE MOTION IS APPROVED.
>> OKAY. ALL RIGHT, MADAM CLERK, DO WE
HAVE ANY IMPERATIVE AGENDA ITEMS THERE ARE NONE TO REPORT.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, COULD YOU PLEASE READ THE IN MEMORIAM?
YES. TODAY'S MEETING WILL BE
ADJOURNED IN MEMORY OF THE FOLLOWING BELOVED INDIVIDUALS
ON BEHALF OF PRESIDENT RANDLEMAN FOR THE LATE MR.
MICHAEL FRANK RICE AND ON BEHALF OF SUPERVISOR MELGAR
AND SUPERVISOR CHEN FOR THE LATE MRS. PHOEBE LEE.
I THINK THAT BRINGS US TO THE END OF OUR AGENDA MADAM CLERK
DO WE HAVE ANY FURTHER BUSINESS BEFORE US TODAY?
>> THAT CONCLUDES OUR BUSINESS FOR TODAY.
>> THANK YOU, MADAM CLERK WE ARE ADJOURNED